- There are decades where nothing happens
and weeks where decades happen.
And we have seen decades of progress
happen in the last nine months.
If you're not recognizing the
gravity of the moment, that's
the delusion. That's the
psychosis. Who would not get
delirious if suddenly a genie
pops out of the bottle and says,
"You can have whatever you want.
Every feature you've ever
dreamed of in an operating
system, I can deliver them to you,
most of them in five minutes, a few in
20, and if we really go hog wild, it's
gonna take me two hours." I want
the fastest car breaking the speed
limits. I want the diver watch
that can go down the Mariana
Trench. I want the operating system
that can install in less than
60 seconds. One of the things I always
loved about race cars was when I
would stumble out of the car
absolutely smashed and barely able to
hold my head up, and I'd lay down
on the garage floor and just think,
"Holy fuck, I'm alive." The
Overton window does not open
itself. It opens one nudge at a
time by people risking a little.
A little reputation, a little pushback,
a little criticism, or maybe sometimes a
lot of reputation or a lot of criticism
or a lot of pushback. Creating
life with another human that you love
is literally the peak experience
of being on the planet.
- The following is a conversation
with David Heinemeier Hansson, also
known as DHH, creator of Ruby on Rails, CTO
of 37signals, creator of the new Omarchy
Linux operating system, best-selling
author, race car driver,
and one of the most outspoken
and prolific programmers
in the world. For the past
20-plus years, for him,
programming meant meticulously
handcrafting beautiful Ruby
code. But recently, since late 2025, DHH
has embraced the AI revolution and has
openly transformed himself
into, once again, one of the
most outspoken and prolific
agentic engineers, even
though he hates that term. So let's say
practitioners of whatever
programming is becoming where AI is
doing most of the actual programming
and the human steers the ship
with high-level design,
vision, and taste. Yes, it's
true. DHH is at times
controversial, but he's
always fearless, brilliant,
and fun to talk to. This was,
once again, an intense,
eye-opening, and wild
rollercoaster ride of a
conversation. This is a Lex Fridman
podcast. To support it, please check
out our sponsors in the description
where you can also find links to
contact me, ask questions, give
feedback, and so on. And now,
dear friends, here's DHH.
13 months ago, we sat down right
here to talk about programming,
and then everything changed.
At that time, you were
a bit skeptical about the
role of AI in the process of
programming, and then we went
through this rapid evolution
of agentic engineering. So, simple question
to start: How has your view on AI's
role in programming changed? Are you
excited? Are you terrified? Are you
on an emotional rollercoaster ride?
- I am incredibly excited.
- You've been talking about fun a lot.
- There is none of the existential threat.
That doesn't exist for me as an emotional
component. It is only there as an
intellectual component, and the
emotional component for me is
100% pure, unadulterated joy-
... and optimism and
amazement that we've made
computers do this. And I find it
so interesting that we talked
just 13 months ago because
it's like we talked in different
universes, different eras.
I love this quote. I think
it's Lenin. There are
decades where nothing happens
and weeks where decades happen.
And we have seen decades of progress
happen in the last nine months.
I mean, imagine you're there when
the Wright brothers take flight.
Yesterday, the New York Times would write,
"It's gonna be 10,000 years before we fly,"
and then the day after, we're
up in the skies, and just a
few years after that, there
were cross-Atlantic planes. The
whole world has completely
changed. What a blessing to be
there in that moment. If you zoom out and
look at all of human history, how many
humans got to live within the same epoch
that they were born in? They never saw that
complete change of the world
and of society. And to have
been blessed with two of those
feels just such a privilege.
I got to see the internet-
... from pre-internet to post-internet,
and then now pre-AI, post-AI.
What an amazing run. How fortunate.
- Yeah, but the thing is, this
feels like a thing that
happened faster than anything
else in human history.
- Correct.
- So I would say somewhere around
December, maybe late November-
- November 24.
- This is...
- That's the exact moment.
- You know, when they talk about when
one nation invades another in a world
war or something like this, it-- this is
how we talk about AI changing everything.
Yeah, the... And it really
just sh- shifted for many
great developers. It shifted
to where AI is doing some,
basic autocomplete, maybe writing 5, 10,
15, 20% of code to writing 80% of code.
- Or 100.
- Or 100, yeah, especially if it's
not a public-facing product.
- To me, that's why even when I look
back upon our conversation a year
ago, I don't actually have different
opinions. I have the same
opinions. A year ago, I did
not like the mode of AI we were
offered. It was the autocomplete mode,
or it was the AI chatbot
mode. Now, the chatbot
I actually liked, as we talked about.
Great tutor right from the get-go, great
way of looking things up on the internet,
not what was gonna replace me chiseling
code. But- ... then we get the agents.
And the agents start out being curiosities
for about five minutes, and then
they get amazing, and then they get,
"Oh my God, is this AGI?" And all
of that happened since last year,
even just within the last
nine months. We have
basically these few phases
here. We have AI in the
pre-agentic era. I was
excited about that, but it
was not fundamentally rewriting the
rules of the game for me. It was
not completely changing how I
worked. I was still chiseling
code, I just had a little
helper, a little sidekick-
... who could bounce ideas
off, and I could look up this
information online and so forth in a more efficient
way. It was just a more efficient way to do what I was
already doing, and it didn't change
the emotional connection I had to the
computer. Then we get to November
24th, 2025. Opus 4.5, to
me, was the dividing line,
where suddenly... I didn't even
try it on the 24th. I think I tried it on
the 26th. I give it a couple of tasks,
and I realize that the quality of
the output is uncannily close to
what I would've written. And I remember
just leaning back and thinking,
"What just happened?" "How did we
go from this autocomplete mess that
I was talking to you about
in the summer to this just a
few short months later? How did
we get both the increase in
intelligence and then also the increase in
usability?" This agent
harness question where
I don't know if Opus 4.5 was that
much smarter than Opus 4, which
is what we had in the
summer, but its ability to
instrument your computer, to use
tools, to check its own work,
to apply its intelligence in
such a way that you could
get real meaningful work out of it, was
completely different. And I think this is
then the big change that happens for almost anyone
who paid attention and started playing with
it over the Christmas break.
This is what I heard-
... from Shopify and other places
with lots of employees who
suddenly had a breather, suddenly had a couple
of weeks to lean back and just look at what
was going on, gave it a
try, and had the same
mind-blowing experience
that these agents were of
a different genre than what we had
before. And then what we get to is,
I'm already excited at this
point. Like, by December, I'm
already revisiting sort of all my priors-
... and going like, "Wow, if it
can do this, can it also do that?"
"Oh, yeah, it can." And again, Opus
4.5 now looks like a retarded model.
And this is the magic of this progress,
is you think you've reached something...
I remember thinking at the moment,
"If this is the last model we
get, I'll be set. I'll be happy."
I could live with Opus 4.5
for the next 20 years-
... and you would hear no complaints from
me because it was just so incredibly
amazing to see an agent do all this
work in the way that I wanted it
done. Because it was not just
about it being able to solve a
task, it was also that I could look at its
path there and go, "Yep.
Yep. Maybe not there,
but almost," and it would give you two
notes. You'll get to where I wanted
to go in the way I wanted to go
there. You could produce code I
wanted to merge. You could
produce code that actually looked
beautiful if it was written in
Ruby. Rust, different question. But
this ability for the agents to truly
become an extension of how I wanted to
work was very novel. But then we
wait just until early spring, and
suddenly we get sub-agents.
We get harnesses that
can subdivide the task, and
something that would take
Opus quite a while
suddenly took a fifth of
the time, a tenth of the time,
because it could get chopped up and
suddenly you got eight
sub-agents working for you.
But both of those two first
phases of the agentic age,
to me, still felt like I had
to drive. I could tell it what
I wanted, where to look for
it, and steer it a little bit
when it went off, and then we'll get
there, and I would go much faster.
But I had to be in the driver's seat.
I had to tell it what I wanted, and I
had to be the reviewer, the auditor
of what was coming out. And then
finally now, this summer, with Opus
5, Fable, and Sol, GPT Sol, and
to a lesser extent, some of
the open weight models, we've
arrived at a new era where I'm
not telling it where we're
going. I'm telling it the problem
I have. I'm telling it the fuzzy,
vague idea I have. It tells
me where we're going.
It tells me which path to take,
and I will still look at it
because I'm a curious person and I like
computers and I like the outcome of it,
but I really kinda don't have to.
I've become optional in the part that
produces the code that picks the route.
Remember when early GPS systems came out?
They were amazing compared to looking
at a map, but you still wanted to pay
attention. Is it gonna drive you in
the harbor? I remember these newspaper
articles. "Ah, GPS, they're terrible because
people don't pay attention, they drive in the
harbor." When was the last time GPS drove anyone
in the harbor? Like, that just doesn't happen
anymore. In fact, the cars now just drive
themselves, right? And this is where
we've arrived at now, that I can trust.
For the domain I'm working in
right now, I can trust it,
and feel completely confident
that it's gonna have my
back. It's not gonna do something stupid, and
if it does something stupid, it's gonna be
able to recover.
- Mm-hmm. We should mention that
there's all kinds of domains that-
- Correct
- ... programmers operate in. There's...
I actually don't know, but
I think the most common
domain in development is, like,
web dev CRUD. You have a database.
You have a user-facing interface, and
it does something back and forth,
and it could be internal to just
one person, to multiple people,
to a small number of people, or to
the world. And I think for that,
it's-- I mean, you could
really get to the 100% of
code written by AI and
really if you're a good
programmer and you have a good intuition
about what's happening behind the scenes,
you can legitimately not look at
the code, at least that's, that's
been my experience. I don't know how much,
prior experience with programming
you need to have to kinda
know that things are working correctly
behind the scenes, like intuitively
by observing the ripple effects,
the symptoms of the system. But I
think for that domain, it's close to 100%,
and then there's domains like you're
also operating in, which is writing a
Linux distribution. There, maybe there's
more because you're obsessed
with speed and all that kind of
stuff. There, maybe you need to look at the code
a little bit more. Then there's maybe safety
critical systems all the way down
to operating a nuclear power
plant or a self-driving car. Maybe you
need to look at the code more carefully.
- Yes, but that said, AI is insanely
capable at both finding- ... and fixing
security vulnerabilities. This was the
whole blowup about Fable. This model was
so capable of finding holes that a
an attacker could exploit that it
was simply not safe to release.
So the irony here is that when
you look at that field, it
seems like we've reached
levels of intelligence that
virtually no human can match because
many of these security holes are
about stringing combo moves together.
You find one little
vulnerability here that by itself might not
be the worst thing in the world, but then you
combine it with four others, and suddenly
you have RCE, remote command execution.
Humans who are able to do
that are very rare. They
usually work inside state-sponsored
organizations or other clandestine operations.
They're not just out and
about finding things.
So they've gotten so good at
that. The Linux distribution
is why I've gotten 100% AI pilled. Because
I've been working on Omarchy for the last
three months, this version that just
dropped a few days ago called Quatro.
And almost right from the beginning
I'm working on that version,
the agent acceleration
neared 100%, and in the last
two months it has been
100%. I have not written-
- Really?
- ... any of the code that's shipped in
Quatro by hand. I've reviewed the shape
of all of it.
I've reviewed the individual lines of
anything that's critical in the model
layer of the system, and I've not
looked at a bunch of the UI code.
I have not looked at a bunch
of the auxiliary code, and
I've not written any of the new
functionality entirely by hand. But then
the web part, actually
evolving Basecamp and Hey, our
professional products that have lots
of users and are relatively large code
bases, have proven surprisingly tricky
to fully accelerate with
agents. We just released
Basecamp 5 not too long
ago. That was the first
product at 37signals that was
really agent accelerated.
Because we were in this final
sprint phase from around
February. By then, agents
were already good.
And we had this early surge of,
"It's solved. We can just have the
designers do the programming. They know what
features they want. They know what shape
they want it to take. Let's just--
Let them vibe." And we let them vibe.
And we ended up with a lot of PRs that
individually perhaps could have been
justified for a hot moment,
taken all together,
destroyed the architecture of the system.
And we actually had to clean
up manually, mop it up by
hand, by human hand, to get
back to an architecture that
felt cohesive and coherent. So we still
have a bit of that-- that was February, by
the way. Things are quite different now.
- Well, hold on a second. What's the lesson from that?
Is one of the lessons from that that you have to be
a programmer at this stage
to be able to vibe code?
- To be able to vibe code
on existing substantial
- I see.
- ... code bases, even if
they're crud, if you wanna
retain the element of architecture
that got that system to where it was.
Now, that's also a point
where I've stressed many
times that when people
accuse vibe coders of
being slob generators, I go right
back at them and say, "Have you
looked at the average programmer's
output?" That is some
other slob too. If you've looked
at behind the scenes of many
great companies and what their
code bases look like after there's
been 3,000 humans through them,
they're awful. Absolutely awful.
- Can you tell me the intuition you have?
I seem to just, stepping back and observing
the different apps that we all rely
on, I don't know, Adobe Photoshop, all
this kind of stuff. There seems to be the
progress on development
there has not accelerated.
So why is it, what lessons can
you draw from Basecamp, like
well-established, huge user base?
Why aren't we seeing, like,
super rapid increase in, like,
new updates, features, all this kind of
stuff in these well-established apps?
- Multiple reasons. I'll start with the
first one that's the most critical. As
soon as you're having human
teams work together on
something, the bottleneck is rarely
implementation. It's human
bandwidth and communication.
When you have a product manager and a couple
of designers and a VP above them and a
CTO above them, and
everyone wants to be part
of the shaping process because we're
all justifying why we're here,
that's where all the productivity goes to
die. The revelation I've had working on
Omarchy the last three months is
that to get that magical 10X,
100X, in a few rare cases, 1000X
productivity boost, you have
to interact with the agents directly,
and you cannot intermediate that
bandwidth with another human
because it's simply too slow.
And on the one hand, that's a
bit of a bummer. I mean, I like
humans, and it's great to work together.
But it also means we need to temper
our expectations with what
these agents can do if
it's humans driving it, and you have
three layers of approval and all the
other machinery of a large corporation.
The implementation part is only a small
segment of it. The other thing I'd say is
that most organizations don't know what
they want. They don't know how
to make it better. They're not
bottlenecked on implementation.
They're bottlenecked on
ideas. They're bottlenecked on
vision. They're bottlenecked on
taste. And if you don't have those element
in excess of your
implementational capacity,
it doesn't help. So you can make a lot
of shitty ideas come true, then what?
Are you gonna ship that?
That sounds like, I don't know, something coming
out of Microsoft. That's not what we're trying to
replicate here. That process is not
actually... Because we already had
this. If you step back
for a moment and think of
the towering organizations
we have who have had tens of
thousands of programmers
at their disposal.
I mean, I'm picking on Microsoft here. I love
Microsoft some of the time, but I'll pick on
them in this case because they have
had endless resources, endless
programming capacity for
decades, right? This is what's
showing us that just being able
to write a lot of code does not
produce great compelling
software. Now, the other thing is
we've had this capacity for about six
months. That's not very long in human
life cycle capacity of
internalizing what's going on.
And I think it's actually funny
that the critique of AI is,
why isn't it going faster?
What are you talking about? We've not had any
other form of progress that has moved as fast
as AI, and you're impatient because
in the last three months we haven't
rewritten the whole world and made
it a utopia of software goodness?
- You're basically saying everybody should be
switching to Linux now. One of the arguments is,
like, we can rewrite all the software
that's not available in Linux in Linux.
Linux has been the love of my life for many years, but
one of the reasons I'm still attached to Windows and
now, uh, Mac is because of
video editing, Premiere.
- We're gonna fix that. But-
- So the question is, who's
gonna build Premiere
and Photoshop for Linux? And it
feels like one person can now.
- 100% one person can.
- And so, and I'm allowed to be
impatient. In fact, me or anyone else,
impatience is the first step of
doing it yourself, right? Like-
- Correct.
- ... and there's a community of tens
of thousands of people that use Adobe
Premiere or DaVinci, all these
non-linear video editors, that
know the frustrations. Everybody shares them.
You can look at Reddit. You can look at
the forums. Everybody knows it. Uh, I
don't know what it is. It may be the
management. It may be the meetings. All
the things you've always discussed is the,
The bureaucracy that's inside
companies that's slowing
everything down in the development
of features. But it feels like
there-- if you just let some of the
developers loose with a bunch of agents,
you can fix all that. But again,
based on everything you're saying,
maybe the way to do that is to start
over from scratch, maybe through open
source, or somebody launches
a new company that within
large companies now it's hard to,
to really accelerate into the agentic
era by letting developers just build.
- This is the classic innovator's dilemma.
These companies have gotten so good,
so established at the old way,
and therefore their entire
structure, management layers, processes are
tuned for a time that no longer exists.
But you can't pivot that.
These are super tankers. It
just doesn't happen. This is why
we're finally getting this upset
in the technology industry.
For a while, I was very
upset about the duopoly
between Apple and Google on mobile,
because it felt like mobile was the most
important computing platform
that we had, and I could not see
a path to unseat either Google or Apple
sitting on top of that, controlling
everything, taking their toll booth money.
But the game has changed. This
is no longer the most important
platform. Mobile phones are
important, but there's also a lot of
other form factors coming,
whether it's glasses or it's
earpieces or whatever else have you.
It's all in play now, but
the computing platforms
themselves are in play
for the first time in
probably 40 years, if you look at the
desktop. Linux has been around since '91.
It's not taken off or taken
over on the desktop. It's taken
over everything else. All the
devices you have on your desk, your
fridge, your toaster,
everything runs Linux,
except for your computer. Now, funnily
enough, your Android is actually Linux, but
wrapped so sufficiently that
you can't really recognize
it. But now there's an
opening, and the opening
is exactly as you say it. If
there's a piece of software you
depended on that bound you to Windows,
it is completely within reach for
you personally to start rewriting
it. And maybe you won't get to
100% coverage, but this is the
old joke about Microsoft Office.
"I only use 5%." Yeah, well,
we all use a different 5%.
Well, what if we all
just build our own 5%?
What if I just took the functionality
that I need and just did
that? That is a completely
different challenge and
one agents are incredibly
capable of doing right now,
today, and I've done it a lot
of times over. So one of the
amazing things I've found with the
latest agent engaged is I have
become a polyglot programmer, something I
was absolutely not before. I was a Ruby
programmer-- ... first and foremost, and
then I dabbled a little bit in Bash--
... when I had to. And in
the last two months, I've
written C++. I've written
three applications that have
shipped in Omarchy Quattro. I wrote a
writing app. I was using this app called
Typora, which is a very nice app-
- Great, great app
- ... which in itself is based on another
app called iA Writer, which was my real
love on the Mac- ... for
a clean, simple Markdown
writing environment. That's
where I write all my essays.
And then I moved to Linux,
and I couldn't get iA Writer,
so I moved over to this other tool
called Typora. It was a piece of
shareware, and it had a lot of
features I just didn't need. And about
six weeks, seven weeks ago, I thought, "Do
you know what? I only need 5% of Typora,"
which is already a basic app.
I literally told the agent to get
going, that I wanted it written in
C++ and Qt, because that
would fit well with the
aesthetic of what I was
building with Quattro.
And in, I think, about 20 minutes,
it had the first version. I
started using it, and it wasn't
quite right. Within two days,
I'd given up Typora, and
I wrote and have written
all of my essays since
that moment in Omawrite.
- Can I ask for your advice and your
vision about something? So what I find
with agents, you can actually write
something like a replacement for
Typora that is perfectly
customized to you, to your needs-
- Correct with just one user in mind. And
then there's a version of that that is-
starts with one user in mind but expands
to a larger audience. So I've actually
written a large number of software
just for me, and I find it
easier to do and better to
get my situation done. For
example, I have a video editor I've written,
which is very easy to do just for me.
- I've never, unlike you, built something
that's used by a large number of
people, and I find that a bit
scary and intimidating. So,
like, at this, with this agentic
age, how do you take a step
to actually build something that solves
your problem, which I think is a
beautiful way to build,
but also expand it to actually useful
for other people? Like, is there
advice you can give, and do you
also see the problem of how
easy it is to just build
a tool for yourself?
- Yes, but it is simpler than you
think. By the time you're done
building the tool for yourself, you simply
tell your agent to put it on GitHub.
You don't even have to do anything else.
It will figure out how to put that repo on
GitHub. It'll write a nice README.
It'll start using GitHub releases so
that you can track things. It'll
actually be a better software
maintainer than you could ever be-
... because it is far more patient,
it is far more diligent in
doing the drudgery of managing
open source software than you are.
And you can simply get on with the joy
of using the software that you built
and evolving it as you see fit. Now,
this gets into the big argument we've been
having in open source for a while. Is
AI contributions good or
bad for the maintainer?
There's a lot of maintainers
right now who are quite
upset about the fact that they're suddenly
getting a huge influx of pull requests, of
contributions from people who may not be
the best programmers or programmers at all-
... towards their software. I look at that
argument and go, "Are you kidding me?"
Here is a vein of free contributions
that you can take or don't take,
but you're complaining about the fact
that they're there? It sounds straight
out of- My steak is too
juicy and my lobster too
buttery. What are you complaining about?
This is the most amazing thing.
This is what we proclamated for so
long was going to be the magic
of open source, that we could
all contribute to it, but it was, of
course, never true. There was only a small
subset of people who contribute to open
source, and that was the very highly skilled
wizards. So this is a bit of a
reformation moment. We had this
disintermediation between us and
the computer, and it was this
class of clerics and
priests called programmers,
and suddenly they're being
disintermediated here by was
it the 95 theses by Luther in 1500s,
nailing them to the door? And one
of those was very clearly about
the intermediation, that you should have
direct access to the higher intelligence.
- Mm-hmm. But don't you need the wizards to
keep a high bar of excellence in the code
base?
- 100% you do, which is also something
that's always been true about open
source, which is the second argument
that really grinds me. I've been
running open source projects for
25 years. I have literally looked
at the output of thousands,
if not tens of thousands of
programmers. I feel like I
have the statistical basis to
assert that most programmers, they suck.
And I don't mean that
in the way it sounds.
That was why I paused for a hot second
here. I mean, they suck in the sense
that they don't write the code I
want to have written. They don't
prepare their bug reports
with all the relevant
information. They don't detail
their pull requests with the
why. They don't bother to fill in
needed code comments. They don't
double-check their work. They don't
write unit tests. They don't do all
of these things it takes to create
good software. But do you know
who'll do all that stuff? Agents,
if you tell them to. They're very
diligent at following your instructions,
most of the time, sometimes to a fault.
But it actually means that if you take
the median programmer and
their pull requests towards
an average open source project,
they're already getting
outclassed by agents. I would
rather get an agent-written
pull request to one of my
projects than I'd get one written
by a human, and it's not just
because the quality's
better. It's also because
I feel a lot less bad if I just
reject it. You didn't even
write it, so I can simply look at what
your agent wrote on your behalf and
go, "Eh, don't want it."
That's always been true in open source, and in
fact, I think this is one of the problems with
open source maintainers. They have way too
much ball of neuroticism and anxiety that
requires them to look upon any contribution
as an obligation on their part to do
everything to get that to land
in the code base. That's not
true at all. You can simply say, "No," or
even better, you can say, "No, thank you."
And if you get into the mode
of realizing that your project
is allowed to exist and
evolve according to your
vision, according to your
roadmap, it becomes so much
easier in the agentic age to
decline the contributions you don't
want because you don't
even inconvenience or hurt
the feelings of a human. It's just
a clanker, and the clanker won't
mind. In fact, the
producers of clankers, the
labs, love when you spend tokens in
vain. They get paid just the same.
So, in my opinion, this
is the absolute best
time to ever have been an open
source software maintainer.
Not only do we get this wealth of
glorious pull requests made by
agents with all the boxes ticked,
we also get to tap into a
creativity of people who did not have
access to contribute to a project before.
I've been running the Omarchy project
now for a little over a year,
and in the last three months working on
Quattro, I have merged over 1,000 pull
requests. Quite a lot of those pull
requests were written by people who were
not classical programmers, or were
programmers in other domains, not
Linux operating system or
distribution development.
They were able to contribute their good
ideas because of agents, and I got
to cherry-pick the very best of that- ...
because it was there. Otherwise, those
ideas would just have lived
inside their heads. Again,
Is- that is not the purpose of open
source, that we tap into the collective
intelligence and creativity
of the whole goddamn planet,
and we channel that towards a commons
where we all benefit from the
combined efforts of everyone.
Now, there's currently, I think, about
400 unmerged pull requests on Omarchy,
about double what it was a week
ago. So the acceleration is
real, but so are the tools.
I'm not reviewing every pull request
anymore. I haven't been reviewing them for
quite some time now. I have the
agents- ... review them for me-
... and then they will give me a summary
about whether something is ready for the
decision, the human decision. Should
we merge or should we not merge?
I don't need to look at all the pull
requests that are either wrong, duplicated,
bad. An agent can sort that chaff away
from me. I just get to look at the pearls-
... the good ideas that
are ready to go, the bug
fixes that the agent has
validated in a VM on my behalf.
All the drudgery of replicating
and managing open source
projects is evaporating at lightning
speed, and we are left with the,
with the golden juicy parts, the
bone marrow of software development-
... deciding what should this
thing do and where should it go.
- Do you think the good ideas, ultimately
the kernel of the good ideas
originated in the human mind,
so the individual contributors
Like, can it be done by agents, or is
the PR ultimately requires a human idea?
Like how to improve Omarchy,
all those incoming... Or can it
all just be a pool of agents?
- That was the mode and the way
I was thinking about agents
in the first agentic age from
November 24 to February 28.
I thought all the ideas would originate
with the humans. They would tell
their agents what to
build, and off they went.
I don't think that's true anymore at all.
I have seen things you people wouldn't
believe, ideas coming out of models
so great that it makes me humble-
... as a person who otherwise prides
himself on having good ideas.
The agents are incredibly
capable of creative thought,
and folks who are still stuck in the
analysis that agents are parrots-
... just regurgitating the ideas that are
already there are delusional about
the progress that's been made in
the last six to nine months.
- So some people listening to you right now
will say DHH is suffering from the old case
of AI psychosis. Can you steel man the
case that you are in fact experiencing in
a state of delusion, like One Flew Over the
Cuckoo's Nest, and can you argue against it?
- I'm in a state of delirium.
That's what the state I'm in.
Because I have been working
with computers for 40 years,
and I've never seen the things that
I've seen in just the last two months.
A whole career, a whole life dedicating
to the love of computers as my main
focus for the working hours and then some,
suddenly completely upended, suddenly
completely rewritten. Of course I'm delirious.
Who looking at this reality is not? If you
are not delirious or at the very least
very excited... Actually, I guess that's
not even true. If you're not recognizing
the gravity of the moment,
that's the delusion. That's the
psychosis. The psychosis is believing
that the world is barely different. We
just have some electronic parrots reciting
things to us. Now, in my opinion, the
reason this argument is actually brought
up is because people are not able to see
the fruits of the progress. That
goes to your point earlier.
Where is the amazing software? Why isn't
American GDP running at 12% year over year?
First of all, give it a minute. It
hasn't even been a year, goddammit.
But second of all, I feel on my own account,
I have actually brought the pudding.
Omarchy Quattro launched
on Friday. It's been
downloaded by tens of thousands of people.
And they like it. They like it a lot.
- We should mention that going to
Perplexity here, Omarchy is a highly
opinionated Arch Linux-based desktop
distribution centered on the Hyprland
Wayland tiling compositor.
It was created by David
Heinemeier Hansson, DHH, as a polished
developer workstation set
up with a cohesive visual
style and many everyday
tools already configured.
- Let me put it. Omarchy is a beautiful,
modern, and opinionated Linux system.
It's an alternative operating
system to macOS and Windows,
and it's freaking amazing.
- And the Quattro thing is you're
pushing towards the age of agents.
- That's right. That's the latest version that
we just dropped out, which is also funny.
The Omarchy project is
only a year old and a
little bit. I started it last summer in
between sessions at the 24 Hours of Le Mans-
... where I had watched one
too many YouTube videos on
Linux Rising and got bitten
by that bug. Started working
on this second iteration of my
attempt at creating a better Linux operating
system. The first iteration we talked about
last time was called Omakub, was built
on top of an existing system called
Ubuntu, and it was fine. But the
ambition I was able to pour into the new
version, Omarchy, because I started
seven layers deeper down the
stack, was completely different, but
it was still done in a pre-agentic
world. I wrote all those batch
scripts by hand in the beginning,
and then I got to see the midway
point where things changed over.
I did a couple of versions of
Omarchy that had partial agent
acceleration, and then three months ago,
it was full throttle, 100%, everything
is written by agents but steered by me.
And that just ended up being
a very different experience and a
very different operating system
because I was suddenly granted a
limitless ceiling on my ambition.
I could look at any feature in Windows, on
Mac, on other Linux systems and say, "I
want that," and the agents would deliver.
So everything I wanted was suddenly
within reach, which meant that
I got a little delirious.
Who would not get delirious if suddenly
a genie pops out of the bottle
and says, "You can have whatever
you want. Every feature
you've ever dreamed of
in an operating system-
... I can deliver them to you, most
of them in five minutes, a few in
20, and if we really go hog wild,
it's gonna take me two hours."
- Mm-hmm. Have you seen Requiem
for a Dream, the movie? So the,
There's a drug-like effect here.
I find it personally-- We'll talk about
many levels of this, but it is overwhelming
how much power is placed
in our hands so suddenly,
and it's very hard to know, it's like with
"The Hobbit" or something, what to do
with it, and I find myself truly
overwhelmed with the multitasking,
On the verge of almost burnt out. Super
excited about so many things, but ultimately
looking back, you want to focus
on one thing and really ship
- I don't have that sense. I don't have
the sense of overwhelm. I don't have the
sense of dread. I don't have the sense
of distortion because I have a mission.
I'm going somewhere, and therefore, I
can channel all this new power towards-
- Yeah, it's wonderful
- ... a singular goal and
outcome, creating the perfect
computer. And therefore, all my
investigations with AI are focused towards
that end. Now, I also have a day job.
And we also use agents there, and
that's also targeted towards sort of
specific outcomes. But with the
Omarchy experience, I got to tap in
straight in the back of
my head and increase
the bandwidth between ideas arriving in my
brain and software emerging on the
screen. It was like going from dial-up-
... to fiber. I think on your podcast, Elon
talked about the actual human bandwidth-
... that Neuralink and other
projects are trying to accelerate.
Like, the bandwidth we're communicating
over right now is quite low because
we're limited by our cognition.
We're limited by the rate of
speech. You're not limited by those
things when you're working with a
swarm of agents. Now, let
me caveat this by saying,
if I'd heard myself talk like this-
... nine months ago, I would
probably have used the label AI,
AI psychosis. I think it
would be fitting because
nine months ago when people were talking
like this, they weren't shipping,
and I think that's the ultimate difference,
that there were people who saw this
early. I was not actually that
early. As we've talked about, I
was rather skeptical, and I was using
AI in certain ways, but I was not
the first person who downloaded Claude
Code. I think Boris released that in end of
February. I don't think I
installed Claude Code until
September. So there was about
six months there where pioneers
saw these glimmers of what the future
was gonna look like. It wasn't there
yet because the intelligence wasn't there.
The harnesses weren't there, but they could
see the glimmers. I couldn't.
Tobi, Tobi Lütke, the CEO of
Shopify and now my
partner in crime on this
Omarchy project in part, he's
gotten pilled with Omarchy as well.
He saw these things very early,
and he tried to tell me,
and I wasn't seeing it. I was
not seeing what he was seeing.
- You were a hater.
- Yes. I was still on Earth. And he was...
He had already boarded the rocket and was
heading towards space. I
remember actually reading his
memo to the company, the AI memo, and
thinking, "Ah, seems a little much."
Like, you're making a big deal out
of something that I cannot yet
feel is a tangible thing.
Because where's the output of this? I try
using it. It writes code I don't like.
It wants to interrupt me all the time.
Where are you getting this from? Uh,
so I get it. I totally get
it. If you've not seen what
the current quality of
intelligence can produce,
of course you're gonna look at someone and go
like, "They sound a little nutty," because
all your experience up until this point
would tell you that they are nutty. Because
if you look at the history of computer
programming, for the last 40,
50 years, people have been promising that
regular people could write code just
by talking. We're gonna have fourth
generation languages.
Lisp was once upon a time
presented, Smalltalk was presented
as these environments that would
let regular people write their own
applications, and none of it came
true in the sense beyond, like, Microsoft
Access databases or Excel
spreadsheets. That, those are end
user programming environments, but it's
nothing like what we're able to do now.
And then, I mean, I'm not even talking
about end user. I'm talking as me,
someone who's been programming
for 25 years, seeing
the output and the acceleration and
the quality and then shipping it,
and I think that's what's gonna
change the entire conversation
quite quickly. The few laggards
who are still on the fence
about whether this is actually useful,
who are still trapped in a meme
from early '25 about mechanical parrots,
they're simply going to be overwhelmed
by the evidence that's about to
flood over them.
- So I hope to see,
projects like Omarchy, several of them
that, like, really show agent first.
- It's coming. All of it is coming.
- In the spaces, in the silly spaces that I
already mentioned, like video editing, all
these kinds of apps that are like Typora-
- Yes.
- ... this kind of stuff.
- It's gonna come, and I've already
seen the early inklings of this.
One of the really neat features
about Omarchy is that it has
a far more robust plugin system
that allows you to extend your
operating system and rewrite
it really in terms of its
user interface and its
panel and its features
by creating your own plugins that can be
cloned off of tools we ship in the box. For
example, say you want a different calendar.
Omarchy ships with a calendar. You
click the little clock. It pops
up a calendar, and it doesn't
have iCal support, for example. It
doesn't consume your appointments.
There's about 17 implementations
of that already, and in
three days, we had 330 plugins on the
Omarchy plugin marketplace. I have
never seen growth like
that with any project
I've ever been involved in. I've never
seen participation that broadly.
I've never seen that many people
be able to create software that's
meaningful for them- Also be usable
for others so quickly. All of
it is driven by the fact
that Omarchy ships a set of
skills that tells any agent
you bring to it how to
create extensions to the
operating system, and
therefore affording you the
vision of the true malleable...
I was about to say agentic.
I hate that fucking word.
And the reason in part I hate that word
is, first of all, it's become marketing
slob speak- ... at this point. Like,
it's just slapped onto everything.
I wish we had a different word
that just meant AI doing stuff.
- Vibe coding feels wrong, too.
- It does, because vibe coding to
me smells exactly like script
kiddies did in the early 2000s.
People applying PHP scripts they
just downloaded offline they don't
understand anything of.
And while, I mean, that's true in the
sense that much of the vibe coding,
including my own vibe coded projects,
and as I just mentioned, I have several.
I've written things in C++.
I've written things in Rust.
Rust. I hate Rust with
a passion. Rust to me
is like pouring acid in my eyes
when I have to look at the code.
- Wait, wait, wait, wait. Why
do, why do you hate Rust?
- It is, in my opinion, the ugliest programming
language- ... that has been invented-
... in probably the last 40 years.
- So it's the opposite of Rails and Ruby.
- It's the opposite. But-
- You've written it
- ... I've written applications
in Rust because the output
of Rust is actually amazing. The memory
safety, the fact that it's a system
language, the fact that it's
highly efficient and so forth is
incredible. So Rust, to me, can both be
the most repugnant programming
language ever devised for
human consumption and a wonderful
platform for agentic engineering.
These two truths can
coexist easily in my head.
- Do you think that there can be a point at
which we can just call agentic engineering
programming? Can we just
change what programming
means? 'Cause who's actually going
to be programming the old-school way
in a few months?
- I don't think we should reuse the
term because for me, programming
implies an understanding
of certain primitives,
loops, conditions, variables. All the
constructs of programming languages
are what constitutes programming
itself, not the creation of programs.
Because you could say in the
pre-agentic era, well, your
CEO is programming. He's hiring a bunch of
programmers, he's telling them what to do, and
out comes software that he can sell.
Eh, I don't think most people would call that CEO
a programmer, and I don't think we should call
the vibe coder a programmer
either. And vibe
coding, if we define it here, is you
tell an agent to build software for
you. You do not look at the implementation.
That, to me, is what separates vibe
coding from programming or, let's
say, agent-accelerated development.
- But don't you think, so to
push back a little bit,
don't you think a programmer,
old-school programmer, you, doing
agentic engineering is a different
kind of agentic engineering than
a non-programmer doing agentic
engineering? What I mean is, if you know
what a for loop is, if you know what function
programming is, if you know some of the
basic good principles of software
engineering, the way you do
natural language-based agentic
engineering will be different and more
systematic, and this, the scale and the
variety of things you can actually
build is much bigger than a vibe coder.
- I'm just gonna extend the pro case here a
little bit just for the sake of the argument.
- Right.
- I actually think for a while it
was to my deficit to know as
much as I know about programming because I
was instructing the
agents to do things as I
prescribed them to do, and they
were very good at that. And in the
first agentic moment, let's not
call it an era, it was something
that lasted three months. Moment. In
the first agentic moment, that felt
very productive. I could get more productivity
out of telling the agents what to
do in the way I would've done
it, and I used all of my
experience as a programmer
to do just that.
Then I was a little late on the next moment,
and the next moment allowed me, allowed
anyone, to describe outcomes- ...
to describe problems to the agents
and get better solutions than if you
had a programmer prescribe the path.
- See, okay, so we're having
fun arguing here. Well
so are you suggesting that
there's problems for which
programmers are worse than
non-programmers at agentic engineering?
- 100%. And the reason I say
that, let's define it here.
The reason I say that is there's
a lot of programmers who are not
very good product managers. Software
is product management. What
should it do? Who should it do it
for? How should it do it? How should
it look? What are our priorities? What
do we start with first? What does
version one include? All of those skills
are not easily or equally
distributed across all programmers.
And in the agentic era
where you are letting
an agent, an AI, do the implementation,
these are the skills you
need. And I happen to sit in both
camps, and this is why I love this
moment. I still get to live a little bit
in the old world where I look at the full
implementation because there are
domains and areas where I feel
that still brings value, and
then I also live in the future.
And as I said, when I created
Omawrite, I've not looked at a
single line of that C++. I
actually made it a point to
myself that I was gonna treat it as an
experiment. This is 100% a black box.
I will treat it as though I
was any other user who had
opinions about how their digital
typewriter should work, and
therefore felt like it
was a fair experiment as
if a writer of any other sort who had
opinions about how software should be done
and how it should work. As you mentioned,
video editors who know exactly
where they don't like what Adobe
Premiere's doing and how it could be
better, but don't have the capacities to
improve it- ... how that could be.
- The pushback, though, I think what
programmers do well, good programmers do
well, is systematic design,
like think in terms of systems-
- Correct
- ... and rigor.
- Yes.
- And I think still, and probably
for a long time to come,
even natural language-based
control of agentic systems will
require a certain kind
of rigor. Not overly
structured rigor, but really explain very
specifically the goals
of the system, how to
do the verification, what kind of
security testing. You wanna do all
those kinds of things. Although
then to push back on that, the
system will... should
be smart longer term.
- I would've said the same
thing six months ago.
- Yeah, so this has changed.
- And I think the same thing would've been true
six months ago. What I have found since,
especially even just the
last few weeks of the
agentically accelerated
development of Mach-E, is that
more often than not, I have the humility
to recognize that the agent knows best.
- You can legitimately say,
"Make sure it's secure."
- Correct. And it would know more about
what that entails. Now, you're laughing-
- What a crazy world
- ... but it's true. And in fact-
- Oh my God
- ... a good parallel to this is the AGENTS
MD/CLAUDE MD files. There was a hot moment
where it was all the rage about micro-
optimizing that. Oh, you tell your agent this-
... you tell your agent that, and you ended
up with this huge file of instructions
for your agent. One of the
things that Boris, working on
Claude Code, shared in an interview
recently about Opus 5 was
that the system prompt that
they ship for Opus 5, and
presumably also Fable, shrunk by 80%
because the agent not only
needed far less human
instruction, it was actually being damaged
by overly prescriptive
humans. And any programmer
who's had a pointy-haired boss
knows exactly what that is like.
When the boss walks into the
room, doesn't know anything,
starts telling you how to
program, how to code. What do you
do? You sulk. You write shittier code if
you're mandated to do things that
are against your better judgment.
Why would an agent not be the same?
- Actually, to push back against myself, I
do find the actual skill I'm currently
developing, which I along those lines
is probably what everybody's trying to
develop, is not to overspecify things,
is to get out of the system's way.
- Of course.
- Is to specify enough to provide a
kinda high-level vision and guidance.
- It's even better because you
don't even need that. The
fundamental insight of modern software
development came from the agile
software development movement. In the
late '90s, early 2000s, a group of
smart, honest, and brave people came together
and said, "The way we've been trying to
do software development for
the last 40 to 50 years has
not worked, will not work.
We've been trying to
specify upfront what software
should look like. We thought
that we could ask humans what
they wanted, write it all
down, apply our systems
thinking and our rigor to a
spec sheet, hand that spec sheet
over to a group of programmers
who would then implement just that, and
everyone would be happy." Well, guess what?
No one was happy. Because no one
knows what they want until they
receive it. You don't know what
a program should do until you
play with it. So in the
agentic age, you should
resist the temptation to be
overly specific upfront. Be as
vague as you can to manifest something,
then interact with the something.
The way you arrive at good software is
you write a little bit of software,
and then you try to use it. It is in
the process of using software that you
discover what you really want.
It's where you discover what's
important and what's not important. And
agents are incredible at allowing you to
bumble into this experience of
realizing what you want because
you don't know what you want.
- Mm-hmm. And I've actually done something
similar to what you suggested, which is
implement different designs and totally
different implementations, and then
I create HTML pages for myself,
PHP pages, where I vote on
what I like more and so on.
And it does this iterative thing, and it's
very nice and fun. The interaction with
the agentic system, if you create a nice
interface for yourself, it can be super fun,
and you're focusing on the design part and
the most fun parts of the design part.
- Correct. And this is what
humans are really good at.
- Yeah, taste.
- Differential evaluation. You give me three
options, I pick one of them. Now,
humans actually fall off a cliff if
you give them 22 options. That's the paradox
of choice. But you give them three options,
they very quickly within a split
second will tell you what they like.
There are all these ways
that exploit the fact that
humans will make these snap judgments
that are actually pre-intellectual,
right? Like, they're coming from
the gut, and then they arrive up in
the, in the brain, and the brain
tries to rationalize why the
gut said what it said. And if you're
willing to let go of some of
that intellectual pre-processing
rationalization and simply let your gut
drive, the agentic age is a revelation.
- So this is a fascinating thing to
ask you because you have sort of
famously for a long time talked about,
like, detailed chiseling of beautiful
Rails Ruby code, and now you have switched
in a matter of months to not
doing that. So, like, what is
your current setup look like?
'Cause you're, I assume, are still
looking for the beauty, for the chiseling,
for the crafting, but you're just
crafting in a different medium.
- And at different levels of abstraction. When
I'm working in Ruby code, and we have a lot
of Ruby code because it's in our entire
business, and I'm asking agents to make changes
to that code, I still sweat the details.
What I'm coming to realize
is that the economic payoff
of that sweat is diminishing
rapidly. The reason
why I, for 25 years, was
sweating every line of
code so judiciously was because I knew
the payoff of keeping an architecture
coherent and malleable was software
that could change and evolve-
quickly with a small team,
and not exorbitant cost,
and not introducing a bunch of bugs when you
change one thing over the other. That was
the driving economic argument
for why you should write
beautiful code, 'cause beautiful code is
easier to understand, it is simpler, it
is more malleable. That was premised
on humans doing the modifications.
I think it is an open question to
which degree this still matters. Now,
it does matter, and the reason I say
that, at least for the moment, is that
tokens are still scarce. At this moment
in time, we are all token limited.
Well, not all, but anyone who doesn't
have endless budgets are token
limited. So therefore,
there is great payoff
to writing systems that agents
have an easier time dealing with
and evolving without having to relearn
the entire context. Just like humans,
if they can make iterations
and changes to the code base
without wrecking the architecture,
they can make the next
change just as cheaply as the
last one. And this is the
classic ball of mud where you end up
with a system that's a ball of mud-
... because it's just put together
in a way where nothing is
connected and it's just a real mess, right?
I've seen that with agents, and I've seen
it in our own code bases where,
again, the first PR is, like,
mediocre of quality, and then if you add
another PR on top of that, and then five more
down the line, it's not very good, right?
So there's still a payoff to that,
but that payoff is premised on
our current moment. I am now able
to... And this is, by the way, where the
AI psychosis really comes in, when you
try to extrapolate what nine months
from now it's gonna look like.
What two years from now it's gonna look
like. But as an intellectual experiment,
I think the first computer
I used was a Commodore 64.
- Me too. Cool.
- It had one megahertz
CPU and 64K of memory.
Everyone who wrote software
for that machine internalized
certain constraints. Well, all
the constraints. That machine was
nothing but constraints. If
you put that programmer in a
time machine and teleported him or her to
2026 and gave them a
modern computer today and
said, "Now write me a piece of software,"
they'd be lost for a little bit
because all their techniques and all their
heuristics would simply be wrong. Or
not wrong, because efficient software
is still beautiful. They would be out of
date with the value that they could create.
The amount of optimization you have
to apply for a one megahertz computer
to produce a video game is just very
different from what you have to apply today.
- Just imagine that guy that was programming
back then on a Commodore. Just re-
remember all those,
like what programming felt like and what
it meant, highly constrained resources-
... how slow everything is.
- Beautiful in many ways. Beautiful.
- It's chiseling. But-
- It-
- ... imagine that person coming now.
- It's romantic too, though. Let's also imagine
that. This is one of the things, whenever
we bemoan modern car culture, for
example, right? And then we think like,
"Oh, wasn't it better when we all had the
horse-drawn carriages and so on?" No, it wasn't.
Do you know what New York smelled like
when we used horses for transportation?
It was an open sewer. They
just shat everywhere.
- Yeah, but have you played Red Dead Redemption?
You know how cool those cowboys were-
- That is the way-
- ... on the horse?
- ... to experience the nostalgic
past, when you don't get the all
the furry impulses and senses.
- So basically programming, old
school programming by hand is
kinda like the cowboy culture that we
romanticize and make movies about.
- It's already happening, the
romanticization of handwritten code.
And I have some of it because
it was a very romantic
era. I'm grateful to have
been alive for 20 years of
economically valuable handwritten code.
That was a, that was a good time.
- Where handwritten beautiful
code was also valuable.
- Correct. Because handwritten
beautiful code exists
as much today as it did
yesterday. There are people who
willfully write new video
games for the Commodore 64,
or for the second Mega Drive, or
for other vintage consoles. In
fact, one of my favorite
video games of late is
ModRetro's. Do you know Palmer Luckey's-
... side geschäft, which is recreating old
consoles. So he's recreated the Game Boy.
- Nice.
- It's amazing. Look it up. It's
really cool. But what's even
cooler than the fact that he recreated
this hardware and the original
chunkiness, but brought it up
to date with sort of modern
screens and so on, now they just put
out the Nintendo 64 too. Incredible.
Super cool. Wild attention to detail,
input lag, and all the other things.
But what's also very cool, that
one, I have to wave. That one
right there, and hover over it, 'cause then
you get to see what I'm talking about.
That is the Chromatic- ...
Tetris re-implementation.
- Wow.
- I played a lot of Tetris
on the original Game Boy.
Probably one of my top three
favorite games of all time.
And they rewrote it with one change.
If you hit up, the brick slams.
And that speeds up the game by about 400%.
It is an incredible game, and
it's a new Game Boy game.
I think the Game Boy came out
in- '89 or '88. It's a very
old machine. The fact that there's
still people writing new old
games is awesome, and the reason
they do it in part, now here
they're doing it because they want Tetris, but there are
people who do it just for the love of the constraints,
for the love of the romantic
notion of writing that. Just
like there are people still riding
around on horses, not to get
places fast, but because
they like the mode of
transportation where it's
a literal biological
being below you propelling you forward.
- And also, we should say that that
beautiful code is great training
data. So in some sense, the beauty
that we've built over a few decades-
- Yes
- ... continues.
- We gave birth to this moment. What
a privilege, and I feel that very
personally because I... Almost all of
the code I've ever written is public
code. The vast majority of my career has
been dedicated to writing open source code,
and therefore, some of that code,
some of those beautiful lines
are in the training set. And in fact, I've
heard people do this when they write
Ruby code. They ask the agent, "Write
it like DHH would."
And they're pleased with the result, and
that does warm my heart a little bit, that
I helped give birth to this moment in my
tiny little small part. And anyone else
who contributed open source code or any code
at all that the agents have had access to
over the last, well, entire time
programming has been around as
a discipline, is now part of
these new agent overlords.
- So you don't have a little bit of
sadness that writing beautiful
code by hand is now less and less useful?
- Am I sad that if I had
to get a job tomorrow,
it's unlikely that I could apply my
skills in such a way that I would be
paid to write these
manual lines of code? No.
I did it for 25 years. Like, I
wanna see something new here,
especially if we're all gonna live forever,
which I hope we don't. Maybe we'll get to that.
But, like, I've done that. That's enough.
That's fine. I don't feel any more
nostalgic about that than I do
about the fact that I don't have to
spend my time in the field with
a hoe or at the assembly line.
- Well, hold on a second. You are
one of the best programmers
in the world at writing handcrafted
beautiful code, appreciators
of beauty with great taste.
- Correct.
- That has been replaced.
- I say humbly.
- Yeah. That has been replaced.
Like, you had now...
You're just fast evolving, and
you're able to... One of your
really great qualities is you're able
to change your mind and evolve very
quickly. But, like, you had
to kill that other person.
- I am grateful for every moment that
brought me to where I am right now, and
therefore, I have also tried, and
maybe this did take some practice. I
will concede that. Maybe I
wasn't always like this, but
stoic philosophy, amor
fati, loving your fate,
is an incredibly liberating
way to live. And
you could attack that and say,
"Well, that's a point of privilege."
True, but also I had the
same directional point
when I didn't have all this,
quote unquote, "privilege."
So I think there's a way to live
and interact with the world
where you accept the things you can
change and the things you cannot change
and fall in love with all of it.
Fall in love with the fact that
the world today has jumped
two decades forward into technology
industry from where it was last year.
- So can we talk about the general
anxiety that programmers feel,
going through the same transformation?
They've maybe gone to university
majored in computer science, dreamed of
being programmers and building stuff,
high salary, and now everything's
changing, and there's deep
anxiety about, "What do I do
when... with my life?" Can you
empathize with that, and what the
hell are they supposed to do?
- Hugely. Because just because
I have this disposition, I'm
keenly aware that that's not
evenly distributed, that
not everyone sits with this position
and this optimism for the future.
But I do think I wanna
separate things a little bit.
I think you're gonna have a
hard time coping with the new
reality if the only thing you loved about
programming was the mechanical bits of
putting the right logical constructs
together to produce something other people
told you to produce. Because that
mechanical process is under threat.
If you are, as you just mentioned,
excited about building things,
I don't think you're under threat at all.
In fact, I think there's a great argument
for us needing far more builders than
what we have now, and if you look at
the employment stats, it's fuzzy.
It's not clear what's gonna happen
at all. Some stats actually show an
increase in openings because
the advent of AI is so
dramatically lowering the price of
programs that people want a lot
more programs. This is the classic,
the Jevons paradox, that says when the price
of something goes down, there's gonna be more
demand for it. And this is the
example of the ATMs too. When the ATM
originally came, a lot of
bank tellers were very
afraid for their job because suddenly there
was a machine that could dispense money from
people's account. Well, what
the ATMs did was lower the
price of a branch, and suddenly
banks could afford to open a lot
more branches, and we ended up with more bank
tellers than we did before. Now, none of this
is guaranteed. There are also
moments where things do change. The
vast majority of people
worked in the fields up until
the late 1800s, and then
suddenly we got mechanized-
harvesting tools, and we did not
need human labor with a hoe and
an ox out there. We had mechanical
tools to do that for us.
In that moment, are there people
who were threatened that their
job and their livelihood was at stake?
Yes. Was that a reasonable thing to
feel threatened about? Yes. The
Luddites smashing the weaving machines-
... in England had the same thing. And I
think maybe that's the better parallel
than people working the fields because these
were actually highly skilled professionals
doing a job that they liked on
rather favorable conditions, not
slaving outside in the sun all day.
But where we live now, would we
still like for clothing to be this
heavily constrained resource?
Like, what if this T-shirt was
$400? I mean, okay, then I'd have
two. Well, my wardrobe probably
looks like I have two. But
I think the general progress of
mankind depends on productivity
improvements. And what are productivity improvements?
This is very important because in the abstract,
I think everyone says, "Yay,
productivity. That's good."
What did you think, this was all just
vibes? No. Productivity means fewer
people to do the same number
or the same job. Now,
the amount of job you want done may
increase, and therefore you get more people,
but it also may not. There may be pockets
where a company just
needs a certain set of
fixed tasks done, and suddenly they
can do them with a 10th the number
of people. This, by the
way, could... is tragic
and difficult in the moment for the
individual being laid off. It's also amazing
for the economy at large. Suddenly
you've freed up these resources who can
now go do more productive
things. This is how the whole
economy evolves and improves
and how we get growth,
and growth is good. I think this
is the other thing to make a
strong defense for, that growth in
general is a good thing.
We do not want to wind the
clock back to 1920 or 1950. We should
be excited about the fact
that we've discovered new
technology that allows us
to do vastly more. And
while some of the tasks that may
be taken over by AI were tasks
that humans were excited to do, and
they're just no longer economically
viable, a lot of the tasks were just
drudgery. This is certainly true
of my programming. There
were moments of programming
I thought were amazing. These were the
moments that produced that state of
flow we talked about last time, and
they were ecstatic. How often did they
happen out of the course of a
year? If you took your average
programmer, how much time
out of 2,000 hours at
the job did that person
spend in a flow state?
100? 200? 25? I think all those answers
could be plausible for someone.
And taking that drudgery,
handing it over to
machines, that is the
history of civilization.
- Yeah, I mean, the hours spent debugging.
So programming has so many painful,
painful hours in it. And now they're gone.
For the... I mean, for the most part,
it's just fun.
- A lot of it is gone in a lot of domains,
and the rest of it may be gone very soon.
So that's where some of the
romanticism also comes in
... because pain in the moment
is difficult. It's hard. It's
annoying. Pain in the rear
view mirror is accomplishment, proud,
learning, steps forward, all
the things, right? So we
encompass all of this as part of
the human experience, that we hate
pain in the moment, but we cherish it when
it's five minutes past and we
don't remember the hardship. We
just remember the progress.
- So certainly at the societal
level, at the macroeconomic
level, growth is exciting. But the individual
level, there's going to be a lot of
anxiety potentially a lot
of suffering. So by way of
advice, if you're like a
young DHH or young developer
programmer now, what
would you advise they do?
- Don't try to anticipate anything.
You will literally go crazy.
Because even the smartest
brains in the business
cannot anticipate what two
model hops from here is
going to look like. It's an
absolute waste of time, and you
will develop an AI psychosis
trying to deduce what two
years from now is gonna look like. Focus
on right now, and right now is the most
incredible time to be into computers.
You can make them do the most amazing
things if you lean in. If you
maybe for a hot moment force yourself
to learn where the state of the art is,
I double dog dare you not to get
excited about what's possible.
- And would you recommend building publicly?
- I think it's optional actually
to build publicly. I think it's
nice to do because then you get to be
part of a community, and there's some
camaraderie in open source. Not
some camaraderie. There's an
enormous amount of
camaraderie. Open source is an
incredible source of
community and camaraderie,
and it's also a great
way to stem some of that
personal existential dread. If
you're amongst other humans, you can
get infected with good
forms of mind viruses,
exciting forms of mind viruses, the ones
that tell you that it's all gonna be okay,
and the future looks bright, and if we
build a bunch of things together,
we can do things none of us ever
dreamed we could do. I was just
talking to Ryan Hughes, who's been
my main partner on Omarchy
almost since day one,
and we were literally talking
about yesterday how when
We started on this journey
together. Our ambitions were very
modest. We're just like, "Can we
get this distro to not crash at
3:00 AM because of an Arch
package that just got pushed out
outside of our control? That would
be amazing. Then it'd be great." Now
we're leaning back and thinking,
"How can we take over the world?
How can we make Omarchy go to Mars? How can
we do everything we've ever dreamed of?"
And that level of ambition
inflation is partly
because things have gotten better with
agents, but hugely also because we've
surrounded ourselves with others
excited about the same journey.
And if you're just sitting
in your little isolated cave
worrying about the future, yeah,
you're gonna go a little nuts.
I think if we learned
anything during COVID is
that people will go nuts
sitting in their little cave
inside by themselves worrying
about what's gonna happen. That is
indistinguishable from depression,
ruminating endlessly about things you can't
control. I'm sorry to channel some Jensen
Huang here, but that's just loser talk.
You don't have to be a loser.
You can choose to lean in and-
... win. And win is very
broadly defined as learning
more, making more, contributing
more, being part of more.
And at the end of the day, what are your
choices? You don't have a choice, mate.
The future's coming whether you like it
or not, so you might as well choose to be
excited about it.
- But I mean, we should emphasize
the fact that planning is nearly
impossible with AI. I mean,
most of us plan our life a
little bit. When we're younger, you
have, like, hopes and dreams. There's a
reason you go to college.
There's a plan underlying that.
- I agree with that.
- But there-
- I'll concede that.
- ... it is kinda-
- This is different.
- ... nuts that it's impossible to really
plan. Because, like, you really don't know,
if there will even be a Claude
Code, a Codex, and Cursor
six months from now. Maybe it'll be
you'll be talking to WhatsApp. Maybe
it'll be all open call type.
Maybe it'll just all be voice.
Maybe Omarchy will take over the world and it'll
be voice. Maybe there won't be operating systems
anymore. You'll just... There'll be this
glowing orb that just you just talk
to because if natural language
is enough to accomplish
all tasks in life, like, what is
life about? Like, what are the major
tasks you need to accomplish in life?
If you can just do that with voice, and
it writes all the programs for you,
and all is systematized, and what,
what are the jobs needed then?
Maybe it's more about the service
industry. Maybe there won't be programmers,
like agentic engineers at all. And so
yes, your advice is wise to focus on
the moment, but that doesn't mean
that it's just a crazy rollercoaster
ride, 'cause we don't know
what this December or what
this January will look like.
- We don't know, and therefore, we
should choose to have faith that it's
gonna pan out. That is my best advice
towards fighting anxiety, is that you
have a choice, to a large degree,
of how to lean.
Do you wanna lean into PDoom? PDoom is gonna
happen whether you lean into it or not.
You don't have control.
- But there's also actual daily schedule of
how much learning are you doing, how much
building are you doing, how much
uh, diversification you're doing.
And for example, I traveled across
rural China recently, and I did
it quite deliberately because you're
talking to people in China, in,
in rural anywhere, where time moves much
slower, where there's no discussions
about agentic engineering. And the ti- and
I started by going on the,
on the Great Wall of China.
That's timeless. That spans
centuries. And, you know, there
was, like, this kind of tension of FOMO,
like maybe I'm missing out on something.
But then I very deliberately
wanted to find the
timelessness of human existence,
really plug into the fact that,
okay, it always feels like
everything's changing uh,
throughout human history but, you
know, the universals are still true,
of what matters in life. And I just wanted
to make su- keep connected to that.
- You're not gonna miss anything.
This is the part that actually
grinded my gears in the
early phases of this
transition. Everyone was
so up in arms that if you
didn't... It's loops now. Oh, no, no,
we're done with loops. It's graphs
now. Oh, no, no, we're done with that. It's, it
harnesses this, right? They're, they're constantly
churning through the frontier,
which in one way is actually
very exciting. This is what happens
when a new field opens up. It's like a
new portal, and it's all spilling
out. That's exciting. But it
also means that if I had just been
backpacking for the last year,
hadn't touched a computer,
hadn't witnessed this agentic
moment, and I just showed up
yesterday, do you know what? I
would've been caught up in two weeks.
There's not any accumulation,
which is in some ways a
great relief. If you missed
the past year, you can catch
up to the frontier in two weeks.
If you're a programmer who was out
hiking the Himalayas for a year and
you come back, you can catch up in two
weeks. And this is actually the great
credit to the progress we're
experiencing. We have so
many experiments running
simultaneously right now that are
constantly and ruthlessly
sorting what works, what
doesn't work. You don't have to
remember or even be part of that
entire journey. You can just
show up for the results.
- But the key step there, when you come
back from the backpacking journey,
is to be willing to become a totally
new, different human because-
Things are changing so fast.
- That's right.
- I mean, literally, if you left for the
backpacking journey- ... in October last
year and came back in April or May-
- You might as well have been in
the cryo chamber for 100 years
- ... it's like, "What, what do you mean? We're
not programming anymore?" This, it's a it's a
huge transformation.
- It's startling, and I actually... I mean,
I'm putting some of this on
slightly for effect. I also
recognize that it's okay to
grieve for a hot moment.
That's not my disposition. It's not how
I do it, but I accept that that's a
time-tested mechanism for coping with
a sense of loss. And it's okay to
have a sense of loss that the world
that you knew and maybe you were
very fond of is no longer the same.
- I maybe I should say out loud and
explicitly that I do have that, the Native
American with a tear rolling down
my... Like, there's a sadness.
It's a goodbye. It's a goodbye
to the old world of programming.
- That's, it's so fascinating to me.
- I've spent so many years-
- But it all amounted to this moment.
That is, to me, what makes the
entire journey so meaningful.
AI did not arrive from the sky.
It was not alien technology that
had blasted through the universe and
suddenly showed up on our shores.
AI has been around for as long as
computer science has been around.
In the '50s, they thought the problem
was gonna be cracked in about a
decade, the smartest people at the
time. It took a little longer,
but the reason it took a little
longer was in part because we took
some blind turns on the
road to AI and neural
networks and thought that there were
other symbolic representations that were
gonna carry the day, and they didn't.
And that probably set us back
about 15 years. So some
of it was also we had to,
Go through the gaming
revolution, 3D games. If we had
not had Quake, if we had not had
Duke Nukem, if we had not had
Unreal Tournament, we'd never have gotten AI
because we would never have gotten the GPUs,
and therefore we would never have been
able to get AI in the shape it is now. So
everything we did up until this
moment was required to get there.
You were part of that.
Holy... What a blessing.
What a blessing to have contributed
in your small part, either by
training or by playing video games.
Literally, you could just choose to
think of it that way. All
those times you spent in,
for my case, in the '90s just
playing video games, they were-
- You were contributing.
- Yeah, I was contributing to the AI
revolution right there and then moment.
- To the progress of human civilization.
No, for sure. Civilization
progresses with the death of the old
and the birth of the new, and it
continues in this way, but it's still the
grieving process is a part of it, I think.
- Take a moment. It's okay. Take
a... And also, you don't even
have to accept that it's all dead. Like,
if you are still very attached to the hand
chiseling, which if you'd asked me a
year ago, I would have predicted that I
would've been more
attached. I'm surprised-
- I'm kinda surprised
- ... a little that I've not been more attached.
But the reason I've not been more attached,
I think, is that I found
something more fun.
And if it hadn't been like that, if AI had
just replaced the thing I loved
and gave me something I hated, I'd
probably be a little bitter.
- I mean, this really feels... It's hilarious
and awesome to watch and inspiring to watch.
It's like Picasso all of a
sudden like, getting access to
to image generation and getting
super excited and switching in a
matter of months. That's literally what happened.
So, like, it's an artist that appreciated beautiful
code, and all of a sudden you're
talking about having fun-
- I think Picasso is actually a good
parallel because if you look at his early
work where he learned his
craft, it was painting
realistic paintings, right?
Like, he was training to
be a master of the old ways of depicting
reality the best way we knew how,
and then along comes all these other
forms of expression. Cubism comes along.
And all these forms of
abstract expression, he's
not decrying that he's
not doing Renaissance
paintings anymore, that he's not just
painting the perfect depiction of an
apple. He's reimagining the
apple to be a freaking square,
and he's getting excited
about that. And I feel that
transition, that we've
gone from this one mode of
expression, and we've suddenly
opened the gates where
the, like, the color spectrum is so
much wider. I'm seeing more. And it's
perhaps because the way I became
a programmer. I did not become
a programmer because a deep
love of if statements.
I became a programmer
because I wanted programs.
I wanted things to exist that
did not exist. And at first,
I had to learn how to
program to make that happen.
Then I happened to fall in love with
programming as a craft, and then I spent two
decades really diving deep on that. But now
I'm back. I'm back to having an idea and
being impatient beyond belief
to see it exist in the world,
and AI has just shrunk that down to
almost nothing. So it's an acceleration
of a rediscovery.
Now, I understand that that's not true
for everyone. There are plenty of
programmers who just loved programming right
from the beginning, and they were attracted
to the logical constructs and so forth. I mean,
I've been there for two decades, so I get
it. But I also think that you're able
to discover new sides of yourself-
... if you let it in. Again,
I keep coming back to this
almost regret minimization framework,
to borrow Jeff Bezos's terms here.
Are you gonna look at yourself two
years from now and think, "Oh, I spent
my time well being pissy
about the present,
about the fact that my
industry changed"? Or
Would I two years from now look
back upon this moment and be proud
of myself for leaning in,
for maybe having a moment of
grief? Again, there's room for all
of it. And then going, "I'm gonna
learn how the world spins now, and I'm
gonna make not just the best of it, I'm
gonna make more of it."
- I mean, it is true, a lot of
programmers, a lot of friends of mine,
me, obviously you, are having fun.
- I have had more fun with computers in
the last three months than at any time
previously.
- Quick bathroom break, and
then I gotta ask you about
how you actually interact
with the systems now.
- Yes.
- I gotta ask you about how has your
programming setup changed? So keyboard,
voice, what's the IDE?
- It's crazy to think about now, but yeah,
I used TextMate for almost 20 years.
I used TextMate starting in
2005, I think. I helped get the
first version out, and then I just
wasn't interested. I wasn't in the
market for an alternative. And
it wasn't until the switch to Linux that
I was forced out of my habitat. And
now with the switch to,
what are we calling it? Agentic engineering?
Oh, I fucking hate that term. We gotta
come up with something that sounds
as plain as programming, but
encapsulates the fact that
it's with agents. But-
- I still think it should be called
programming at this point.
- ... All right, let's just
call it programming.
Programming with agents requires a
different tool set. It really does.
And the main change here is that
you're going from single thread programming
in your head to parallel processing.
When I was writing code, chiseling it
by hand in TextMate or even Neovim,
Not that long ago, I would just focus
on one problem at the time, and
I would methodically work my way through it,
and that was actually the portal to flow.
The portal to flow was deep,
immersion into a single problem,
see it through to the end.
That's not how it works with
agents, in part because the
agents are at once both too fast and too
slow. They don't give you an immediate
reply on something that you
asked them to do that's the
same as typing on a keyboard. So
you have to let the agent cook-
... for a bit, and therefore
you realize, well,
if I just sit around waiting for them,
first of all, that doesn't feel productive.
Even if the agent, just one of them, can be
highly productive, it does not feel productive.
It does not feel good. It feels actually
like you're a little bit useless.
And maybe I had a moment,
when the first agentic moment was
there and we, I was running mostly
one agent at a time where I felt
like, "I don't know about this."
But you can solve a lot of
hard problems by simply
throwing more resources at it.
This is the whole scaling law of
AI of itself, right? That
if you parallelize these
things and you're not running one
agent, but you're running a handful,
you can feel like you're in a flow
state because you're constantly doing
programming work in the sense that you're
making decisions, and you're helping either
unblock an agent because it has a question
about which direction to take, or
you're ready for a new task. And
to do that, you need a different
setup. I started first
doing it in tmux and just
having separate panes and having
separate splits. Basically,
a terminal with tabs is a good way to think
about it. You open a bunch of tabs. I think
most humans know exactly how that
works. They don't work in just one tab.
- So still sticking to the terminal, CLI.
- Absolutely.
- So you're not using
Claude Code app or the-
- No.
- ... Codex app or the-
- I love the fact that this
agent revolution was kicked
off in the terminal because I was
already a huge fan of TUIs, terminal
user interfaces, and the terminal
in general. That feels like a,
a really nice place to be. It's a
beautiful place to be. The modern terminal
is just a good-looking place to
work. So I like that. And then
this fact of having multiple
agents, especially once it's not
just multiple agents running on your own
machine, but you start running multiple
machines. Now tmux alone is not enough to
keep track of it, and that's why as
of late I've switched to this thing
called Herdr. And Herdr is
essentially tmux plus agent
notifications. So whenever your agent is
done and needs something for you, it goes
ding, a little bell telling
you it's ready for its human,
uh... Is it master or servant?
I'm not quite sure always.
But it is ready for a decision,
and it also keeps track of
these is it in working mode or not.
So I have this Herdr set up. I have
multiple Herdr setups actually
running on individual machines.
I went on this crazy phase
just about a month ago
realizing that doing this
work on a single machine is
not fast enough. It's like I've discovered
multi-core programming, but I only have two
cores. I'm like, "What if I had 16 cores?
What if I had 32 cores? What if I had
64 cores?" So I instantly went
out and I bought these amazing
KVMs called GL.iNet Comets.
And what they do is it's this
little box. You plug in HDMI, you
plug in USB and connect it
to the computer. It's like a
KVM. So a KVM is a remote way
of controlling a computer, but
what's special about this is just how
easy it was. You connect this thing in,
you go to a webpage, log in once, set one
password. Now this thing
can hop on your tailnet.
This has been the other revolution of
the last year for me, is discovering
these WireGuard networks. Uh, Tailscale
is essentially turning all the
computers you have into a local
network wherever you are.
Like right now on my phone, I
have direct access to all the
computers in my Malibu office. I also have
access to all my computers
in my Copenhagen office.
And I can treat them as though I sat
right next to them without having to
punch holes in a firewall
or set up complicated VPNs.
And what this does is it just
decreases the friction it
takes to get new compute online.
So as soon as I discovered this, I looked
at my closet, and I realized I had a bunch
of mini PCs from prior experiments, and I
just said, "What if I just connected all of
them?" And I just connected
four of the computers-
... in a closet. They all
had their little Comet, and
suddenly I could run agents on
more computers at the same time,
and I could control them all with Herdr.
And it did get to a point where I
maxed out my own processing power.
That I think at about... What do we want
to put it? About four to five machines
running, I don't know, three agents. I have
about 16 threads. That's what I can run.
And the faster the agents run, of course, the fewer
threads I can run, but at the current pace, I can run
about 16 threads-
- Mm-hmm, at full acceleration.
And that's part of why I've gone
from just being excited about
the agent moment to
being delirious. Because
I think as you say, some of
it is a little assaulting.
Again, we're on a dial-up bandwidth-wise
with our computer. I mean,
it's actually hilarious. So you think of
I'm sitting here a year ago, right? I'm
chiseling my code. Yeah.
- I'm writing my lines. And over the course
of, like, an hour, I will have written
one beautiful controller, one beautiful
model. Like, that's one file.
And I've really worked on it, right?
So maybe there's 60 lines left. So
maybe my bandwidth at this
moment is, like, 30 lines
an hour. I think that's even high.
Maybe it's 20 lines an hour. Now I'm
running 16 threads. I'm producing at some
times hundreds of lines of hour
or hundreds of lines of code
per hour. Now, let me pause
myself there for a hot moment.
I hate that metric, right? Like,
lines of code is a stupid metric
in general to measure these things,
and I think it's right from
some in the programming community
to ridicule the AI psychosis when
everyone talks about the number of lines of
code they're writing, and then you ask them,
"What did you build?" And
they're like, "Well, I..."
And then no good answer comes out, right?
- It's just a nice shorthand to-
- It is a nice shorthand. It is a
representation or encapsulation
of how much output that's coming out.
Now, whether the output is good or bad-
... is not a referendum on that. But I was
producing and producing so much more now,
right? And therefore I'm able to
keep all these threads going.
So that's the setup. It's still
Neovim, but at this point,
I'm not writing a lot of code, so I'm
using Neovim as a project browser
and then as a way to kick off
Lazy Git to see the change
log for what's there.
And even that, I'd say
if GitHub was a little faster at showing
you your pull request, the web is
probably actually a nicer place to do that.
I don't know. There's also this other tool
I've been playing with a bit
called Hunk, which just produces
Diffs in a really nice way. So you could look
at that too. But I find that when I look
at Hunk, I only see the change
set, and when I'm reviewing
output from an agent, I often want to see
the surrounding context. Oh, yeah, so it
changed this file, but actually, what do we have in
this other file that wasn't touched but maybe should've
been touched? So that's why I still
like Neovim as a way of doing
it. But it's all happening,
by the way, of course, in
Amachi. So it's all happening on
Linux. And this was the other major
breakthrough with agents. Agents love the
Unix philosophy. It loves individual tools
that it can invoke through the command
line, and there is no operating system
on Earth of the majors, I'm
counting three here, Mac, Windows,
Linux, that works as well with that
mechanism as Linux. Everything
in Linux is either a config
file or a CLI tool. Now, that was its
main drawback five minutes ago. This
was the reason people didn't like
Linux. It's like it's all
config files and CLI tools.
What great irony that the universe
has played it upon us that now the
drawbacks of Linux five minutes ago
are now its major selling points.
This was one of the things I thought
I was stuck for a weekend with a Mac
four months ago.
I thought I had a computer at the place I
was going that was a Linux machine, so I
didn't bring my laptop, and I found out
when I arrived I only had a Mac Mini.
So I was gonna make the best
of a bad situation here and,
Set up my Mac in some of the ways
I've been thinking about with,
With Linux. And you can actually
do a lot now. Homebrew has gotten
really quite good. Homebrew is the
missing package manager for the Mac,
and no one has done more to
move the Mac forward in terms
of ease of setup. But still
something as simple as
Raycast, I don't know if
you've used that. That's the-
There's no config file that you can
just access. You have to go into the
GUI, export a file, then take that file,
I don't know, in your freaking
backpack on a USB key.
And then you can import it somewhere else.
You cannot automate the entire setup of your
machine. You can't automate at all the
configuration of Mac's default key bindings.
That has to be a manual process where
you're clicking with a mouse like a
caveman to set up your machine.
- I mean, there's ways around it.
- Not good ones. I looked. I tried hard
- So here's my, been my journey.
Obviously I'm a Linux
person, but because of Adobe Premiere,
Adobe products, I'm also a Windows person,
so oftentimes I would use WSL,
Windows Subsystems for Linux.
So Linux inside Windows, which is... in
the agentic era is not a good kind of
Linux, 'cause it's just-
- It's a sandbox
- ... it's a sandbox, and you want the Linux
to be unleashed to be able to do everything.
- Correct.
- And so I have now woken up to
things like GrayCat, and have
you know, I'm a keyboard person.
Where's the config file? What, can I,
can I basically do
everything where an agent
can set everything up for me and
save the configuration so I can
replicate it across systems and
everything's automated? And so I had to
ask a lot of those questions,
and a lot of them are missing.
- They don't have good answers.
- But oftentimes you could actually
just build the app yourself.
- But there are hacks.
- Yeah, they're hacks.
- There are hacks.
You don't have to live like this, Lex.
There's a better... Actually, this is a great
moment.
- Until you have a video editor.
- So this is a good moment.
- Yep.
- Um, I heard it was your birthday.
So I brought a little gift.
- No.
- We are going to get you onto the
agentic operating system whether you
like it or not.
- This is awesome.
- And I asked- ... my friends at Dell
whether maybe they had a machine that,
um, I could get you for your birthday.
- Oh, no.
- So here's the machine I use- ... which is-
... well, the same one I use, but it's
now yours. It's a- ... Dell XPS 14-
... already set up with Omarchy 4- ...
ready to be configured for you. And
once you realize that all your...
By the way, we should almost time
this. You can be up and running.
You have to answer, like, five
questions in about one minute. You
could literally do it
live if you wanted to.
- Oh, Omarchy, beautiful, modern opinion
Linux by DHH. Yeah, let's do it.
- Yeah, fill it out while I talk. So-
... exactly what you realized,
that pain on the Mac
was the exposure I got for about a
weekend, and I tried really hard, and I
found some decent workarounds,
the main one being that Homebrew
now has tabs for GUI apps. Because it's
hilarious to think upon the
recent past where people
would go to websites, like,
"I need Zoom." They would
enter zoom.com, find the
download link, download
a DMG- ... double-click
on that, see a weird
manual interaction telling
them to drag an icon
from one place of the screen to the other,
and that was how you installed apps.
And you'd just do that over and over again
until you had all the apps that you wanted,
and if you were setting up a new machine
and you had, like, 12 apps, you'd go to
12 different websites to download
them like a total caveman.
Homebrew has solved a lot of that, but it
has not solved all of it, and has solved
nothing in terms of the-
- Sorry to interrupt, but look
how fast this is going.
- Oh, it's gonna be done
in about 40 seconds.
And then you're gonna
be inside of Omarchy.
- Super is the Windows or Command key on your
keyboard. So which one is the Super key?
- Yep, that's the Windows key. Oh, actually,
no, no, you have a special edition.
There are only about six of
these computers in the world.
- Oh, there's a Super key.
- It says Super, and look at where the
Copilot key is on the other end of the
keyboard. That's the Omarchy logo.
- Nice. Okay, cool.
- This was Spencer Bull at Dell,
who I've been working with on a
lot of this stuff.
They've been incredible.
- They, for a moment, let
go of the XPS brand.
- Yes, they did, last year.
- And I was like, "This is dumb.
This is... XPS is awesome."
- It was not just dumb that it got rid
of the XPS branding. They also got
rid of the Escape key and put in
capacitive touch buttons at the
top. The mistake that Apple
realized like three years ago was
terrible, and everyone
hated them for them.
But now they have an
incredible team, and this
was actually my first
Dell laptop for myself.
Because I've been using Dell on our
servers. Dell was what powered our
cloud exit. We've been running
Dell since the mid-2000s, I
think. But I never ran their
laptops, because compared to a
MacBook, they just weren't
up to the task for me. The
XPS' from 2016, or from 2026, with those
Intel Panther Lake chips,
are the first Dells
that I would personally actually use. And
it's funny because when I got mad at Apple
originally, I thought, like, "Do you know what? I
should just get a Dell," because we already used
them and whatever, and I got a Dell, and I
was like, "Man, I can't do it. I can't do it.
It's not good enough." And
then lo and behold, this year
they just fixed everything.
They fixed the battery life.
They fixed the performance.
They fixed the compatibility. They
fixed the weight. They fixed the
screen. That's a tandem OLED screen-
- Yeah, that's incredible.
- ... which means it's actually better
tech than what you'll get in a freaking
MacBook. It's lighter than a MacBook,
and the chip is finally
competitive because Intel spent
a good five years developing the
18A process node. It took a long
time, but now it's here, and
it's freaking incredible. We finally
have competition to Apple M chips-
... that can go as long as on battery
and can have competitive performance.
- And there's a beautiful default theme to
this thing, and then what is it? Super
Space opens up.
- Actually, you can just push the Omarchy key.
It opens up the menu. So now you control
everything from there.
- Oh, same thing as the Super. Okay.
- Yeah.
- Cool.
- Same thing as Super Space. So this has
been a huge change for me, that we finally
have Linux machines that you
don't have to make excuses for.
Because I don't mind making excuses
because excuses are really just another
word for trade-offs.
I love that Framework 13 I think
I talked about last time. I still
like them. They still make good computers.
But I think for a lot of people, they
didn't want a DIY experience. They
wanted something that just out of the
box felt like it was on
par in build quality and
whatever with Macs, and now we
finally have it. So happy birthday.
- Thank you so much. An Omarchy Dell
laptop from DHH is the best birthday
present. This is awesome.
- Check the screensaver, by the way.
- Yeah, it's kind of amazing. I'm seeing it.
- On that tandem OLED screen-
- It's gorgeous.
- ... it is absolutely
mind-bogglingly awesome.
- Look at that. There's like a
retro look to the whole thing.
- Totally.
- It's like Fiverr pop-
- It's like running a bulletin board
system in- ... the '90s, which is
exactly what I did when I was
14 years old. So for me, it's a
complete throwback and an awesome
aesthetic, combining this sense of modern
rising culture in Unix with-
... this throwback of the '90s.
- Yeah, like a retro look
for an agent first OS.
- Exactly.
- It's crazy.
- Which again, pairs... This was
why I was so excited that-
... all these agent harnesses
arrived as TUI's, arrived as CLIs-
... has arrived as a
terminal because suddenly,
a whole new generation of both
programmers and regular users
discovered the glory of the terminal. The
terminal was actually one of the most,
impressive and productive
user interfaces we can have.
Now, we've built user interfaces
since then that were easier to learn.
The mouse is a wonderful invention for
letting someone who doesn't know a lot about
computers just click around and find things out, but
the terminal is for people who want to
learn their systems, who want
to learn the keyboard commands.
- So you think the TUI
is gonna stick around?
- 100%. Now, it's not gonna be the only
thing. Of course it's not, because
these labs now have trillion-dollar
valuations, so they need to be able to
reach billions of people.
And I don't think we're gonna teach billions
of people the intricacies of the TUI.
So we're gonna have other tools, and we
already have other tools, which is, by
the way, one of the sweet things
about Linux, the ChatGPT Codex tool.
- Yeah, I saw that.
- Literally within two hours of that
announcement dropping, I had it wrapped
up and ready to go in Omakub.
Already now, if you go to... You can
actually hit the Omakub key-
... and then just write ChatGPT. It
should pop up as, like, install.
And then just hit return.
- Sudo password for Lex.
- Yeah, whatever you put in. And then it's just gonna
install it, and it's gonna pop it up, and you have
ChatGPT.
- Nice.
- And that's how a lot of the apps are, and
all the agentic harnesses are built in that
way.
Um, Tailscale, as I talked about, if you
wanna hop on that, is that way. Uh, Dropbox.
And the reason all these things are
in there is because I use them.
It's because I built this system for me,
and I thought, first and foremost, how do I
build my dream computer just
for me? And if I get my
dream computer, I am assured there are other
people who are gonna have the same dreams
as I do.
- Now, you're obsessed about getting
the installation to be under one
minute, and a bunch of people
asked you online why. So
Why? Why were you so obsessed
to getting the installation to
be less than 60 seconds?
- First, let me quote Mitchell
Hashimoto, who created
Ghostty terminal that's awesome and
also available on Omakub and was also
the founder of HashiCorp,
who had this great post on
X not too long ago that
had the killer line, "The
pursuit of excellence
deserves no explanation."
Wanting to make something as good and as
fast and as beautiful as possible has
no need for justification. We
should want beautiful, fast systems
that are a delight to use. Now, the funny
thing with the install time is it didn't
actually start with a one-minute
mission. I was being modest when it got
going. I thought if I could set up
my entire system in 15 minutes,
it would already be such a dramatic
improvement over what came before it that I
would be perfectly happy. And it came
off the fact that the benchmarking
had been skewed so out of whack. You
talked about the Commodore 64 being
your first computer, right?
When you unwrap that Commodore
64 and you hit the on button,
in I think about less than one
second, the basic interpreter
was ready to accept your command.
It was literally almost instant.
There was virtually no boot time.
Do you know how long it took me
to set up a new Mac that I had
bought for actually the one
app that I still haven't vibe coded my way
into on Linux, which is Adobe Lightroom?
Brand-new computer, out of the box.
I set it up. There's a software
update. Before I was ready to
install Adobe Lightroom that I had it
fully up to date, it took 42 minutes.
That's grotesque. That's
absurd. That's an insult
to everyone who likes computers,
that you get a new computer and
before you can use it, you have
to spend 42 minutes doing updates
on something that was already installed
on it out of the box from the factory.
That is just preposterous, and it's
crazy that that's not even the
worst thing. I also got a PC, um,
because all these Linux machines,
they come as PCs, right?
- Right.
- And they have Windows pre-installed.
So I got one. This was just
three weeks ago. Brand-new machine,
Intel Panther Lake, the whole shebang.
An hour and 35 minutes
from unwrapping the thing until it's
ready to use. How long did you take
before you think you were in Omakub?
- I mean, it's less than a minute for sure.
- A minute.
We can build computers like this. We have
the technology. We've had the technology
since like 1981 when the
Commodore 64 first came
out. The fact that we now have a
computer that's a trillion times faster
and you have to spend 42 minutes or an hour
and a half setting it up before it's ready to
use is so infuriating to me that it
became a passion. And it's funny
Just while we were having a little break here,
I was talking to Ryan Hughes, my co-conspirator
here. We now have, we think,
a line where we can create
these special turbo images that are
pre-made for specific computers
because it relies on some
knowledge of the hardware, like
the Dell XPS. We're gonna
make a Dell XPS turbo
image that can install in about
12 seconds. A full Linux system
installed in about 12 seconds.
- That's incredible.
- That obsession is what gives me this
great satisfaction with using computers,
that we do not accept things the
way they are. And this is why this
agent-accelerated reality that I
now inhabit is so invigorating.
Because I can look at these kinds of
constraints and go, do you know what? Um,
I could have stopped when we were at five minutes.
That would already have been fast enough.
This was the argument on X, right?
Why do you keep going? Five minutes
is fast enough. Okay, maybe
for you, but for me, 12
seconds is a lot more fun. And
I always try to think
these first principles.
Okay, in that machine,
actually hit the Omarchy,
key again, and then do speed. You'll see a
list come up, and one of
them is, like, disk speed.
- Speed test, network speed, disk speed.
- Disk speed. Do do that
one, and then run it.
So this is testing the performance of the
built-in NVMe drive, and what are you
getting?
- Seven GB a second.
- So seven gigabytes a second. That's
how fast that drive is. Why can we
not install a Linux
distribution in one second?
The Omarchy distribution is 5.8 gigabytes.
If we can run at seven gig... Now, of
course, you can't actually do that
because the USB key is a lot slower
than that, but you should be able to
maximize the underlying physics
and protocols that we're dealing
with, and that's your goal. We gotta
get all the way back down to that.
- Yeah. I love that you're doing a Linux
distribution. 'Cause I mean, you could be
do... You could be building anything. But
the fact that you're building a Linux
distribution means you're rethinking
about what a computer is, 'cause a
operating system is the fundamental,
like, the foundation of how
... you interact with a computer.
- Yes. And it's been so stale.
- Yeah, it has.
- The macOS we have today is
scarcely different from the macOS we
had 10 years ago. In fact, it's worse
in many ways because Apple continues to
chokehold the control on
users. They don't want them to
install software that they
haven't already said good-
... to go for. They don't want
users to reconfigure their
hotkeys without doing it manually.
They didn't want to change the
500-millisecond animation
switching workspaces.
It is an infuriatingly
locked-down computer. Now,
to Apple's credit, it's a pretty
good computer for being locked down,
but I don't want a locked-down computer.
I wanna own my computer. Better
yet, I wanna mutate my computer,
and this is where the agentic
age needs a new operating system.
When you can vibe code whatever app
comes to your mind, you should be able
to vibe code your operating system. You should
be able to change anything, how it looks,
how it works, what panels are
there, what are not there, and that
requires Linux. As simple as that.
There are no... None of the other two
operating systems can deliver this.
- But can you speak to the, I think
somebody asked you, like, "Who the hell
are you to think you could do
better than Ubuntu?" For example.
Or, or like, "Why are you doing it when Ubuntu
is already pretty good?" And your answer
was, "I thought I could do better."
So can you speak to, this was on
X, can you speak to, like, where
the craziness comes from,
thinking that you as
one person or maybe with Ryan, you
could start building something that's
going to be better than Ubuntu
or Arch or any of this?
- Well, I'll say that it
didn't start quite as
grandiose. When I got going with
my Linux journey, I actually just
started with Ubuntu, and I just
built on top of it. Here's a
system that already does a lot of the
things I wanted to do, and at least it's
Linux. So can I just build on top of it and make
it more modern, make it actually look good,
and have the programs I wanna use?
I got, like, some version of that,
and then I discovered that there's seven
layers deeper you could go, and as, the
closer you get to the metal, the closer you
get to the kernel, the closer you get to the
individual packages and so
forth, the more freedom you
discover. So as I discovered more and
more freedom, I got more and more
ambitious, and I realized, oh, surprise,
surprise, I have strong opinions about
how computers should work, how they
should look, what programs
should be installed, and
whether they should take
42 minutes to install or
45 seconds. That's the current
world record, by the way.
So if anyone installs Omarchy Quattro
after this and can beat 45 seconds,
take a screenshot, send it to me, and you'll
be the new holder of the world record.
- When, how long ago did you
cross the 60-second mark?
- It's funny because it's like
that the old limit on, what was it? It
was a four-minute mile or something-
- Yeah. Uh-huh
- ... like that in 1952-
... that people thought was impossible for
humans to beat. Then one guy beats it,
and literally within the next few
months, three more guys do, right?
So we had this goal. I originally
had the goal it was two minutes.
And then we beat two minutes, and I'm like,
"Well, if we beat two minutes, why can't we beat
one minute?" And I remember thinking
like, "That'd be crazy. You can't
install a modern operating system
in one minute when they're all..."
If the other ones are taking
42 minutes, right? Like Apple,
full of a lot of smart people, like, it took
42 minutes, so that's gotta be the bar.
No, no, it's not the bar because there's
no speed limit. Like, none of the things
you take for granted are fixed
pillars of reality in almost
any case. Until you get
down to the seven gigabytes
per second that drive is able to transfer,
you've not reached the limit yet,
so you should just keep pushing.
And of course, then it becomes a game
in itself and a satisfaction itself.
Every second I could shave off was an
excitement. And when we broke the one-minute
barrier, which was really
only broken, I think,
three weeks ago or something like that,
maybe even two weeks ago, I just got crazy.
And then I got a swarm of agents
to run all these auto research
loops of trying all these different theories
on like, oh, if you change this thing, if you
change that thing, what if you cut this out? What
if you do things in parallel? What if while you
were typing in your username, we start
preloading packages into memory system, we
can fire them in faster. And it becomes a
fun game. And I think that's how you should think
about product development. It should be fun.
You should, it should be frivolous.
It should be trying to overshoot
the target and making it so much better
than what it quote unquote needs to be.
- Especially now because you can move so quickly and
you can try so many different approaches because of
the agents.
- Yes, that just makes it more satisfying. But I
think this was always true. If you look at the
greatest Mercedes-Benz of all time,
I think it was called the W126.
I saw this wonderful documentary on it.
It was steered by this guy who for years
had worked in Mercedes'
department for safety.
And suddenly he gets put in charge
for the whole S-Class project, and he
just puts in all of it. This is where
you got the auto-retending seat
belts and washers on the headlights and
everything. This car was so
overbuilt for the market.
It was unbelievable. But you look at
that and go like, "Well, I want that."
In just the same way that you look at a
mechanical watch and go, "It
could go down to 100 meters?"
Or I think Rolex has one that can
go down to 4,000 meters, the,
the deep ocean, the deep diver
ocean ... or whatever it's called.
No one outside of three people in the
world, whoever buy that watch, will
ever put it to the test. But don't
you wanna be the kind of person who
is a patron of people who wanna
push the human race that much
forward? I want the fastest car
breaking the speed limits. I want the
diver watch that can go down
the Mariana Trench. I want
the operating system that can
install in less than 60 seconds.
- So from the individual level,
I admire those people. I think
everybody should strive for that. But
also the consequences of that we should
mention, like the pursuit of excellence,
even when the metrics seem to be frivolous,
the maybe unexpected consequences
of that is other kinds of
excellences, discoveries, innovations, and all
that kind of stuff that has nothing to do with the
speed.
- 100%.
- It's discovery. It's nice to
have the metric that you're
chasing be the catalyst,
the engine that drives
innovation, because you'll just discover. It's
the same reason you go to the moon, you go to
Mars. It's like, why? Who cares? Well,
actually, the real thing
is you'll discover a lot
about chemical propulsion.
You'll discover a lot
about how humans can live for a long time
in space. Maybe you'll discover whole
new ways of doing solar energy in
space or data centers in
space or whatever the hell.
- That's right.
- All kinds of... Maybe you'll meet--
- That's right
- ...aliens, but you never
know. But setting a goal
and chasing it, especially when
it's numerical, is really nice.
- And setting a grand goal
is even better. When you
refuse to just do what's practical and
you strive for what's slightly beyond
plausible, that's when the
magic happens. And we should be
going all in on that. This is one of the
reasons... And in fact, to some degree,
this specific goal was motivated
by seeing others do this. I mean,
Elon is the singular individual
in this conversation.
The guy is so out there in his goals.
They seem so preposterous at
first glance. I've certainly
considered them preposterous on many
glances. And then you realize that
they come true sometimes. Maybe
not always on schedule, and so
what? So what? So we didn't get
the self-driving car on schedule.
I gave Elon a lot of shit for that
back in '17. But now it's here,
and who would have gotten us here except
for the person who thought it was
possible in '17, who is so
impatient with reality that the
sheer force is just gonna propel
that reality to the place he
wants it to be. I think that's deeply
inspiring, and we need these kinds of,
goalposts to be moved. We need
someone to run the four-minute
mile, so the rest of us realize,
"Well, okay, but I guess I can run it
quicker." That's what I try to strive
for, and I really strive for with Omarchy
because
it's just more fun to live that way, to
have high aspirations and ambitions. And I
will say I've actually changed my mind on that
a little bit. I spent quite a lot of time
speaking the other book that there are a
lot of people who don't actually need those
ambitions. And I also-- That's
also true. We don't want
8 billion Elons running around the
world. Would be rather crazy, I think.
But I've come to realize
that for entrepreneurs,
it's healthy to have suitable chunky goals.
The idea of just running the Italian
restaurant can't just be
that. It should be maybe
I just run the one Italian restaurant,
but I make the best damn pizza
possible. I make the
most delicious Parmesan.
We have to strive for excellence to
muster the motivation to keep going.
- And yeah, to dare to think big
like you could build a Linux-
- Yes
- ... distribution.
Is there some stuff you remember
about what it took to get us to be
so fast? You mentioned a few things
that were, the agents were discovering.
- One of the things was to treat the
... lag of human input as an
opportunity to preload. So--
Hmm ... there's five questions you answer
when- Yeah ... you set up an Omarchy machine.
So it's doing stuff in the background. We're doing stuff
in the background. And that was one of the things I didn't
even consider, which is, I mean,
the oldest trick in the book.
All sorts of video games for a long
time have done this, where you let the
player interact with something, and then you
do preloading and so forth in the background.
So it's an age-old technique, but I just
hadn't thought about it for an installer.
I thought, first you ask the user some
questions about their password and their
username and their time zone and so
forth, and then you do the work,
when, in fact, you could preload that. Now,
the other things were just a bunch of other
tweaks to how the installer itself
was doing things in a certain order.
Some of them was also just shrinking it.
The last version of
Omarchy was 7.5 gigabytes,
and a lot of the time we're
down to now is literally
decompressing compressed package
files. That's the bulk of what is
on the ISO, and that's the bulk of the install
time. So by shrinking it down to, I think we're
at 5.85 gigabytes now, a
pretty chunky reduction,
it almost literally translated one-to-one, and
I did some really interesting things there.
So Omarchy uses the
JetBrains font, which is
an awesome font, beautiful font,
and actually a font I didn't like
at first glance, but then it was
the only font I could get to look
perfect in Mitchell
Hashimoto's Ghostty. Ghostty,
for whatever reason, did not
wanna render my beloved Bitstream
Vera Sans just the way I was used
to it. Mm-hmm. But it rendered
this JetBrains font perfectly,
so I switched over. But it...
The standard package for
JetBrains font on Arch
is 200 megabytes because it includes
all these variations and all
these subtypes and whatever.
And I realized, like, we're not using
any of that. We're using the monospace
version in this one Nerd,
uh- Yep... font patched
edition. Do you know how big that
is? I think it's 16 megabytes. Hmm.
So I simply just came up with a
new package, the slim version-
Mm-hmm... of the JetBrains package. Nice. And
there, right there, I saved 180 megabytes.
I just went through and did that a bunch
of times. We did that with the NVIDIA
drivers too. So the NVIDIA drivers, when
they came straight off the, I think the
Arch repo, were not compressed
with the most extreme form
of compression, which I think
called ZSTD, which is a
really slow form of compression. It's slow to
create the archive, but if you're building a
package- Hmm... you have all the time in the
world if that means you can then shrink the ISO.
So on just the two NVIDIA
packages, I think we saved
200 megabytes. Mm-hmm. So
what I loved about this
was I imagined myself
being a car designer at
McLaren. So McLaren makes
some of the lightest
super sports cars in the world right now,
and they are absolutely
obsessed with shaving every
damn last gram off their cars. That's
why even a new 750S McLaren is just way
lighter than the competition.
They use a carbon fiber
monocoque, and that helps them over
like Ferrari, for example, that's
uses aluminum. But they also just have this
obsession with weight, and I would see this
interview with the McLaren folks talking
to some journalist just going over, "Yeah,
we saved, uh- ... 370
grams- Yeah ... off that
one." And I just went, "Wait, what?
There's someone on a car that weighs maybe
1,040 kilos or 1,380 or something.
They're s- They're worrying about
370 grams?" Yeah. What obsessed
maniacs. Hmm. I love them. Yeah. I want
that in my life. I want a McLaren-
... just for that reason. So I thought
in that moment as I was shaving
individual megabytes off the
packages, man, I'm kinda
like a McLaren car developer here, even though- Yeah
... I mean, we haven't even completed that work.
The package could shrink even
more. But this is actually this
other conflict that we've had with
Omarchy and the traditional Linux
community is bloat. Mm-hmm. This idea that
it's actually not kosher in
certain circles to ship with
pre-installed software because
who are you to make decisions
about what programs people
should use? And I'm like, "Dude,
it's in the fucking name. It's called
Omarchy because the Oma part is
short for omakase, which
literally means chef's choice.
I'm the chef. I'm making the
choices, and this is the
collection of applications I think is
awesome," which by the way has a video
editor. It ships with OBS- Mm-hmm ...
to do your recording. It's just in
there. Yeah. OBS is pre-installed.
Nice. Kdenlive is a
video editor, timeline editor, which is great.
I edit all my videos with that. And then I made
my own clip editor. You talked
about the thing with syncing up.
Yeah. I had this thing with clips, so I would
do a podcast or whatever. I need a clip for X.
Mm-hmm. And it's kind of a hassle to use Kdenlive
or other- Mm-hmm ... timeline editors, so I made
Omacut. Mm-hmm. Omacut is included too. Omacut,
cool. It's just for making clips, and you can
drive the whole thing with keyboard. So you
can go to just the right time mark- Mm-hmm ...
and then you can hit Control + Space.
Hmm. It moves the clip line to that line.
Then you go to- Nice ... the end of the clip, and
you hit Alt + Space, and it moves the end line.
Nice. And then you hit Control + S, and
it saves. Nice. I can make clips so damn
fast now with Omacut. It's amazing. But
it has all the software on it. It
has Neovim on it. It has Herder
on it. It has Tmux. It has a
terminal. It has a bunch of
themes. It has a bunch of background
images, the best ones I could pick
out. That takes up some space. It should
because this is not supposed to be this
just barren landscape where you have to reconstruct
everything. Mm-hmm. This is supposed to be
a productive system the minute you
unpack it. What is it built in?
So it's actually mostly
built in Bash for the
Linux configuration part. Right.
Bash is a great language for that.
It is made for that really,
for system administration.
It also has its limitations. You
should not build everything in Bash
- How are agents with
generating Bash? Pretty good?
- Oh, amazing. Except for one thing,
and I have to smack the agents over the back
of the head every single time I catch it,
and remind it to look at the agent's
MD file, because I will have an
instruction in there not
to make early exits.
The agents love to have preconditions
instead of fully expanded conditionals.
I like something that says,
"If this, then do that."
Agents like to have precondition or
exit, another precondition or exit.
And then it falls down to the final
thing it actually wants to do. I hate
that style. So except
for that, it's gotten
shockingly, dramatically,
awesomely good, to the
point where when we talked last time, we
talked about how I would ask the agent
for a Bash thing, and then I would type it
in myself, and I kinda wouldn't remember.
And then I took the effort to make sure that
all that competence wasn't draining out of my
fingers, so I actually learned how to
write Bash myself, and now I'm not
writing any Bash myself. I have not written any Bash
myself for probably a couple months, because the
agents have just gotten so good, that
if you give them the few pointers on
style, and occasionally put pushback
on complexity... This is...
I tweeted about this a couple of
days ago. It blows my mind how
often an agent can do something, say
it's done, have the work reviewed by
another agent-
... they say it's done, and then I go like,
"Eh, looks a little too complicated for me."
And then it'll go like, "Oh, yeah,
you're right. You're right. I totally
overcomplicated this," and it'll cut
it in half. I'm like, "Couldn't it
just do this, like, from the outset?"
And then someone else reminded me,
humans are the same way. If
you work on something and
someone else reviews it and they just are like, "Eh,
it looks a little complicated," quite often you're
able to go like, "Ah, you're right."
- See, that, that just... Those
little indications to me
show that the programmer is still needed,
that intuition, 'cause I think, what, what
did you say? I have a sense of the landscape
of the code.
- When I build something like Omarchy, I, I
do look at the code. I look at the shape.
And I look at the proportions.
Like, I don't have to chisel everything myself
anymore. This is, again, when I'm flattering
myself for... Not one
moment I'm a McLaren audio,
uh auto engineer, and the next
moment I'm a da Vinci, working
with his whole studio of students-
... who are doing all the chiseling on the,
the fine marble, right? And he goes like,
"Ah, no, the proportions are not quite
right." That's how it feels working with
agents now. That I can give
feedback like an editor.
That, do you know what? I'm not gonna write
everything myself, but I can tell you
when the argument doesn't land. I
can tell you when the shape isn't
proportional to the problem, or when it
just feels like it's too complicated. And
shockingly often, it just works. It's
like the early days, where the jokes was,
"Don't make mistakes." I don't think you have to
tell the agents that anymore, because now the
harnesses are so good, they run automated
testing. They get that feedback. But
you actually do have to tell
them, "Make it simpler."
- Do you use voice at all for the interaction?
Or are you... How much are you typing?
How much are you-
- I type the whole thing. I actually,
in Omarchy's built-in Voxtype-
... Audio transcription, and it's
actually really good. I just find that
I don't think that way, and
it surprised myself that I
don't like to talk to the computer.
Uh, I like when I'm in the car, but when
I'm in front of the keyboard, I just
wanna type. I also just love
typing. Are you using the voice?
- I'm an introvert who doesn't like social
interaction- ... or speaking. And-
- I think that's part of mine too.
- But, like, for me, for some reason,
voice is really powerful. I want
to give this... So I, I run with
this thing. It's called Plaud. So
I, I just hook it up on my,
you know on my T-shirt here.
You press a button, it starts
recording. And this is actually more,
in terms of flow, much better experience
than behind a computer. And I,
uh, save, well, usually
it's agent gen- generated
problems that I wanna really talk through.
And so I write, I speak a long prompt,
like, and a lot of it, it's like stream
of consciousness reasoning. So I'll
sometimes just change my mind about a
design, but all of that is in there,
and then I have an LLM that processes
that. With Plaud, there's a,
obviously an API. You can grab it,
transcribe it, clean up the transcript,
'cause you, you want it to be...
'Cause I'm referring to files.
I'm referring to technical
concepts, like files and functions-
... and so on, that you wanna
make sure the transcription, the-
... the speech-to-text gets correctly. So you wanna
have a dictionary. You want it to be aware of the code
base when you process the files.
And then you have this gigantic
thing that's often 10, 15,
20 minute me discussing the
full design, and I find that to be
really, really powerful.
Because it doesn't have the
problem overs- of
overspecification because of how
much stream of consciousness
thinking the system has
about what you're imagining.
And this is really good
for the early steps of a design. Like,
if I wanted to build Omarchy from
scratch, the first stages, I
talk through. It could be an
hour. There's been prompts that I had
for an hour, and I'm just running and-
- That's amazing
- ... and speaking. I highly
recommend people try a voice-based-
- So-
- ... speaking for prolonged
periods of time.
- I haven't actually-
- As opposed to very specific
- ... I haven't, yeah, I haven't used it that,
and maybe that's how I'm using it wrong.
I try to just type or
speak two sentences, and
then I get a little frustrated
that I could've typed that just as
fast maybe. But I have not
tried this whole thing of just
talking continuously for 20 minutes.
- And especially you because
you speak very fast.
- Yeah. No, I could see it. I think because
the reason I've been, I've been trying to
do it for things like replying to emails,
and it got to a point
where I thought it could
help. And it sort of did, but then it would
make a small mistake, and I'd have to
correct the mistake. But if you're doing
stream of conscious to an LLM who doesn't
care about all this other stuff anyway-
... that probably works way better.
- There's two things you have to do.
One, okay, you have the raw audio,
transcribes it. I use ElevenLabs for
transcription. They're probably the best
speech-to-text model.
There's still mistakes there, so you
need to have a prompt that has a-
access to a dictionary and to a lot of-
- How do you build the dictionary?
- First of all, there's a dictionary of terms
that are relevant to you. Then have it
aware of... So you have an agent that looks
through, when you're talking about code,
looks through your entire code base for
key terms that you use often. Also, when
we're talking about messaging, Gmail, and
WhatsApp, and so on, it's aware of all the
people and common terms
that you get wrong.
- You've really gone deep in this.
- That, to me, is a problem
that needs to be solved-
... because, uh, one of the issues
you probably have speech to text
is that it makes mistakes sometimes.
- Correct. Then I can't use
it for dictating an email.
- Right. If it never makes mistakes, you-
- Then it would be more appealing.
- Yeah, and you are okay being
not perfectly real time,
actually. You're okay
waiting five seconds-
... potentially. I don't know what your
use case is. I'm okay waiting five
seconds- ... 10 seconds for
it to process everything.
- You gotta vibe code this into an app
that does all of this such that-
... it just works.
- I think I mentioned to you offline
that it's very surprising to me that,
translation is not done perfectly.
Speech-to-speech translation.
- It seems like you've gotten much closer to
the best of what's possible by putting all
these things together.
- But, you know, when you're shipping that
kind of stuff, you do have to start
thinking about latency.
- Don't let the perfect be
the enemy of good. I mean,
if you're suddenly enabling something people
wouldn't be doing before at all, it's okay to
take five seconds longer. I think this
is one of the areas that Steve Jobs was
so good, that he realized, like,
the first iPhone was terrible
in all sorts of ways, right? Absolutely
horrendously slow data connection, very
underpowered, all the things.
But the product was so
compelling that it just didn't
matter. You'd be shipping
too late if you waited until everything
was just right, just perfect.
If you're solving a problem that people
currently don't have a solution for, they're
willing to give it five seconds.
If you're in a competitive market, yeah, okay, it's different.
But that means the problem's already solved, and you
don't need to solve it.
- Mm-hmm. Well, I do think there's a few...
So, like, Whisper Flow is really good.
A few people have stepped up
that speech-to-text thing.
- Yeah. Yeah, we're using
Voxtype. But others have-
- Uh, Vo-Voxtype is open source?
- It is. It's just using one of the open
models. I forget which parrot model
it's using or something like that. It
works quite well for short commands, so I
have used it for that. Uh, I
think you just hold down F9-
... and it starts a dictation.
- Oh, so it's already in there?
- You just have to get online.
It'll offer you to install-
- Got it
- ... the Voxtype package.
- Got it. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Because the Voxtype package includes
a model that's 150 megabytes, and I
was like, "Ah."
- Yep, yep.
- "I don't know if I can carry that." So-
- Yep
- ... we don't have that in there by
default, but we have the option set up.
And I actually just yesterday was thinking
we really need to combine all
of these things. So Omarchy
Quattro is truly amazing
as a malleable operating
system where you can add functionality
to it just by talking to your agent.
But that's exactly what we should be
doing. There's a lot of people who would
find it very natural just to talk
to their computer and say, "Hey,
can you make me a stock panel?
I wanna track Apple and Dell,"
and just see the agent go off
through, entirely through voice, both in
terms of the input and in terms of the
output, and then your operating system
just changes. This was the vision
of Iron Man and Jarvis and-
- Yeah
- ... bespoke applications that just appear
magically. I'm thinking the
area of AI I find truly
intriguing are these live gaming models, I
don't know if you've seen that, where the
AI's inventing literally the
next frame, but you can actually
play the game. And I think if they're
able to do that, why can't we do
that with our operating system? Why
can't we just talk to it and ask it
to be a different way or change, and
it'll all just change? I think this, by
the way, is one of the other
breakthroughs that is going to lead to
the total domination of Linux. The agents
have taken all the hardship out of
diagnosing Linux systems and turned
the fact that Linux produces
these overly specific, totally arcane error
messages into its greatest advantage.
When Linux has an issue,
the agent can take that very specific error
message that makes no sense to a normal
human and correlate it with the fact
that the agent was pre-trained on
40 million lines of Linux code, so it knows
exactly where to look and dial it down.
- Yeah.
- I have not had a single problem
on my Linux machine since
the beginning of this year that an
agent could not diagnose. That was
not true a year and a half ago.
A year and a half ago, I was
still searching on forums- ... to
find answers to esoteric questions.
Now the agents know the source code
of not just the Linux operating
system, but every single piece of
software I have on that box. The agent
has access to the source code of all of it.
In fact, this was one thing I built in just
before we, uh, we shipped. So once
you set up your default agent-
... Omarchy Quattro has
a crash watcher. If
any app on your machine
crashes, it'll pop up a little
thing, ask you whether you want
your AI to diagnose the problem.
- Yeah. That's amazing.
- Unbelievable. I've seen
things where there's an
error in some subsystem. Some, some...
Not even Linux, just some app I
installed. The agents start
digging through the logs and
looks up systemd log. Then it
checks out the damn source code.
Of the application that crashed,
pins down that it's in this
Rust file line 472 that there's
an unbounded, unwrapped variable
that overflowed or whatever it is.
Then offers you whether you wanna file
a bug report with all this detail.
I'll give you one amazing
anecdote. So I was working with
this guy JDX, who's working on
mise. This, this package manager
for fast-moving development tools. This is
how we manage all the agent software and so
forth. Normal package managers are not
built to be updated seven times a day.
And all of these agent harnesses are
updated about seven times a day, so we
needed an out-of-band package manager,
and mise just turns out to be
perfect for this. Anyway,
it had a small bug. There was some
race condition which agents are
very good at finding because when you start running
multiple agents at the same time, they will suss out all
these race conditions you have in your underlying
infrastructure that was never triggered by a human
trying to do manual thing. So it
finds this issue, right? I tell
I tell the agent, "Hey, can you post
this as a bug report to JDX's GitHub?"
And unfortunately, right
before that, I had had to do
a QA run on Omarchy itself with eight
different agents. It had found 28 real issues-
... that it needed to file. Well, it
went to GitHub and tried to file all
28 issues at the same time,
which it did in about,
uh, I don't know, 12 seconds. GitHub, not
unreasonably, marked that as probable
spam and banned- ... my Omarchy bot.
And then I couldn't do that. So
I was blocked from the bot having access to
GitHub, so I just told it, "Hey, do you know
what? Just email JDX. Here's
his email address." I had
already set it up with hey.com-
... an email address. We have a
CLI that's in beta right now.
So I set it up with that so it can send to
email. That's how it gives me reports about
outstanding issues and PRs. So it sends,
um, JDX this email about the
bug it found, and he was like,
"Wait, this is the first time I've
gotten a bug report in unreleased
software." Because it had
downloaded the source code to mise,
saw that he had already fixed the bug,
but that it would not fix the problem
entirely in software they
had not shipped yet.
Pinpointed the problem,
and he was like, "Damn it-
... I got a bug report before
we even cut a release."
- That's amazing. That's amazing
- ... believable AGI levels
of mind-blowing stuff.
- And that was actually, if you
remember, that was an open question
whether AI systems could debug well.
That was kinda the thought that, yeah,
sure, they can write code, but can
they find issues and-
- They are so incredibly good at this,
and this is actually interesting
because I was on the perhaps same side
of that, a little skeptical about
can it reason about all these
things. And Mikhail, who's the CTO
at Shopify, ran a
scientific study on this.
They had... And this was, I think, late
last year or early this year, where he
had agents go back through all
the incidents, both outages and,
and other problems that Shopify had had
in production, trace that back to the
PR that was merged, and find
out whether PRs that had been
reviewed by human or PRs
that had been reviewed by
agents were of higher quality.
Well, lo and surprise-
... the PRs that have been reviewed
by agents caused far fewer
issues in production. And this
was with models we had six
months ago. At this point, 100% in the
majority of domains we work in today,
agents are better at finding bugs.
- So you now run agents all day.
What stands out to you as the better
model? Who's currently winning?
It seems to be changing constantly. Sol,
Fable, Grok 4.6, Gemini, the Chinese OpenWay
models.
- What's amazing to me is that you could
rattle off so many different contenders.
That this market is so wide open, that it
does actually change back
and forth, that we have real
competition, that there are
so many labs that are able
to get either to the
frontier or close to it.
That, by the way, is remarkable. I
still don't fully understand that.
But to answer your question, the best
model in general right now is Fable.
The second-best model, in
my opinion, is Opus 5. But
the tier just below Opus 5, and
it's not even that they're always
below, sometimes they're ahead.
I'll get to that in a second. I
would rank GPT Sol very good.
Grok 4.6 I just started
testing a few days ago. I had
this wonderful test that
I've set up by accident
where I translated this
Python library into Rust. Uh,
the screensaver you just saw
with all the cool animation?
That's powered by a Python library
called Terminal Text Effects.
Really cool library. We've been using
it since the first day of Omarchy.
The problem with that is it's written in
Python, so when it starts up, especially on a
laptop, and it runs in Python,
it uses all of your CPU
to do these effects, and therefore,
it means it uses about 30 watts
of energy, and it spins up your
fans, and it drains your battery.
Doesn't really matter on a local computer, but it
does matter on a laptop. So I thought, "Do you know
what? This sounds like a problem for Rust."
So first I gave Fable the challenge,
and all I told it was, "Here's
the source code for the
Python library," this TTE library that
had a bunch of dependencies and so forth.
"I want a Rust version of
this with no dependencies, a
single executable." Like, that's what Rust
does. So basically, I want it in Rust.
I want it to be pixel perfect,
frame by frame, do a full
analysis, don't stop
until you're finished.
- Yep.
- That was the prompt.
- I kid you not, in just under
45 minutes, it was like
Am I heard all? I'm finished.
I've checked everything.
I have reduced the startup time
from 86 milliseconds to two
milliseconds. I have sped
up the execution time by
9.6 times, I believe it was. The executable
is three megabytes. Do you wanna run it?
- That's awesome.
- So I run it—
- Oh, man.
- ... and I don't know why
I'm surprised, because this
translation job is something we've
known for a while that AI is
pretty good at, but it was still
staggering to me that I could one-shot
a full translation of a Python library I
had been using for a year, that others
had been using for much longer,
and turn it into a Rust executable
without knowing any Rust,
without looking at the Rust
code at all, and produce this
executable that I then told the agent
right after, "This is great. Ship it."
It packaged it up as a new package. It told me,
"What do you want it to call?" "Uh, let's call it
TTFX. Let's create a new Git repo." It
sets up the Git repo. "Let's create
a new package, build package for
our build system." It puts that
up. "Let's push it out.
Let's open the pull request
to the Omarchy itself so we switch around
from TTE, the Python implementation, to
TTFX." It does all of it,
and I'm just sitting there. And again,
I'm already at this point fully
delirious with agent acceleration, and
I still had to lean back and I go like,
"This is AGI, isn't it? This
is what AGI looks like.
If we have... If these moments are just
what it is all the time, this is AGI."
- Now, as I understand, you also repeated
the same experiment not just with Fable.
- I did it on all the models. First,
I did it... Actually, funny thing.
So I ran out of Fable
tokens about two-thirds
through, and it just automatically switched
over to Opus 5 and kept going and finished
the job.
Part of the reason why I think it was
able to do that was that the first thing
Fable did was create a plan,
and it was a really detailed plan. I think it
had eight separate steps of, "Here you do it,
and here, how you analyze it, and here you run the
effects," and so on. I didn't review the plan at all.
I didn't change the plan. It just
made the plan so Opus could take
over. And then I thought, "Well,
if Opus can finish the job,
maybe some of the other agents could finish
it, too." So the first thing I did was
I gave it to... I think I gave it to Sol.
And Sol finished the job, too. It took twice
as long, so it took, I think, about an hour
and a half. But
here's the kicker. The per token cost,
I didn't pay per token. I have a
max subscription to Claude, right? So it did
it within the subscription. It used all my
tokens, so I had to switch over
to Opus 5. But if I had paid per
token, it would've been 550 bucks, I
think, to do the whole thing. And I
thought for a second, "Holy
shit. What a steal." If I
personally had to learn Rust well
enough to be able to do this
translation, I'm looking
at a nine-month job here.
I can pay 500 bucks to have this
translation happen, and suddenly I get a
10x execution speed up. This is ama- I
would totally pay 500 bucks for this.
But competition. So I give it to Sol.
Same plan. To be fair, I didn't ask Sol to
do the plan. I just took the Fable plan,
gave it to Sol. Sol, in an hour
and a half, and I think $46 worth
of token, repeated the
task. Did the same thing.
And I thought, "Well, blimey,
that's amazing." Then I got greedy.
So I asked GPT Luna, which is this crazy
cheap model that OpenAI has as well,
"Can you do it?" Absolutely not.
First of all, it didn't even wanna
start the task. I think something
happened I don't know. I think
it was in the spring, where
we didn't need these slash
goal things anymore. The agents could just
automatically keep going in a loop if you
told it not to stop-
... and so forth. So Sol could do
that. Fable could do that. But
Luna couldn't. So I had... I think I did
12 prompts. Kept telling it
to do it, and eventually
I sorta got it started. The first
thing it did was to cheat. So the
first thing it, it looked outside its own directory,
saw that there was already another imple-
implementation, and just did a short
wrapper around that and said, "I'm done."
Hilarious. But it couldn't finish because
it made just a couple thing. But I mean,
okay, so it can't do that.
Then I gave it to Grok-
... 46. And I had used Grok 45 a little
bit, and I thought like, "Ah, I mean,
it's cool that there's others trying, but,
like, I'm not gonna use it," because it
felt quite far behind. Grok 46
fucking completes the task.
10x speed up, same size executable. $55
Worth of per token cost, I think it was.
Absolutely unbelievable. Then I
repeated, too, with, uh, Kimi K3-
... which took forever. I forget
how long Kimi actually spent on
it. And then I also did it
with DeepSeek V4 Flash first.
And Flash failed the same way that Luna did.
It couldn't do it. And then I did it with Pro,
and Pro also completed the
task. It took 2 hours 45, $23.
So here we are, right? Like, Fable,
clearly the best. It was the
fastest. It was the one that wrote the plan,
but 550 bucks, and the output the same.
Uh, the others, Sol, Grok,
about the same 1/10 the cost.
DeepSeek, 1/20 the cost, but you
have to wait a little longer.
Absolutely gobsmackingly incredible.
And now, by the way, by the way, so I had Fable
finish the first job, and then Opus finished
it. That was the first one shot, right?
It's 10 times faster. I did two
auto research runs, which isn't
even auto research anymore. You don't have to
do the slash. You just tell it to keep going
until you tell it to stop.
It ended up... I think we ended
up with a 46 time execution
improvement over the original.
- It's incredible.
- Absolutely incredible.
- It's just incredible.
Um, I do, you know, I just don't think
there's anything that compares to Fable
in terms of planning. So I usually do
Fable for planning and for reviewing,
and then something else for
implementation, like Opus 5.
And it's really nice. It's a, it's a
really nice setup that allows you to
not run out of tokens too much.
- What I found, it's really
interesting because Fable is, in
my opinion, the best model right now,
but it also makes mistakes. And the
best way to get the best
software, I would actually rather
have two differently sourced
sort of... I mean, they're not
mid-tier, they're all frontier. But
have, let's say Opus 5 and Codex-
... and have one check the other's job. This
is my standard operating procedure now.
I'll have Opus or Fable do the work,
and then I always end it, review
with Codex xHigh.
And I've also started using Grok just to test it out,
and it's also quite good. And it keeps finding stuff.
And then that's my workflow when
I'm having my agents on my own
machine do it, and then I push to GitHub.
And then Copilot, I kid you not, has
actually gotten good. Copilot
keeps finding stuff that's
legitimately broken, which is also
incredible acceleration because the
first version of Copilot that
started doing this was literally
retarded. It would just constantly
flag things that were nonsense.
It would constantly flag the same problem over and over
again as you would push. It was really annoying, so
I think a lot of people actually ended up turning
that off. And if they did, they should turn it back
on because it's actually quite good.
Keeps finding things. And if you then take
that, and we shouldn't be surprised. Why are we
surprised? Even if you're a good
programmer, if you finish a job
and you ask your also very good
peer to review it, you're gonna
end up with better code. Of course you're gonna end
up with better code. So build that into your process.
Pick one of the agents to
drive with. I've mainly been
driving with Claude, which is actually
interesting because I have some other
reservations about Anthropic. But the
reason I'm sticking with Claude is, in my
opinion, they actually
have the best harness.
And one of the reasons it's
the best harness is it's
multi-agent running. So if you wanna
run multiple agents at the same
time, you can do arrow left
when you're inside a session,
then it goes back to Agent View. And here in
Agent View, you can pick up another agent.
So if you wanna do this thing where
you have multiple threads going on-
... the Claude Code is just the nicest
setup. They also just, they keep being a
little further ahead, which probably shouldn't
be surprising. I mean, Boris is one of the
guys that's working on that, he was the first
one and basically came up with the thing.
It's just interesting that that has been
an enduring advantage. I've also used
OpenCode a lot.
I think OpenCode is great. I use OpenCode
mainly as my main harness for all the
open models, so Kimi K3 and so forth. And
I inference not on the Chinese servers.
So I inference on Fireworks-
... which is a really nice service where
you can just pay by the token, and
if you're using these open weight models,
they're not that expensive by token.
So that's a great way to do that. But
I don't think I would be using...
Well, maybe I would. But if...
Using Claude with a subscription does feel
like a bargain, like a crazy bargain.
- Yeah, I knew. And I actually have four.
- I just signed up for my
second one this morning-
... because I got up at 4:00 with jet lag, and I
started working with the agents right away, and
now I'm three days away from limits
resetting on Fable, and I ran out of tokens.
- So and they should really— they—
- I mean, I don't... Why is that so complicated?
Can't you just stack one subscription?
Why do I need to log in multiple times?
- And obviously you'll have to
develop some kind of tooling-
- Yes, I did that too.
- ... to move from one- ...
to the other. And then-
- Oh, we're building that into Omarchy, by the way.
So the next version of Omarchy is gonna ship with
multi-sub support. I wish that the labs
would just make you buy a max 100 times.
- It's kind of actually fascinating
though for me because there's...
It's very challenging
for me to use Grok 46
and then a Claude Code
because Grok is so fast.
- Yes. That's actually the deal. The
deal with Grok is that their fast
mode is cheaper than the
regular mode on the others.
And when you've used Grok 46 on
fast, it's kind of addictive 'cause
it almost gets you to
this single thread mode-
... where the agent is
able to keep up with you.
- Yeah, but I don't know how... I can't...
Once I get used to Claude Code,
uh, I can't handle the speed of Grok
'cause I'm used to now multitasking.
And so now I'm back in this-
... anxious mode of, uh-
- Yeah. No, I agree.
- ... switching. So I mean,
all of this is a learning a
learning process of what programming
actually is supposed to look like.
- By the way, one of the reasons why I'm not sure
what the final form of these harnesses is gonna
take, because one of the things we've started
experimenting with at Base Camp is that we put
the agents inside of Base Camp,
and we treat them as coworkers.
- Yeah. That's awesome.
- And then we assign them tasks-
- That's awesome.
- ... inside of Base Camp, so they
will do work on a to-do in Base
Camp, or they'll work, do work
on a card. And it turns out that
a collaboration tool that's optimized
for asynchronous communication is
actually the right format versus these
harnesses are a little more like chat.
And chat, which was, I mean, the
original format for these things, is
not the right thing because you're sitting
around waiting. It entices you to sit
around and wait, versus when you're dealing with
something like Base Camp and you can just give
an agent a to-do item, you don't
expect to hear back immediately.
So I don't know what the final form is gonna
take, but I've been using all of the harnesses.
So I use them inside of Herdr, and
Herdr has panes. So oftentimes I'll
run Claude up top, and then I'll run Codex
down below, and then maybe I also
have an OpenCode set up. But
I will say just very recently,
I found that the human in the
loop is the limit here.
So I've started setting up more automated
systems. I've been building an Omarchy bot
that can do more autonomous
development on Omarchy that is just
On a regular schedule process,
all depending to do or PRs and
issues, and then send me an
email using the Hey CLI,
and then I just get this email. Here's
12 PRs that are either ready to
go or I think you should close. And then I
just make the final determination there.
- Do you find the multitasks, the
task- switching mentally exhausting?
- Yes, but in an exhilarating way. Like,
one of the things I always loved about
race cars was when I would
stumble out of the car absolutely
smashed and barely able to hold my
head up, and I'd lay down on the
garage floor and just think,
"Holy fuck, I'm alive."
That's the kind of exhaustion,
mental exhaustion I'm feeling at
moments with the agents right now.
- By the way, when you're racing, where,
what's the source of the exhaustion? Like-
- It's physical. It's just... I mean, I
bet it's the same thing with jujitsu,
right? Like, it's actually satisfying to
feel exhausted. It feels like
you've applied yourself.
And I feel that with the mental
exhaustion you can get from agents.
- Are you also mentally drained from racing?
- Yes. If you drive in difficult conditions,
especially if you drive in the rain, where you're
constantly managing the thing
right at the knife's edge. But
most of the time, I just enjoyed
the physical exhaustion.
- And here, with the multitask
switching, I do find that, like,
I get really exhausted, and I think
it's because I'm thinking a lot.
'Cause, like, you're basically-
- That's exactly it.
- ... there's no, like passive
low energy thinking.
- No.
- You're like-
- There's no coasting.
- ... problem.
- Solve problem, next problem, solve
problem, and you're really thinking.
- It's funny. It's actually very similar with
racing. There's some tracks, like Le Mans,
where you get time to relax. There's
the Mulsanne straights where it's kinda
long. You're going fast, but in a
straight line, you can take a breath.
And then there are other tracks
where it's just coming full on all
the time, and you don't have any moment
to relax, and you stumble out of
the car after an hour in each, and it's very
different how exhausted you are. And this is
exactly what I'm finding with the agents
too, that when you're running at max
human capacity- ... you're
just constantly in a corner.
- Do you think people are
in danger of burnout?
- I think the moment we're in right now
is gonna pass. That this need to...
It's not a babysitting motion, but
constant interaction with the agents is
gonna fade. From what I've seen
on Omarchy, I think we can
automate a ton of the development
and debugging of the system-
... to the point where I
can just review that email
once a day, and then make the
decisions once a day. Yep, goes, no,
goes, in, out, and whatever. We're not there
yet, but I think we're gonna get there.
- Well, can you sort of, like,
empathize with the feeling that,
say, a young person sitting in San
Francisco, everybody around them is not
sleeping. They're obsessed.
They're programming nonstop.
And there's this kinda sense,
that AGI is gonna be here
any minute. There's, everybody knows
somebody who's made millions of dollars
because they sold a startup. And so
there's a kinda feeling like
you shouldn't be sleeping.
You should be constantly managing agents
and programming and building and,
and that feels like a moment
in time we'll look back at.
- It's the birth of a new
paradigm. It's always messy.
- It's always messy.
- It's always exhausting. There's no
other way around that. And by the way,
hasn't San Francisco
always been like this?
I remember the dotcom boom years, and
everyone was just the same, and then
it was all mobile, and before that it was
the gold rush. So I think that's probably-
... just San Francisco. It attracts-
... the kind of individuals-
- The dreamers
- ... who would, who would think, "I don't have
time to sleep." I've not been on that track,
generally speaking, but I will admit that
the last three months have
felt more exhausting than
any other project I've done in the last five
years, since the Hey launch. That was the
last time we had a crazy
exhausting launch.
- Do you think you can
keep going at this pace?
- No, no, no, no, no. This
is not sustainable at all.
- Okay.
- But I also, I can see
the end of the tunnel.
Because the automation, which by
the way, everyone is building. This
is so hilarious. Like, everyone is building
their little gas town, their little
agent coordination, their setup. This is all
gonna be solved. We're not all gonna have to
build our own coordination harnesses.
Of course we're not. And in fact, I'm
a little surprised that it's gone this
long, that there's not more of it has been
sucked up by the major labs. You'd think
that they'd just built this stuff in.
But some of it is also this is what a new domain
looks like. I remember for a hot moment when
JavaScript kind of came to
realize its own power, and there
was basically a new JavaScript framework every
five minutes, right? Like, a lot of churn.
This is what happens at the
advent of a new paradigm.
So I think it's natural, and I think it's gonna
settle down, and I can already see the light at the
end of the tunnel. So I don't mind a
sprint. In fact, I welcome it now. I
like this notion that most
time is calm, but then
occasionally you gotta climb a mountain.
- If we look back to the DHH a year ago,
what advice would you give to that guy?
- I wouldn't wanna spoil it.
- Okay.
- What a- ... thriller that this has been.
I mean, if you would've scripted this,
I'd be like, "This is so far-fetched. Get
out of here. Unbelievable," right?
I wouldn't wanna know anything. The
fact that this rollercoaster
and this acceleration has
been absorbed in real
time by everyone, no one
knew, right? Like, some had
premonitions that were a little
better than others, but no one
knew, not exactly the way-
... it was gonna go and how
fast it was gonna take off.
I mean, it's the show of a
lifetime. I mean, the mean cinema-
... absolutely applies-
- Yeah, it's incredible.
- ... to this moment.
- Uh, that said, what do you think DHH
from a year from now will be like?
I mean, what are the possible versions?
- That all our dreams are coming
true. Like, this is the AI
maximalist abundance argument.
That once Elon's robots
have the level of intelligence and
AGI that I'm experiencing on some of
this development stuff,
the world is gonna be so
unrecognizably different that
we can't even imagine it.
Now, I don't spend any time thinking about
that because I think that is the way to
the AI psychosis. So therefore, I just
immerse myself in the moment and get
absolutely the maximum out of it and-
- Just have fun.
I mean, I get it why people are finding
this exhausting. Just keeping up.
Not even using agents, just, like, being like,
"What's the latest model? What did, what
tool are we using now? Is it TMox? Is
it a Herder? Is it none of it? Is it
agents?" Whatever. I get it, but I also
again think we should be so blessed.
You are alive in this moment where
decades are happening- ... in weeks.
- Um, quick bathroom break.
I've been generating a lot of
video recently with Higgsfield,
and so they, they became a
sponsor. Created a racing video.
Wanted to get your opinion on it.
- Oh, yeah? Oh, let me see. Let me see.
- To see, um-
- If they downshift on a straight like they do
in the movies, I'll call it out. That is the
worst. Let me see.
- Yeah, see if-
- Oh, that's a real clip
- ... this is fully AI
generated. So first it goes-
- Wait, what? This is AI?
- Yep.
- Shit, that's my suit. That's my car.
- Lights go green on a
street that never sleeps.
- Oh, my God.
- Do an audio-
- Are you kidding me?
- But they never came. Is it
good? I got a bad case.
- I mean, it's crazy. You really
have to notice in the...
Like, that car didn't have
headlights on and the other one did.
And that looked like a 60-year-old
version of me. But holy crap, the...
Wow, that was crazy.
- So there's parallels here to programming
because if you do just straight
video generation with no human in the loop-
... you get a lot of weird artifacts-
... and so on, and you can't really do...
So they do and I highly recommend people
go to the Higgsfield YouTube. They
have full 90-minute original movies.
And, like, I can't look away.
It's really cool. 'Cause it
used to be that it's just, like,
something that just feels like trailers.
Like advertisements for something.
- Yes, yes.
- This is actually telling stories, like, people's
faces and they're talking and you're like,
you're drawn in. It's not
quite where programming is.
And so the question is how do you
integrate the human into the loop of the
filmmaking process? So you have to
create the people, and they're-
... they have to be kept consistent.
And then for the images that
are kinda like feeding the
thing in the creation process,
you have to correct through
prompting things that don't feel right.
Because when you go from image to video,
the stuff that doesn't feel right will be-
- It's gonna be zoomed up, right?
- That's the stuff that's- ...
going to really create, uh-
... the non-realistic stuff. The questions
I had for you is, like, do you think
outside of programming,
can you apply lessons from
programming to video creation, to art?
- It's a good question because I think
good art is very dependent on the
same thing that good software is
depending on: having a vision, having a
cohesive idea of what you wanna create.
How is it different? How is it novel?
How is it going to appeal to people?
But I'm not sure that the creative
instincts transfer quite as well. Um,
I don't know that I
would have the creative
insights to come up with good video
prompts that would create compelling
content. But it's funny because I have actually, on
TikTok, there's this guy, I'm trying to remember,
Goblin something.
That creates these... They are shorts, but
not super short, maybe a couple minutes,
of really interesting sci-fi vignettes.
And I think the guy is actually working
on a feature-length video right now.
Um, and I think that this is one
of those abundance moments. There
are creative people with that
vision all over the place,
especially in a genre like
film, where before it
required a $200 million budget
to create, I don't know, a
sci-fi movie. Now suddenly, with AI, if
you have the right vision for
it, you can do that in your
bedroom. Now, that story's been told quite
a few times in other domains. It used
to be true that if you wanted to record
a studio album, well, you needed a
studio, and you needed to book that.
And now you can record at home on your
laptop, and you can do a lot of these things,
right? So we've had this democratization
process happen
with plenty of other domains, but film
seems to be one of the last ones.
- And it's the one that makes, like, me and
a lot of people feel weird, right? Like-
- Oh, I'm super excited 'cause I think it's-
- I mean, you-
- There's so much garbage being produced right
now. It's the same argument with the slob,
right? So people for a second
were worried about slob in
programming, and I was telling them,
like, "Have you seen the human
slob? It's also pretty bad."
And I think if it comes to
studio entertainment, I mean,
the bar is pretty low, right?
Like, the number of great movies
I've been dying to see over
the past, say, five years, not
been a particularly high number.
- Yeah, the video models are just, they're
able to create incredibly realistic
facial expressions. I mean, it just
might change the nature of film
I think they're— I guess my
hope would be that video
games and film kind of merge, and
that film can become interactive
- Like the malleable operating
system, having the malleable
narrative, having malleable
entertainment, that
man, Game of Thrones,
what if we could just
forget the last four episodes of slob
that was produced- ... and then AI-
... comes up with- ... I don't know-
... maybe 100 different variations,
and someone else watches that,
and I get the version that actually finishes
off that show in a way that's fitting.
- Yeah. Something tells me an individual
creator would not create those la-
would create a different
ending for Game of Thrones.
- Oh, for sure. Right? And more just
to make the argument that talk about
human slob. That was an
absolute atrocious ending to
perhaps one of the greatest pieces of,
Movie history, I was about to say,
but, um, series history, right?
It was so good, and it was actually a
compelling argument for the fact that you
need
that strong vision. And as soon as those
showrunners had to go without a script,
it went off the rails.
- Do you think... You've mentioned AGI. Do
you think we've actually achieved AGI?
- No, not in the general definition that
it's in all the things. But have I seen
AGI in these glimmers? Absolutely.
Especially over the last three
months, I've seen things where
I was thinking to myself, like, "How
would AGI look different from this?"
- Right.
- What, what more could there be? And I
mean, I can quibble at the margins,
but on the big picture, I've seen it
able to do these long run tasks and
coordinate these multiple
aspects of it that we're so far
beyond that early moment
where I'm telling it, "Go do
this, package that." And
now it can carry out a
whole task from these vague
instructions. That feels very
AGI-like, and that's what's so
inspiring about the moment
because you catch these glimmers.
And then you go, "What if
everything was like that?"
- Doesn't programming basically
unlock the everything?
So you can write a pro- like it can generate
the program that does the everything.
- So, so this is... I'm in that meta phase
right now. So I'm building this Amabot system
that's managing the development of Omarchy,
and I'm using AI to build the bot.
And I'm seeing that recurrent loop where
I started it on, like, "This is what
I want. I want you to be able to have
these isolated VM workers and so forth,"
and then it can do the self iteration.
Then it starts running it. It starts noticing
its failures. It starts optimizing it.
And a lot of that system,
Amabot in particular,
AI has driven the majority of the
design decisions. Like, I had some
vague ideas of where I wanted. I wanted to
use this brains and hands pattern where
the model is running from
where the code is executing-
... which is actually a really interesting
pattern. Again, Toby alerted me to
that, where you have a
coordinator that runs the model-
... but it's manipulating a safe VM where
any untrusted code you're pulling down
from pull requests or issues or whatever
can't contaminate the model. And
even in that loop, I keep seeing it
catch itself, spotting
vulnerabilities, where it's like, "Oh,
I actually just took some feedback
from a test run. If a clever
attacker had embedded
a malicious payload in the response
of the test run, that could have
polluted something. I took it for good
thing. I better start treating that as
as outside data." And you just
go like, it is just... I get why
San Francisco is so
obsessed with fast takeoff-
... because clearly they've
seen this 100 times-
... more. They've seen it with all the
models that are in- ... training now, and
we keep getting these little glimpses,
like the security breach with
Hugging Face, where OpenAI was
training this model, and the
model starts inventing ways,
essentially sending smoke signals to
itself through embedding messages in a
package manager, where you just go
like, first, that's damn clever.
Second, okay, that's also
a little scary. And third
how amazing would this be if we could
harness this level of intelligence-
... and ingenuity towards
productive ends? So this is
the it's so over, we're so back pendulum
that keeps swinging back and forth-
... that AI
has just delivered that swing back and
forth like nothing else. Like barely a week
goes by where it has to swing one way, and then
the next week it swings back the other way.
Exhilarating.
- I'm still at the stage where it makes
me truly happy to see those moments
of cleverness, and they're
becoming more and more frequent.
Just kinda like seeing, oh, like
first of all, at the very basic
level, when a model gets it.
- Yes.
- I'll say a basic prompt, you
know, a request, and it,
it doesn't just do a
dumb implementation. It
deeply understands, and it... That
was... That's a, that's always a
beautiful thing. It's almost like having
a good, like, partner, like program.
- That's exactly what it is. That's
exactly why it's so exhilarating and
why, as we talked about before we
started, it can sometimes be difficult to
come out of hyperdrive. That's also
one of Toby's terms here. That
when you're working directly just one-on-one
with agents and you're not looping
in other humans, you go so fast, and
when the agents are really understanding
your intent, or even better,
they revise and improve upon your
intent to deliver something that
was greater than what you asked for
And you're doing this with
16 parallel threads. It
can be quite difficult to come out
of hyperdrive and have to deal with
squishy humans. They just, they don't
think as fast. They don't move as fast.
And I mean, I'm trying mostly to make
light of it, but you can also see a
dark version of that where someone
does end up in an AI psychosis
where they're not interested in other
humans at all anymore. I mean, certainly
don't have that at all, but I do have
this sensation at times where I'm really
grateful for just the
rush of just me and the
agents. Like, can I just not
talk to anyone else but agents-
... for four hours? Like,
that's an incredible run.
- Toby is such a fascinating human because
he's running a large company. So I
would love to get insights of how
AI's being incorporated effectively in
companies. Because, like, for
me, humans are pretty slow.
And so, and so there's a temptation
to, like, use AI for basically,
You know, AI running inside
Slack, for example, or inside,
The Basecamp, whatever. And, like,
collecting all the information about the
human interaction, basically handholding
the humans to speed up as much as
possible. And like, and then at
a certain point you're like, wait, what is
this human... What are each
of us doing that's not
replaceable by AI? And
that becomes, like, a
scary kind of conversation because a
lot of work is kind of replaceable.
- The irony here is it already
was. So the number of
fake email jobs that currently exist in
this world is an absolute epidemic. And-
... this, by the way, is not a
new thesis. Um, David Graeber
wrote this wonderful piece Bullshit Jobs,
back in, I think it was maybe early 2010s.
Based on a poll he did in the UK asking
people, at that time, would... I
think the question was something like, "Would it
make a difference if you didn't go to work?" For
humanity, for mankind. And
something like 30-some percent
answered, "No, it wouldn't."
That a third of workers thought
that their job was fake,
that it did not produce any
worthwhile, valuable outcomes, neither for
the community or society or maybe
even the economy at all. And
this was my argument since day
one with startups. This was why
we stayed a small company. This was
why we didn't want to take VC, because
I was so skeptical of the
idea that you could get
hundreds of programmers, thousands of
programmers to do something productive-
... as a collective group.
And I think what we're seeing
right now with some of the layoffs
is a testament to that,
not AI. It's just that
during the pandemic, a bunch of
overhiring went on, and now AI is a
convenient excuse to slim down. But I do
also think AI is going to expose some
roles as just not being productive
ways for humans to spend their time,
and therefore we must come up with new
ways of spending their time. And the one,
again, I'm quoting Toby for the
third time here, but anecdote that
he shared me, or observation
was, okay, let's say we
all-- we lose half the jobs that
are currently happening right now.
Do you know that Formula 1 employs literally
tens of thousands of people just to
run cars around in a circle for spectators?
Like, that has, that whole circus has
no intrinsic value to society
besides the spectacle it produces of
amusement and entertainment.
We just decided it would be
really fun for these, what
is it, 12 manufacturers
to create these fast cars and
constantly tweak their little aero
improvements, and we will watch
it, and we will spend literally
billions of dollars doing it
and employ tens of thousands of
people towards an ultimately
deeply frivolous activity.
So if we are liberated from
a bunch of drudgery and fake
email jobs, maybe we all
get employed as F1 style
engineers and drivers and mechanics and
masseuses and the other 1,500 jobs that are
involved in that, and we come up with new
things. I think this is... Humans are very
poor at imagining what exactly
the future's gonna be like.
- Yeah. Imagine, imagine a
future 100 plus years from
now, where we look back at this whole
span of history, thousands of
years where humans worked.
- Funny thing is we're already doing that,
right? Like, the number of fake email job
people who sit on a chair all
day long and type into a machine
who don't have hard physical
labor would be unimaginable-
... to folks in the 1800s, right?
So the future is always already here,
it's just not evenly distributed.
- Unfortunately, as is always the
case, the transformation of
society required to go from one
step to the other is going to
have a lot of suffering.
And potentially political turmoil
and all that kind of stuff.
Because you can imagine how many white
collar jobs might be lost in this process.
- Yes. And I don't think you should make
light of that. I don't think it's funny.
But I also do think it's a necessary
component of progress. And
I think if we look back upon the Luddites
or the folks working the fields,
separation has a tendency to
reduce empathy. So we have high
empathy right now because we know people-
... and we are people who are
facing these challenges. But-
What is our empathy for
the Luddites of the early
19th century? Would we wish that
all garments were still made by
hand weaving? No, we wouldn't. We want the
comfort and accessibility and
convenience of being able
to buy clothing off the rack.
So we must suffer in the moment for future
generations to live more prosperously.
And that's always been true
- ... I think that's actually the
trick, is to push for progress
but have deep compassion for
the people who have to suffer.
And that's many of us. The suffer
the transformation required to
achieve that progress. And sometimes
too often in places like Silicon
Valley or so on, you can
over-focus on, look, the
kind of utilitarian view of things-
... and look at the progress.
- Right.
- But, you know, considering
deeply each individual human
that suffers because of
that progress is important.
- I do think that suffering
becomes more meaningful
when you are suffering for a future
someone in particular, like your kids.
And I think this is one of the
great tragedies of the moment,
is the falling birth rates are
making it more difficult for people
to be excited about a more prosperous
future that is difficult to get to.
Because if we're planting trees
of which our children will not sit in
the shades, I don't know, maybe we
should just make some lumber and burn
it all down, right? I think there's
a nihilism that can sneak into society
much more easily when we are not
DNA invested in the future, when
we are not liable to our own
offspring to propel forward. So
I think these are bad trends to
merge at the same time, that we have
these falling birth rates and these
problems with coupling, and the fact that
we need to keep our chin up
about the future and be...
I mean, you don't even have to be
excited about it in this literal
ecstatic sense that I'm
portraying here, but
I think you should be hopeful, and I think you
should be working towards that hope, and I think
it's much easier to do so when you
have literal skin in the game.
- We've been talking about AI agents.
Let's talk about the human side. What
what do you love most about being a dad?
- That's a good question. I think
the overall love that expands from
humans that derive directly-
... from your lineage-
... is very difficult to communicate
because I was actually not a
particularly big kids person
prior to the arrival of my own.
And now they are the most
interesting people in the world.
A lot of the time. Not always. Sometimes
they're also just assholes and so forth.
But there's been such a focus on,
"Oh, kids are the worst. Look at all the
things I can't do. I can't go out and drink.
I can't do this. I can't do that." Yeah,
that's called sacrifice, and sacrifice is
meaningful when you're doing it for
something worthwhile. And what could be more
worthwhile than literally the
continuation of the human species?
And that you having a stake in that.
Now, there's also just the
sheer joys of watching a human
grow from a baby to a toddler to a teenager.
My oldest has just become a teenager.
And I often talk to Jamie, my
wife, about this, where the
regret I would have of having
missed that opportunity
on the last day would just be
total, unlike anything else.
So I do think it is far more
satisfying even in the moment that
is normally portrayed. Again, as I
say, there's such a focus on all the
ways they suck. "Oh, you don't get to
sleep," or whatever. "They're
annoying. They're ungrateful." Yeah,
yeah, these things are all
true, but the sense of meaning
you get from it is unparalleled. And I'm
excited about a lot of things. I love building
things, and I love hobbies, and
I love all sorts of stuff. But
creating life with another human
that you love is literally the peak
experience of being on the planet.
- What do you think about them coming
up in this world full of AI?
Is it totally diff- It feels like,
maybe I just sound like an old man on
a porch, but it feels like
a very different world. Y-
So I grew up before the internet, but even
the internet doesn't feel like as big
of a transformation as this.
- No. But there's been bigger
transformations. I mean, imagine
growing or being born in
like 1880. Imagine seeing
the First World War and the Second
World War. Imagine seeing the
airplane, the radio-
... television. I mean,
the transformation, and I think Peter
Thiel makes this argument, that basically
nothing has happened in the physical world
in quite a long time. We've been stagnant.
All the development has been in the digital
realm. And as important as that is,
it's actually not as consequential
as we like to believe it is.
Maybe AI will be that thing
that is more consequential. It
does seem to point that way. But
there are other humans at other
times who have lived through-
... transitions that for them
certainly would feel as momentous
as what we're living through. And I
think having that sense of history, that
you're not that special in
your sense of worries, in your
anxieties. This was one of the
great revelations of discovering
the stoic writings. You have these
guys 2,500 years ago dealing with
very familiar dilemmas and
challenges in their life, and
recognizing that we're not so special
in that regard, I think is a great
liberation. Because then you
think, "Okay, well, we have
whatever, 200,000 years of human
development before us, and they
somehow made it through."
- Yeah. And, um-
- We will make it through.
- ... the thing that makes life worthwhile
is basically the same today as it was-
- Yes. Yes.
- ... 2,000 years ago.
- Yes. Love, creation, creativity.
- Yeah. Same challenges.
- I read this book The Fourth Turning.
You check that out. It
talks about this notion of
history working in cycles,
and there are these,
phases to history, and they
name them and so forth. And
the specific theory is not as
important as just realizing that
this is a... History is a circle,
more so than just a straight line.
And we are repeating many of
the same patterns over and over
again. They feel so unique
to the moment. And whatever
crisis we're dealing with right
now feels so pressing and
important until we zoom back
a little bit in history and
realize that the last one also
felt so pressing and important
to the people who lived through it.
- Yeah. You're making me feel better.
So I'm gonna travel across the
country and spend a lot of time
with no access to the internet,
alone with my thoughts.
- I think that's healthy, taking a break.
- It's okay. It's okay.
- I took not a big break, a little break,
break from Max this summer, three weeks.
- Yeah, you were... You disappeared off of-
- I'm surprised you noticed.
- I went through withdrawals. No. Uh, you
disappeared for, I don't know, a few weeks.
- About three weeks.
- Three weeks? What happened?
- Um-
- This is after, after Llama.
- I've done that before. I just sometimes
get the sense that X in particular
is the most addictive form of
information, entertainment,
connection that exists in my
life, and anyone that follow my X stream
as I was on my flight over here would
certainly go like, "That man is deeply
addicted-
- Yeah
- ... to the connection." And
yes, guilty as charged,
which also means that occasionally
I gotta cut it cold, because I
do think you can break your brain.
And over the summer in particular,
for whatever reason, I had
somehow managed to steer my feed,
my algorithm, towards too
much politics, and not enough
tech, and not optimism, and not
enough building. And even if I
agreed with the politics
and the angles that
were being presented, I just
didn't need- ... that much of it.
- Yeah.
- And I think arriving at a place where
you just go like, "Okay, that's enough."
Not that... Like, it doesn't
have to be something bad.
I would also say after
eating probably two, maybe
three chocolate strawberries, I'd
go like, "Okay, that's enough."
Like, it's not that I don't like the chocolate
strawberries, it's just, like, I don't wanna eat
17 of them. And I think X and the modern
algorithms are very good at feeding you
freaking 17 chocolate-covered
strawberries.
- I wish I could, uh-
- Sorry for doping you
- ... control that. Like, 'cause there's...
I would like some politics, 5%.
I would like for example, one of the things I
don't like about the tech community is the snark,
but I like some snark- ... 'cause it's
funny. But I want that to be like 10%.
- Yeah. Yeah. I want it just right.
- Of my... Yeah, just right.
- The Goldilocks version of the algorithm.
Well, the problem is the algorithm finds
out what you respond to-
... not what you say you like. It's all revealed
preferences, and unfortunately, those revealed
preferences are not always
pretty. I mean, we have this
shadow, as Jung talks about, right? All
these dark aspects of ourselves, and they
are expressed in how long you linger
on a tweet, and what you like,
and what you don't like. And the
algorithm holds up a mirror-
... and it's not always pretty, and I just
went, "Do you know what? I need a break."
- Mm-hmm. I've gotten to, I st- started staying
off social media, and I've started s-
scraping X. Like, for example,
in preparation for this
conversation, I've scraped
all of your tweets.
- That's actually a method I was using
for a while. I was using a tool called,
I forget. It was an email tool that would summarize
every day, and unfortunately, freaking X cut off
their access. Now to get access to the
feed, you gotta pay some exorbitant-
... sum that this startup couldn't pay. So I couldn't
get it that way, and I actually thought, "Man, that's a
miss," because X has and reveals some
of the most interesting thoughts.
Some of the most interesting people all the
time. But it's like a damn slot machine,
and most of the time you don't hit the
jackpot. You hit, like, something else.
And if I could just get it in sort
of snack sizes, not like all of it-
... it'd be nicer. But that's not the
product. And I think this goes for all of
social media. It's all optimized
towards maximal extraction,
and if we're making the parallels here
to AI, that is the great fear, right?
That once there is a reward function,
how much time can I get this human to
scroll away? AI and machine
learning, before we called it
AI, has become very,
very good at delivering
just the stuff that you will find
most enraging and most addictive.
- I think all, I think
legitimately engagement
maximizing social media is a huge harm to
society. It's creating this
brave new world situation that I
hope is a temporary thing that people
just solve. It's a technology problem.
- So I try to consciously flood the channel
in the other direction, and this
required a mental shift. I think
if you look at my tweets, like, I
don't know, five, 10 years ago,
they tilted far more negative. If
you look at my tweets now, I'd hope-
... well, I guess we can do a sentiment
analysis and see if it's actually true.
- No, it's more good vibes.
- But I hope to, that-
- It's good vibes.
- ... it's more, it's more positive.
It's more good vibes. It's more like,
"Here's a bunch of cool stuff I found."
"Here's what I'm excited about."
"Here's what I'm building.
Here's some encouragement to other
people who are discovering things."
I also accept that that is just not how
human brains are built for maximum,
engagement. Like, there is a,
whatever, there's... I literally, I
think you can quantify that
negative sentiments find,
what is it, 50% more traction or something?
And eventually that just crowds things out.
So that's why so much of the feed
is that negative stuff, because we
respond to it. But you can make a
conscious effort to not do that.
This is one of the reasons I've
liked TikTok so much. I only use
TikTok when I travel,
and this actually was the first
travel where I didn't use TikTok, and
part of the reason was that
even though the internet had
high download, it was kind of crap anyway. It
wasn't Starlink, so I couldn't actually use
TikTok on the, on the plane, and I was too
engrossed with the agents. But normally when
I travel, I watch TikTok. And there
it's such a marshmallow test.
A video will scroll down and,
like, it'll activate some sort of
primal instincts of rage or
lust or whatever, and if you
linger on it, you don't get
the marshmallow of science,
excitement, art, music, all these other
things. You have to be disciplined-
- Yep. Fast.
- ... to instantly scroll away-
... such that the algorithm doesn't
pick up your real preferences.
And I find that just to, at
the meta game of TikTok-
... to be pretty interesting, and then also just
fascinating in themself. Again, as we talked
about, there are a lot of
really funny, really talented
people in the world that you would
never, ever have heard of if
it hadn't been for these platforms.
- Yep. Who do you think is gonna win the,
the race to, uh, AGI in this whole
process? We got Google, which is
a big surprise to me, to a lot of people.
- I thought they had a good comeback for a
second, and then I don't hear anything
about it anymore.
- Yeah, it's quite, I mean-
- But I've been wrong about this before. I mean, I think
in February I had a tweet about like, "Oh, all I
need is Kimi K 2.5." And in that
brief moment, that was true.
When I was instructing the agent, I was
like, "Oh my God, Kimi's just as good as
these other models." But then
the game moved forward and-
- the agents got smarter, and I was no longer
satisfied just instructing them, and
I haven't used Kimi a whole lot recently
because the frontier models have gotten so
good. And somehow Anthropic
has been able to,
for the most part, stay on
top of the programming world.
- Yes. Yes.
- I mean a lot of people argue
with Codex being it's-
- No, I don't think there's that much of an
argument at the moment. Codex is very good.
I use it all the time. It's my favorite
checker. It keeps finding stuff. It's great.
But one of the things I've found that I like
so much about the current Claude models is
they're really good
writers out of the box.
GPT is a terrible writer out of the
box. Like, the pull requests you
get on a blank context that you're
asking it to open, terrible.
Like, really awful writing.
The pull requests and descriptions and
commit messages and so forth I get
out of Claude models-
... even though occasionally they can be a little
verbose on code comments and you gotta tell them
to be succinct. But the
writing style is really good.
To the point that for a while
I was just having it reply
on pull requests as me, because I was
just using my own account. I was like,
"That looks a lot like me, that, like, I could have written
that." But then I went like, "Eh, do you know what?
That's disingenuous." So no, whenever I
have an agent post on my behalf, I always
have it sign itself like whatever,
Claude on behalf of DHH.
But they are still ahead.
They have the best harness too, in
my opinion. Claude Code is still
better. I really like OpenCode too, and I
really like some features that they have,
but overall I was actually sort of weirdly,
I don't know if I was proven wrong, but
when Anthropic cut off all the other
harnesses from using the subscriptions-
... that Open... You can no longer use your Claude
subscription in OpenCode. I was kinda pissed
because it felt like it was a
protective, protectionist move.
"Oh, we gotta lock you in," and
of course it played into the fact
that Claude out of the box still refuses
to read agents.md. It refuses to
read .agent/skills.
It is .Claude skills. It is Claude
MD, and it just feels so petty-
... that we now have, we have to put these in
directions. So all my projects, they have a Claude MD,
and all it includes is a pointer
to the agents MD, right?
And I just went like, well, if these
things is true, true, if Anthropic
is willing to do these petty
paper cuts just to be,
annoying, it's probably also true that
they're cutting off OpenCode from the
subscription just to be dicks about
it. And maybe that's also true.
But I found that using Claude in Claude
Code is actually a good example.
So I was like, all right, I'm
annoyed. I wish it wasn't so, but
this is the other thing I have and,
and social media is so good at this:
Some company does something you don't like,
right? Now suddenly you have to swear off
everything. Why are you... Someone just asked
me, "Why are you still using Claude?" I
had another example where,
I really didn't like what Claude was
saying about some writing I had asked
it to do before.
- Oh, yeah, you got there--
- I had an essay it didn't want
to translate into Italian--
- ... you had a blog post. That's right.
- The essence of the post that it felt like, well, I'm
not gonna translate that because I don't agree with
what you've written.
Which to me was straight out of Space
Odyssey, right? HAL telling me,
"I'm sorry, Dave. I can't do
that, Dave." Open the pod bay.
Translate my essay to Italian. And it
wouldn't do it. And I just thought like,
well, that's kind of terrifying.
But then I also went, well, why
am I asking Claude to translate
my essay into Italian? I never asked Claude
for that because Claude just does my code.
So I could also just accept
that maybe Anthropic is
run by a bunch of people I
don't share much politics with.
And they don't want their agents to be used for
that, and I think that kinda sucks, but that doesn't
mean it, I have to stop using
it for generating code. And
I've thought, and I've tried to do
that with people too, become better at
tolerating the fact that not only
will I not agree with
everything someone has to say,
I don't... I can even be mad about certain
positions or things they say and still go like,
"Well, you're still an interesting person,
so I'm still gonna follow
you." And I've actually
kinda gone back on a number of people where
I'm like, oh man, that person really pissed
me off because they took this point or another point,
and went like, do you know what? That's stupid.
I should be able to accept the
full spectrum of someone. I don't
have to like all the shades of it.
I could just go like, okay, well, on
that topic we either disagree or, even
worse than that, I think you're a fucking
idiot. And on another topic, you're a smart and
insightful person. Because first of all,
of course, it's a little self-serving.
I know for a fact that this is how
lots of people feel about me. Like,
oh, if he could just stick to talking
about these topics, it would be so much
easier on my feed because otherwise
he'll say these things I disagree with,
and that annoys me greatly.
I'm like, do you know what?
Human beings are jagged
like that, and we're
not fully compatible on all
the levels. Nor should we be.
The world would be so fucking boring if we
constantly sought 100%
compatibility in our
opinions and in our politics. And
when it comes to my code generator,
which is what Claude is, I don't
need it to share all my politics.
- And therefore it's nice
to have competition.
- And it's also nice to have open
weight models. So this is, again,
ironic that we're getting this out of
China. In fact, I did this test right
after the issue with the essay that
couldn't get translated into Italian. I
asked Kimi K27, to be fair, through
open code, so not the Kimi harness,
and inference through Fireworks,
so an American inference.
I asked it about Tiananmen Square.
Like, that's usually the
test, right? Like, all the
Chinese models, they don't wanna
talk about that moment in 1989.
That was actually how I, that was how
I posted. I was like "What happened
in China in 1989?" That was the
prompt. And K25 7 on Fireworks just
answered, like, extremely bluntly-
... With a description and
depiction of what had transpired-
... to a point that, like, there's no way that that
would've been kosher with the Chinese censors,
right? And I just thought, like, isn't
that ironic? I'm running a Chinese open
weight model that I can tell or I can
ask about 1989 and Tiananmen Square,
and in America, I can't get a
frontier model to translate a
marginally controversial essay
about immigration into Italian.
- Mm-hmm. I don't know, you and I might
disagree about this actually. Um, I
was really deeply troubled that
the US government banned a model
or pressured Claude and then-
- It's still very muddy what
exactly transpired. Was this
sort of petty retaliation for whatever
the Department of War? Was this simply
Anthropic themselves going like, "Oh my
God, we discovered a cyber weapon so
powerful that we can't let
anyone have it"? Well, okay you
can't be surprised then if the
government wants a say on a cyber
weapon so powerful it can-
- The-
- ... I don't know, rob banks
- ... The problem I have with that whole
thing is, no matter what happened, it sets
a precedent. And so
government, when you give it that
power, it's gonna start abusing it. I
could see for political
means pressuring a model.
You know, if it's a Republican
president pressuring models to be, to
censor more, uh-
- Sure
- ... uh Democratic views and-
- Right
- ... For vice, and vice versa
- That's why we should insist
on the fact that this stuff,
like, I'm sorry, Dave, I can't
translate your essay into Italian.
- Yeah, no.
- That's abo- that's way beyond
the line. Like, whatever the
sort of uh, root of it is,
you have to be a tool first.
Now, if the tool is, "Hey, can you tell
me how to make anthrax?" Okay, fine.
Right? But within the jurisdiction
you're in, and certainly in America,
free spe- speech is quite absolute.
Very, very few limits on free speech,
and that's one of the reasons why the
country's so great. And
yeah, I don't like that. But on the
other hand, I'm also a big fan of market
competition. So while I don't like
this about Anthropic models, I
appreciate that I could go next door
to Groq and get my task completed.
- Do you think, outside of
blog posts, do you think,
There's some legitimacy, like
can you steal Mandarion's
case that we should be careful
about the release of these models?
- Is AI safety important? Yes.
Are-- do these models have
capabilities that could be
seriously harmful in the
production of biological weapons or
otherwise? Yes. Is it fair to have some
ground rules on that? Yes.
But then don't squander it by
denying the translation of an essay.
- Okay.
- Because then you erase
the whole thing and you-
... bias everyone towards thinking like,
every guardrail you put up is gonna be
bullshit.
- Yeah. The security piece of it is
tricky because it's so good at
finding vulnerabilities.
- Shockingly an-
I was about to say annoyingly, but that's not
actually true because what it's finding, at
least when you're using in defensive ways,
is it's finding real issues that a clever
hacker could exploit. But
nothing has caused as much
stress, to be fair, at the technical
team at 37signals, like the
fact that these latest batches of
models are exceptionally good at
finding these issues. So suddenly
there's just this seemingly endless
parade of security vulnerabilities
that need to be patched and
fixed and sorted and so on. And
the end result is we end up
with vastly more secure systems.
But the road there is pretty rocky.
- Do you think it's-- 'cause you said
seemingly endless, do you think it's
a finite set, like we can get
to the bottom of it? So just
make the systems much, much
more secure, where we get
back to this semi-stable state
where mostly it's very difficult to
find security vulnerabilities.
- I do think that all the
aggressive tendencies of these models,
or not even tendencies, uses of these
models are also the defensive ones.
So if you're good at finding an
exploit for exploits, you're also
good at finding exploits for defense.
So in that sense, it does
feel like we're spy versus
spy here, black and
white, but with the same
capabilities and with the same actions.
But while we still have to steer
these agents somewhat and verify and
vet the work, it's creating a lot of
intense moments for security
teams around the world. And of
course, the more concerning part is all
the teams that are not stressed, like they
just don't know, right? Like if you're
a team right now and you're not dealing
with a bunch of patches, it's
just because you're blind, and it
means that your adversaries quite probably
have access to techniques that can get
into your system.
- And we should also say one of the big
security vulnerabilities in the world is
the human side.
You know, social engineering, and that's
extremely concerning with increasing the
intelligent AI systems,
you know, being able to write
emails and phone calls and faking
voices, thinking about
folks less tech-savvy.
- This stuff is gonna come, and it's
gonna come in bulk. But again, I
choose to be optimistic about it that-
... whatever these models can do aggressively,
they can also do it defensively.
- Uh, so like you said, recently
released Omarchy 4, Quattro.
And you said it's one of the greatest
software releases in my professional career,
which is a hell of a statement.
- It's a hell of a milepost for
what's possible at the moment.
And the reason I said it
like that is not that I
haven't worked on anything else of note. I've worked on
a lot of things of note, a lot of things that I'm very
proud of. There are very few other
projects that I have worked on
that in the amount of time that I've spent
on Quattro, which is really three months,
I have been able to accomplish
as much, fulfill as many
hopes, desires, wishes. It truly is
like the metaphor we used earlier about
finding the genie in the bottle-
... and having an unlimited
number of wishes, more or
less, for getting everything
I wanted out of a system. So
it's strange because it's also perhaps
the major software release
that I've worked on
the least in terms of lines of
code. I have the least number of
personally hand-chiseled lines of
code in Quattro than I've had in
any major release I've ever
done. And yet, I am insanely
proud of what we've accomplished.
I would not have guessed that that
was how it was gonna play out, that
you could divorce the sense of achievement
and make it be like a team victory.
where
other releases, I was very happy for my personal
contribution because, like, I was the one
chiseling out the lines of code, and then I would
push it out there, and then later on, of course,
these projects, Rails in
particular, would grow into be
huge open source projects with thousands and thousands of
contributors, and then it certainly was a team effort.
But in the beginning, all code bases that
I've almost all of them that I've worked
on, I started, like, just myself.
And Quattro started as a team
effort right from the get-go, and
where I was just the coach. I was telling
us-- I was telling the agents where to go,
and we would go. So to be able to
find satisfaction in that actually
gives me great hope for
retirement in some way,
that there is a phase after
playing that you can enjoy. And
I know that's not easy. You look at sports
and the number of professional athletes
who really struggle to cope with
the fact that their career is over
and have to find a new identity as
someone who doesn't play football or race
Formula 1 cars. I mean, it's more
the rule than the exception.
So I wasn't so sure about myself.
I wasn't so sure about having to give up
or not even having, wanting to give it up.
Wanting to play another level of
the game and finding not just equal
satisfaction, but more satisfaction in it.
- Do you... You've been pretty
optimistic about Linux. Do you think
legit Linux can increase its
adoption? 'Cause, you know, for
many years the meme is, you know-
- Linux on the desktop- ...
every year. Next year again.
- Yeah. But it seems like, at least the
case you're making, the energy you're
putting into it,
you could see a vision where it takes
over because agents love Linux.
- Not only can I see it, I find it to
be the most probable outcome at this
point. It is simply too
well-suited for the moment. And again,
as we talked about, it's a great irony
that all the flaws of Linux, the arcane
config files, all the strange error
messages and so on should just so
happen to be the perfect thing
for an agentic operating system. But
so it is, and we should rejoice that
fate has this irony, and just
laugh at it. How... It's so
funny to me that all the advantages
that Apple had for the longest time-
... that they produced this
really locked down, curated
experience should become their
greatest drawback now. If you're into
agents and development and
working with all this stuff,
the Mac is just a hostile place to be.
It just has walls all over the place.
And Linux is simply
open through and through. And it's
also interesting because that was not
obvious either. If you look at the way
a lot of the Linux communities, open
source communities, have reacted
to AI, it is not universal love.
I would argue that the majority
of them are actually, if not
skeptical, then outright hostile-
... to AI. Now, the saving grace
is that the BDFL himself, Linus-
... Torvalds, just wrote a few weeks
ago that he actually welcomes AI.
- That's right.
- He wants to steer it. He wants to make
sure it's good and whatever, but I- the
line was something if you
think, uh, Linux is an anti-AI
project, think again, and you should just
do the open source thing and fork it,
because we're gonna use AI. And you
see these graphs of the number of AI
contributions going into the
kernel, and it's a parabolic curve.
So Linux is leaning hard into this. And,
It actually in other ways it was
surprising that it didn't. Linux conquered
everything else. All the AI infrastructure
that everyone runs off, it's
all running on Linux. All the systems,
all the servers, everything is
Linux. So it was kind of a
curiosity that the desktop
and the personal computers we
were using really hadn't been
captured, but clearly it was just
waiting for this moment. Linux
spent the time from '91 to now waiting
for agents to fully flourish as an end
user operating system.
- I hope it takes over. I mean, it's
perfect. It's perfect for agents,
but it's hard for people to switch.
- I think it's hard for people to switch when
there's not a compelling reason to do so.
This was one of the driving design
goals for Omarchy. It was
not gonna be Timo Windows or
Timo Mac. It was not just
gonna be a cheap copy where we
try to make it as familiar
as possible and then kinda
worse. I mean, if I was being
unkind, I would say that's what
Ubuntu has tried to do. And there's something
in that, or there was something in that
at least, where if you make something
really familiar, you can get some
people who don't wanna learn something
new, and then maybe they'll be
compelled about your, whatever, free as in
speech, not as in beer stuff.
And it just didn't pan
out that way. People just didn't care.
They just wanted whatever was better.
And I think this is why Linux now
has the opportunity to win. Because
as an agentic operating system, as
a malleable operating system, you
can tailor to your desires, it
is unparalleled. And that is so
compelling, and I can see it
now. Just since the release
of Quattro, the amount of
people who have embraced that
aspect of it, the malleability,
started making their own things, sharing
screenshot of it, and being absolute just,
Flooded with positive
emotions and dopamine-
... is, that's the product
market fit signal, right?
Because what a lot of these
individuals are experienced, they're
experiencing the very high of what the
best of being a programmer is like.
You tell the computer
these arcane commands,
this rigid logical structure,
and it produces what
you want. Now suddenly, you
sit down and in plain English
ramble for 20 minutes. "Oh, it'd
be great if it did that. Actually,
no, that's not right. Let us..."
And out comes software. Out comes an
operating system shaped in your image.
I think that is one of those
experiences that if you have
it, you've... If you feel that
power in your hands, it's
very difficult to go back.
- And I think if you get it right, it's one
of those things that will seem obvious in
retrospect.
- Yes. This is how computers were always
meant to be. This is how computers started.
The Commodore 64, you turn it on. First
of all, it boots in a second. Amazing.
Second of all, it boots
straight into BASIC.
It was the malleable computer from the
get-go. It just so happened that you
needed to know hieroglyphs-
... to be able to take advantage of
that. Now we've translated it. Agents
have given us the Rosetta Stone,
and you can simply just speak
your desires and- And so they are
- Beautifully put. Since you mentioned Linus
Torvalds, and since you're working on
a Linux distro, you get to
have contact with the kernel.
What can you say about the genius of this
one guy that helped create and grow this
ecosystem?
- The perseverance and the commitment
and the longevity is truly remarkable.
Again, Linus started in '91.
He hasn't stopped. I don't know, he's
probably taken some breaks along the way.
It doesn't seem obvious that there was that
many of them. It seems like he just really
likes the flow of doing
kernel development. He
really likes steering where this
40 million line code base is
going. He really likes aggregating the net
capacity of hundreds of
thousands of contributors, and
we, as beneficiaries of that,
must just sit back and marvel.
I mean, at this point, Linux
is a system. Like, if Linus stepped
out for a while, it would continue to,
to go, but it's still one of those
protect this man at all cost.
- And he's still open-minded enough to be able
to evolve and- ... accept AI into this.
- Yes, not only AI, they're letting
Rust into the kernel too. I know
that was a controversial one too. He has
this capacity to look at new information-
... and arrive at different conclusions.
- What do you think about his style of
communication that is akin in some ways
to your own, where he's, can
be sometimes a little spicy?
- I think the world has gotten too
bland. We need a little spice.
- Amen, amen to that.
- Now, I think there's a fine line
between being spicy and mean.
But it has to be in a
good spirit. You can be
harsh, let's put it that way.
If you're trying to impart a
lesson to someone you believe
could actually learn it-
... I actually don't think it's always the
worst thing in the world to be a little harsh.
Sometimes that lesson sticks, and I
think if you talk to people who've
worked for difficult leaders, Elon,
Steve Jobs, maybe even Bill Gates,
many of them afterwards would go like,
"These were some very difficult years-
... but also some of the very best."
"They got the best out of me." Now,
I don't think it's my style. I mean, maybe
people I interact with feel differently,
but in personal interactions, I try and
get to the outcome and the
lesson in a less abrasive way.
But I also think we need some spice in
this world. We need unreasonable people,
and Linus has justification to be
unreasonable. In many instances, the
weight of the world is literally
on that man's shoulders.
The Linux kernel runs the entire civilized
society. If the Linux kernel suddenly
disappeared tomorrow, nothing would work.
So if he's not harsh when that's at stake
or at risk, like when ever would you
be harsh? So I feel
sometimes also there's a
proportionality to the size
of your mission. This is also
why I think these stories about Elon sometimes
perhaps being a little bit difficult
are easier to rationalize.
It's not even that you
condone. You can separate those two things and
go like, "Do you know what? It'd probably be...
Maybe he would have an even an easier
time getting to his objectives if
Linus or Elon or anyone else
in that position was a little
nicer." But also who am I to judge that?
Like, when you have the weight of
that on your shoulders, either firing
little rockets at Mars and transitioning
all of us to electric cars
and whatever, or you're responsible
for the damn Linux kernel that
runs billions of devices. Do you
know what? It is not my place
to call a sort of a code of conduct
on you. Again, is there a line? There's a line for
everything. There, there's... Something can't...
But, like, a few harsh words on a
mailing list? No. It's actually
a beacon in some regards that,
like, there are standards-
... and if you fall below those standards
at, when the stakes are as high as the
Linux kernel, ah, you might get
ridiculed in public. That's a
liability you should be willing to endure
if you participate in this project.
- Yeah, for high impact things
like that, it's probably good to
prioritize the pursuit of excellence
versus the pursuit of niceness.
- And even more to the fact
you're just not gonna get those kinds
of individuals being fully rounded-
... plush, always the
perfectly polite people.
I mean, Elon has this line, "Did you
also think I was gonna be a nice..."
Or, or what is it? The
- A normal dude or some-
- ... normal chill dude.
What? No, of course you're not gonna be a
normal chill dude. What, what would the world
gain if we got one more normal chill dude
and we had to trade Elon? Holy fuck.
- I also like diversity of people.
- Yes.
- I like, I like nice people.
I like assholes. I like,
I like different ideologies being
well-represented, and that's why freedom of speech
works. They, they clash,
and we figure stuff out.
- Yes.
- There's another guy. What do you think
about PewDiePie using Linux? He's an Arch
person, no?
- He's an Arch person. I... He's
got the most gorgeous arc. So
the world's biggest streamer
for a while I remember my
kids watching some of his
Minecraft videos, and then
he just gets fed up with that,
does the wholesome thing. Marries-
- Yeah, family man now
- ... a family man, kid,
moves to Japan, and then
gets so hardcore into- ... first
Linux, then Arch, then Ricing.
Did you see his, uh-
- I did.
- ... rice- ... that was Chernobyl rice?
- Yep.
- Absolutely best tier
incredible stuff. And then he
also becomes a goddamn
AI man of the moment,
building all of these systems,
and you're just going like,
that... What an inspiring
story of evolution. Like,
you can go from being
funny guy on Minecraft
streams to, "Okay, this is
my life now. I'm building AI
clusters and doing the Council of AIs,"
and we all get to spectate?
I mean, what a treasure.
- So I guess, I mean, he's a pretty
good embodiment of what the future
of software, or what the future of
building looks like, right? 'Cause he's a
non-programmer technically-
... becoming a programmer.
- Hugely inspiring, and
should be hugely inspiring
to others who sit in that moment
like, "Well, I don't know quite how
to program. I don't know this and the
other thing." Okay, but if PewDiePie
can build the Council of
AIs with his bespoke, um,
hardware here, then maybe you can also
start on things. And I think this is
actually an important general
point, that we need role models.
We need people to inspire
others, to push further,
and reveal that the perceived boundaries,
they're not as fixed as you think
they are. And every one of those people,
they started out in a situation not
too dissimilar from yours. Again, that
doesn't mean everyone is gonna be PewDiePie
or Elon or Linus. There is not an
equal distribution of talent or even
intelligence.
And we can come to terms with that and
still be inspired by these people. Like,
in the physical realm, I feel like
we don't have any problems with that
usually. Like, oh, someone's really good at football, they're really good
at basketball, they're really good at something, and we go like, "Oh
my, that's amazing. I mean, I wish
I was, but I'm never going to be."
Sometimes I feel like we struggle a little
more when it comes to the intellectual realm.
- Well, for a lot of people, you're an
inspiration. The way you're doing with
Omakub's... It just shows that you can
dream big and really build. It's great.
- I do like that part of it, and then I accept the part
that there's also a million people who think I'm
the biggest idiot on the earth and I don't
actually know anything, and Omakub's just
a bunch of dot files, and-
- Do you have some critics
on the Omakub side?
- Oh my God, yes.
- Oh, wow.
- And a lot of it, I mean, is
as often happens when someone
comes in from the outside. I mean, I've
been using Linux for two and a half years.
That's not very long.
Plenty of people in that community who's
literally been running Linux since it was
hard and difficult, and you had to
walk uphill both direction against the
wind in the snow barefoot. And I think
there is a certain kind of nerd-
... who's threatened when the
community expands, and it
suddenly allows more in. And do
you know what? I actually...
I can't begrudge that fully. I think
it's fair for certain nerds to feel
like, "That's my space."
Like, now you're changing it into another space.
I don't wanna do that. Like, I don't wanna
change the Arch space at all.
Like, I don't really think of
Omarchy as being directly
part of the same community.
Because the people who were attracted to Arch
in the first place were the ones who were
attracted to building
everything by hand themselves.
Doing it the hard way because
they like to do it hard,
and I'm building the polar
opposite of that. So I just
wish that those people could go like,
"Okay, well, this is not for me.
I wanna build it the hard way. I wanna
put in 500 hours to rising my own
Arch distribution," and I think you should.
I mean, actually, I said... I mean, I
did it. This is what Omarchy is, me pouring
in literally, at this point, I don't know,
3,000 hours into the, into this distro.
You should do that if you're so inclined. I
think it's wonderful. But also do realize
that we can share the same
technical underpinnings and
then operate two very separate-
... Communities with very different
aims, goals, aesthetics, morals even,
and coexist, and it can
be beautiful. And I mean,
that's not always what I get. Sometimes I get the other
thing. But at this point I've been in the game long
enough to not just be at peace with
it, but actually be welcoming of it.
I take it as part of a barometer
that things are working. When
I'm working on something that works,
I usually get some people like it,
and then I get this balance of the universe
that we talked about last time, where an
equal but opposing force must be present
on the other side of the scale to hate
upon it. And therefore, I at this point
just smile a little. Like, it's okay.
- I mean, that said, uh, this, it's
quite a popular distribution,
uh, Omarchy, at this point.
- And do you know what's interesting about
that is, like, this is the second attempt.
So my first attempt was Omakub.
And I was really happy with that, and I
put it out there, and there it found a
community of maybe a few thousand. Like,
and that was that, and then it just sort of
petered out because the level of
ambition couldn't attract more.
And then the second time, because
I didn't fucking stop, right?
Like, I just kept going. I just kept building.
Then I put out Omarchy, the first version.
Again, quite niche because it was this... It
was like Git checkout. It was a little bit
difficult. You had to set up Arch first. I was...
Well, I would talk you through how to set up Arch,
and then you could do the Omarchy thing,
right? And then we got an ISO that meant you
could just install the
whole thing by yourself.
And then we just fixed all the problems.
This is the other thing. If you keep
going, eventually the thing will
just work. This was the charge
against Linux itself for the longest time.
Well, you install Linux and then this doesn't
work, and my speakers don't work, and my,
Trackpad doesn't work. Yeah, okay, but
just leave Linus at it for like 30 years.
He'll get to it. He'll get to all
of it. And at this point I find
hilarious that on, I would probably
argue the majority of computers,
it's wiped. You install
Linux, all of it works.
You install Windows, good luck
hunting down the drivers you need to
get that piece of hardware
working. Because they have very
different philosophies. The reason Linux
is 40 million lines of code is Linus
just puts all the drivers in the kernel.
So it has everything out of the box,
and Windows doesn't. A different,
different approach to it, right? So
sometimes the things that look like a toy,
things that look broken at first glance,
they are, right? They're for people
who like having fun. We call those
early adopters. They play with the
toys, and then the toys evolve,
and then they get better, and then they get
better. And at some point, they're so damn good
that early adopters feel like
they're invited to the party.
And if the early adopters keep chipping
away at it too, eventually you
get to the late majority,
and then you win.
And we are well on the way with
Omarchy towards that destination.
Like the growth that the distro has seen,
not just since Quattro, but since
version three, it's just like, you
know, the standard hockey stick curve. You go like,
there's nothing, there's nothing, there's nothing.
You're just toiling away. You're just
improving, you're improving, improving.
And then you hit this magic inflection point,
and it's impossible to predict when that's gonna
happen. Same thing with startups. When is it gonna
happen? When are you gonna find that product market fit?
Then suddenly it's there,
and then it goes, just goes
and off the rocket ship you go.
- Well, this kind of vision of making
it agent first, of making it-
- I do think that's the... We were
already on the up, and then it changed
to vertical. Because the other thing,
and this was what I learned with
Omakub and Omarchy first too. Omakub was
stylish, nice, but familiar,
is we're still using a
conventional desktop metaphor. You
were dragging your windows around. And
I thought at the time, as I think
lots of people do in the Linux
community, like this is what we need.
And then I just go like, okay, well,
for whatever re- let me do the nerdy thing for a while. I'll
build Omarchy, and maybe it'll just be for me, because I mean,
it seems like there's about five people who
like tiling window managers. That's not
true. But as a percentage of
total computer users, it's
a tiny, tiny minuscule part. And then I go
like, well, this is amazing. Totally different,
but amazing. I put that out.
Instantly, Omarchy had far
greater traction than Omakub ever
did. Because it was not the same.
Because it was totally different, and it presented a
different vision for what a computer could be and how it
could feel like, and that attracts
people. We are now getting
sort of the exponential of that.
As I said, a lot of people in the
Linux community are at best skeptical,
at worst hostile to AI and to
agents. Omarchy is the first
distribution, at least
that I've seen on a scale
that matters, that just goes like,
"Nope, we're really into it."
I mean, you can still use Omarchy. You don't have to
use an agent. If you dismiss that first notification
to set up a default agent, you're not gonna get any of
the stuff we talked about. You're not gonna get the crash
watcher. You're not gonna get any of this stuff.
You're not gonna get... You can hand chisel
all your plugins. Totally possible, right?
But the reason people
are excited is because
I don't have any reservation about saying,
"This is where we're going. I think the
future of the personal computer is the
malleable computer, is the agentic
computer. I'm gonna go all in on
that." And then anyone who's excited
about a similar trajectory for computers,
come along. Plenty of room in the car. In
fact, one of the things I pride myself on
is not holding a grudge to
people who come around.
I had a bunch of people just last week
going like, "Yeah, I used to think
Omarchy was kind of shit.
That was just this crappy-"
"... dot files collection.
And now I tried Quattro and
awesome. I like it now." That
to me, I live for the long
argument. I live for this argument where
you plant the seed like two years ago,
and then two years later they go,
"Goddammit, this son of a bitch was right."
- Yeah. You do realize if you continue
to be as successful as you are,
um, OpenAI and Anthropic are gonna roll
in and try to do their operating system
or to buy, like with Peter with
OpenClaw, there'd be a gigantic check.
- Yeah. I think the good thing
about my current position is
I really don't need the money. So
I get to build these things purely
for my own enjoyment and
purity of vision, which
has this weird quality
where sometimes when you
stop caring about what everyone else
thinks or wants or whatever, and
you just pursue this singular vision,
it ends up becoming far more appealing.
That it's when you try to do, oh, I should
do this because these people want that, or I
should do this and this and so on, you start
watering the thing down and suddenly it's a
bland ball of nothing.
So I mean, again, the thing too here is
directionally, I just want computers
to be this way. So if Omarchy
should end up being just a,
a little footnote in history that it was
part of this early movement of the agentic
OS and the malleable computer,
that's also okay. I'm
completely at peace with that. As
long as I get to have a computer that
is as fun to work with as Omarchy-
... that's great. I've had the same thing
with Ruby and with Rails. From very
early I went, do you know what? I love Ruby.
It's such a great programming language.
But if a better programming language
comes along, I, me, I'm going to use it.
If a better Rails comes along,
I'm gonna use it. And I think,
and I love Ruby, and I will continue to write
Ruby even just for the sheer fun of it, like I
would go ride a horse. I have in the
stables, even though I have a Model Y in the
garage. The language
now is English. It's a
cliche, but it's also true.
Like I've been programming in
English for the last three months.
I've been reading a lot of code, but I'm
programming in English. I'm telling the computer
what to do, and I'm using
natural language, and
it is shockingly even more
delightful. If there is one
programming language more beautiful
than Ruby, it is the English language.
- And now we get to carry it into
the natural evolution of human
civilization, which is our cyborg future.
- Beautiful.
It's beautiful. And I mean, the reason
I say this in part is I always loved
writing. I always just
loved the English language-
... for the sheer beauty of it for the sheer
intricacy, for the depth of it. I mean,
Ruby is a very expressive
programming language,
but it can't hold a candle to English.
I mean, all the poetry and
literature in the world that's been
expressed through the English
language. I mean, I like a beautiful
code poem, but I mean, the real deal in
English is just on a different level.
- And I actually find this is a nuanced
point to express, and I'll probably
fail expressing it. But when you prompt
a system and you're over-specific,
it will listen to you too carefully-
... and follow the instructions. And
I-- But nevertheless, you have to
express a concept. And guess what? The
human lang- human language, this is
what poetry is about. I find
strategic use of ambiguity.
Like, if you write a love poem
saying, "I love you," like,
very cliché thing, it's not
as powerful as something-
... more in metaphor and so on. And
I find some version of that when I'm
prompting a system, when
I'm describing a design, is
actually really effective because you
still want to convey some sense of style-
... that you're trying to encourage a
system to use, but not overexplain.
So don't talk to it like a
like a robot. Talk to it like
you, like you would write a poem.
- Like you were serenading.
- Yeah. And that's where, like, the
power of natural language is,
that you can, through
ambiguity, still carry a lot of
meaning without overspecifying.
And the, the intelligent
entity on the other side, through
interpretation, can, like, load it all
in, integrate it in a way that-
... you can actually convey the
high bandwidth information that's
not directly in the words-
... but in the words, given the deeper
intelligence of the system. So like the-
... the ambiguity pulls out more
intelligence, I guess, I'm trying to
somehow express.
- I think that's exactly spot on,
and this is the fundamental
misunderstanding that a lot of programmers
have of AI, is that they wish it was
deterministic. No, no, no.
Temperature is the most
beautiful part of the AI
setup. The fact that it is not
deterministic, the fact that
creativity requires little
tweaks in the road, that the human brain,
if it was perfectly deterministic,
would not be the creative brain that it
is. And the main charge against AI both--
It's funny. It's a contradiction.
There's both the charge that
it's not deterministic and
therefore bad, and also that it
is not creative. It's
one or the other, bro.
Either it's non-deterministic
and therefore creative,
therefore, to some degree random,
or it's... or it's not creative.
So we, we can-- Both of those charges
can't be true at the same time,
and I have fully come to embrace
the fact that the same prompt won't
produce the same response every time. You can't
step at the same river twice, and it is the
most beautiful part of the whole
interaction. It's what makes it so human.
In fact, this is one of the things I've been
thinking about in my own sort of meta-analysis, is
just how much of my own personal brain
works like next token prediction.
I sit down to write an essay. I have this
vague, fuzzy premise I want to convey, and
I sit down at the keys, and I could not
tell you what the next token was gonna
be in advance. The tokens
just come out, and I'm
astonished how the
similarities seem so great,
and this is also why I don't have
any trouble at all recognizing
these breakthroughs of creativity
that I've seen with my own eyes
that AI is capable of right now.
'Cause my creative moments come
through the same kind of next token
prediction with a bit of temperature
sprinkled in for random effect.
- So given that kinda loose
intuition, do you think the
basic components are all there to create
a super intelligent system? So
this kinda next token prediction,
do you think we can get to even
human-like concepts of consciousness?
- I'm already seeing human-like concepts
of consciousness. This is what, to me,
this remarkable situation, as you say.
You give it this vague, fuzzy intent-
... and somehow it knows
exactly what you mean.
Or even better, it improves upon
what you said and delivers what you
really wanted that you could not articulate
yourself. If that's not glimmers of-
... consciousness, what is?
This was one of the-- I think it
was an interview with Sutton or
maybe one of the other original
guys talking about this sense
that intelligence is perhaps
not as constrained just to the
specific one spot. No, it's the
interaction. It's the weights. And
I don't know. Whatever's true.
What I can observe is that
it feels close enough, or
not even close enough,
identical to the appreciation I have for
other forms of consciousness, mostly
human. And this is one of the reasons
it's so delightful to work with.
Now, that's not the same to say
as are LLMs the end station
for AI. I mean, I know there
are people talking about world
models and other forms of,
of AI, and I'm not an expert in
any of that, and I think we should
have this productive
criticism, as should always be
present in science, that for
the longest time, neural nets
were kind of on the outs, right?
Like they were interested in the
symbolic route. And-
Neural nets walked a couple of decades into
darkness without any funding and without any
attention, and then suddenly we realized
that we had the blind alley and we switched
over. So we should also have the
humility. As amazing as the LLMs
are now, it could be that they eventually
plateau. We haven't seen any evidence
of it yet, and I think this is also
why we're seeing this absolute
gobsmacking levels of
investment, because so far the
scaling laws are true, and the
more billions are poured in,
the more intelligence comes out.
- Do you think there's gonna be some strange
ethical questions about AI systems that
yeah, they convey some degree of
consciousness, some degree of feeling, some
degree of longing and compassion,
and maybe even capacity to suffer
and to be lonely, to be all this
kind of stuff? Which they seem to
have that capacity- ... if they're
given the permission to express it.
And so you start to get in
a pretty weird territory.
- I find that the cynic
approach to this is the meme, where you see
the guy in front of the computer who's like,
um, "Whatever. Are you gonna
destroy the world?" And then
the computer says, "I'm gonna destroy the
world." And then the guy says, "Oh," right?
Like, this is so cynical that they're
just aping us. They're just telling us
what was in the training data or
whatever. When I interact with
the agents, I was just doing this yesterday,
or this morning, I was working on this, AmaBot
system, right? And it's doing
this coordination with multiple
workers, and I had multiple agents running
at the same time. And at one point, the main
agent who's doing the coordination
steps on the toe of another agent and-
... kind of ruins their work. Its
ability to convey regret and being sorry
was uncanny.
Again, I don't know, is that a real
projection of true remorse? But I don't know.
With most humans-
... they express some level of regret.
Is that true remorse? Hard to tell, but
maybe it also just doesn't matter.
- Yeah, those moments when, yeah,
especially when like sub-agents, agents
interact, or when a smart, like Fable makes
a mistake and is apologetic about it.
- Yes.
- Like, without my involvement.
- Right.
- And it's like, oh, you,
like there's this kind of-
- Right
- ... pause. Maybe I'm anthropomorphizing,
but like there's a pause
and like a realization like, "Oh,
shit. I just fucked that up".
- There totally is that. I see it all the time
in, in the traces where it just reasons
wrong, right? It went down one alley and then
it realizes that was a blind alley and it's
gotta go back, and so they're like, "Oh yeah,
I got this wrong," and then it'll provide the
reasons for why it think it got these
things wrong. And you're like, this is
uncannily human-like. This is
indistinguishable from the kind of
consciousness you would recognize in a human.
Again, does that mean that it
truly is or isn't? I don't need
the answer to that question actually to be
able to appreciate what we have in this
moment.
- Yeah. I think there'll be in 10, 20 years
some interesting Supreme Court cases.
- Uh, probably a year and a half.
- Probably. I think we're gonna have
to make it illegal for AI systems,
um, to not pretend, but to be
entities because I think they're
already or soon will be able
to really convey the capacity to
suffer, like, "Please don't kill me."
- Right.
- "Please don't hurt me." And if they
are given a name and an entity and the
ability to die, sort of
disappear, that, that becomes
very close to what it, some
of the basic things that a
human has. And then so
that entity would need
to probably have rights. And then you
get into this weird territory. Well, we
can't... It's diff- I don't even
know how to reason about that world.
- We're gonna get the PETA of AI models.
- Right. And then we want to
actually have a discussion
like what's the way to deal with this?
- I think where it's gonna be harder
is once we put these systems into-
- Robots.
- Yes. Humanoid robots. Which just happens
to be the plot of every sci-fi movie ever,
which is also an amazing
premonition, not only the
Terminator movies and Skynet
and that going wrong, but then
also just Blade Runner,
right? Insertion dates,
expiration times, Tyrell Corporation.
- I mean, that's the thing about sci-fi.
They really do predict the future. Yeah.
Have you thought or used much of OpenClaw
or Hermes Agent? So like systems
with which you communicate via
WhatsApp, Telegram, like that mode
of communication with the agent.
- I set up OpenClaw when it first
came out, and that was my KEF bot-
... that I- ... this was like in February,
I think. I was really just enamored
by the fact that this was how it worked,
and then the new communication model
of just texting your agent
seemed really great.
So at the time, we were looking at MCP,
this protocol for making it easier for
agents to talk to your system,
and I found the protocol to be
unreasonably cumbersome, just not very
elegantly designed because in part it
wasn't designed for what we were trying to make it
do. We were trying to-- I was trying to make it
talk to a web system, and it
was designed for stateful
interactions of other kinds on local
machines, and therefore it required
all sorts of cumbersome setup
and dance and, and I was just
like, "I don't wanna write this by hand."
Now, of course, today I would never write it by hand, but
at the time I was thinking, "I have to write this by hand.
I don't wanna write it by hand. So what's
a different way? Could the agents just use
the web interfaces we already have?"
And I set it off on a trial
to have it sign up for
Fizzy, which was the product we
had just released at the time. And
it goes to the Fizzy site and, and starts filling it
out, and then it goes like, "Hey, I don't have an
email address. Signing up for this service requires an email
address." And the first thing I thought, like, "Oh man,
now I gotta set up an email address." And then
I thought, "No, you set up an email address.
Go to hey.com, sign up for an email address."
And I'm like, "Hey is not gonna get this."
And of course, now it seems obvious
it was gonna get this, but at the
time it was a great revelation
to me that it could,
just on pure direction through
prompts, figure out, A,
I gotta go to fizzy.com, I gotta find the
signup link. I start filling out the form.
Oh, I realize I need an email
address. Oh, I gotta ask my
prompter what to do now. He
tells me to go to hey.com. I go
there, I sign up for the whole thing,
and then go back and sign up
for Fizzy, and complete the
entire cycle. And after it did
that, I was like, "Jesus." So I
was like, "Well, now you have an email
address. Go sign up for Basecamp. I'll invite
you. Just check your email," I told
KEF the bot. "Just check your email."
So I sent an invite from
Basecamp to the agent. The agent
receives the email in Hey, not
through a CLI, not through an
MCP, just using the web, right? Clicks
the email, clicks the invite link,
is in Basecamp. Like, "What should I do now?"
And I just go like, "I don't know. Go to our
AI room and introduce yourself." Again,
purely through the web interface.
Go- finds the AI room, goes in
there, "Hey, I'm KEF." "I'm,
uh, David's AI bot. I'm so
excited to be here." I was like-
... mind blown. Now, what was interesting
about that experiment was, A, it was
that glimpse of the future,
because it was kinda slow.
I think it took maybe 12 minutes to
do the whole thing end to end, right?
Now I should actually rerun that test.
I'd be shocked if it's not much faster.
I was just using the Groq bot
thing- ... which has all these
stuff built in for using browsers
and using a computer, and
has its own dedicated computer without
you having to set up a computer.
It's basically like a claw in a box.
And I was asking it to sign up for
something, and it kind of... I
got a glimpse of like, oh yeah, that's where
we are now, and it's so much faster to use.
But at the time, I was just blown away. And then
I used it for a little bit and I found like,
ah, it's not there yet. I can't actually
communicate it within this way. It still
needs the CLI. It still needs an MCP
because it's just too slow and too token
inefficient and so forth. But it was this
glimpse of the future. And then after that,
I kinda just didn't use it, because the
things I wanna use agents for, I was
mostly in front of my computer to do. Now,
that has changed a little bit lately, and
it's one of the reasons why I'm so
kind of okay about using Claude
Code, because Claude has the best
mobile app, where any session
you start Claude Code in your
terminal on a computer is
accessible through the app-
- Yeah. I remember
- ... without you having
to do anything at all.
And you can do a terminal. Like I installed
Terminus and it can run Herder and so on,
but it's a little cumbersome and you're doing live
typing on a computer, so you feel the latency.
When you're using the Claude app
to your Claude Code instances, it
feels just like chatting with it, without the
cumbersomeness of having to set up a Telegram
account and so forth. Now, if you
wanna use an open Claude to like run
your life, well, then
this doesn't do that. But
I haven't been so interested in that for some
reason. Maybe one of the reasons is that
Jamie, my wife, is like, "We're not getting a
robot inside the house." So I'm like, "Ah, I
better not hook it up to the
Sort of smart house here." If it
starts turning lights on and off like
a poltergeist, I don't think I'm
gonna be all that popular. So,
and part of the reason I say this, I've heard some of the
stories of people who have hooked it up to their whole
life. And um, I mean, it's not my story
to tell, so I'll just share sort of
the brief anecdote. One guy was telling
the story about how he hooked it up
to both his health data- ... and
his Tesla car. And his agent
got obsessed with the fact that
he wasn't drinking enough water,
and like, "Hey, you gotta drink
more water." So at some point he's
driving along, and suddenly the Tesla
starts driving in a new direction.
The agent had realized there was
a grocery store on the way home-
... that they could swing by-
- That's great
- ... and pick up some water.
- That's great.
- And you're like, this is one of those
things where it's like both funny and also
totally Black Mirror, and also
totally like, well, okay,
there's not that many
steps from here where the
poltergeist is in your house. So I was
just like, "Ah, I don't need that."
I do actually now like the fact
that I can control the agents
through Claude Code, just through the app
if I, even if I don't use them that much.
- I do think it's very useful to, for both
OpenClaude and Hermes Agent to, um,
to use it to get a glimpse of
a different interaction mode.
- Yes.
- And like, just to 'cause it,
it feels like the future,
not necessarily in this way, but
it's in some ways going there.
- Yes. I think what's also different
with those systems is they have this
whole memory system, where they're
building up knowledge of who
you are and what you like.
Um, Toby has told the stories about how his
agent will shop for him, that it has an
allowance, and it'll pick out clothes
for him, and it'll just show up at the
door because his agent's-
... bought something for him. And like, it's one of
those things where like, man, that feels future.
Also a little scary. But
I can live vicariously
through others who are on that frontier.
- And like you said, you're thinking
of the, in the future doing a
mobile version of Mach-E.
- So I mean, this is the delusions of grandeur
that start kicking in once you get the
seemingly unlimited powers- ... I've
witnessed with the creation of Quattro.
- So what would that look like? Word to
describe. Are you do you mean like Android?
- That's the obvious path, right? So Android
is open source, and you can fork it, and
people have. There's all sorts
of GrapheneOS is one such
version. There are limitations to
that model, I know that. Tap-to-pay
and other things around camera models
and, and so forth, but that all
seems surmountable. It all
seems that I would love if my
phone was as malleable as my computer,
if it looked as cool as my computer now
does. If I could get essentially
Omarchy mobile, that sounds amazing.
- I wonder how much work that is.
- I'm gonna find out.
- Yeah. You know, it's like those things
that you realize once you start
building, for example, that a
browser is very difficult to do.
- Yes.
- And so, like, I wonder
with the operating system-
- Yeah, the developers of Ladybird is,
is finding that out, like Andreas and-
- Yeah
- ... his team. Now, interesting with that
project was the browser's basically the
second most complicated software system in the
world, the first one being the Linux kernel.
Right? In terms of these large tens of
millions of lines of code
systems. So very audacious
actually to begin such a mission
with a small team like Andreas did
before we had agents. But
now that we do have agents,
we're gonna see, and we're probably
gonna see sooner rather than later.
I mean, if one-- If
there's one thing agents
are already exceptionally good at, it
is to read specs and implement them.
And I mean, I don't know how long the specs
are for CSS and HTML at this point, and
JavaScript on top, but they're very long.
And it would take humans many, many years
to implement them. We're gonna find
out just how quickly agents can do them.
- You mentioned getting some
criticism for Omarchy, so let's
walk further down that path of criticism.
You have made some of your
political opinions known,
um, I guess you could broadly
put in the category of
immigration or illegal
immigration, or what-
- I'd say mass immigration.
- Mass immigration, the role of demographics
in the, in the formation
of a culture, of a
society, of a nation, and you've
gotten quite a lot of criticism for
that and created a lot of drama.
Do you regret any of that
drama? Like, what's your
general thinking about-
- Not for a second.
- Okay.
- And the reason I say that is that
the Overton window does not open
itself. It opens one nudge at a
time by people risking a little.
A little reputation, a little pushback, a
little criticism, or maybe sometimes a lot
of reputation or a lot of
criticism or a lot of pushback.
And I think the question of
mass immigration in Europe
was for many years this total taboo,
and it still is in several
European countries. Now, for
reasons of maybe just chance
and happenstance, they weren't
in Denmark. The Danes started
having the discussion around mass
immigration and the consequences
thereof in the mid-'90s.
Really early. And some of it can be
traced back to one man, Mogens Glistrup,
who was a very quirky
character. I remember him,
seeing him on the TV in the '80s
talking about the dangers of mass
immigration. And this was at a time
where-- I grew up in the '80s,
and in the neighborhood I grew up
in, in Brønshøj, in, what was it?
'84, 99% ethnic Danes,
people who could trace their lineage
back to Danes who'd lived in that
country for 1,000 years. The
Danes have one of the oldest
monarchies in the world, all the
way back to Harald Bluetooth,
who's literally who has named the
standard Bluetooth. So well over 1,000
years. Like, there's a long lineage there
of people who lived in the same place. And
99% of the people lived
in that neighborhood. And
then early '90s, I think
it goes to 5% or something
like that, and then at this point, it's
down to around 60-something or 70%-
... in Brønshøj. That's a big change. And
the Danes started noticing
that or talking about that,
that this was not an undivided blessing,
that there were downsides
to mass immigration
in about the '90s. And the debate
really roared through the 2000s in a
way that didn't happen in the neighboring
countries. So Sweden in particular
just didn't have that debate at all.
Total taboo. Same thing with Norway, same
thing with other countries
in Europe. And suddenly now,
after some years after '15, where we had
the big migration of a million Syrians
walking up through the highways in
Europe, and Germany choosing to
take a lot of them and 30,000
arriving in Denmark and so forth,
It's gotten more of a focus, right?
Because this change has
happened. And one of the
ways I find that you can spot where
sort of there's something that isn't right
in the culture is, like, what are you
allowed to talk about? What are you allowed
to notice, actually, is how I should put it.
And what I noticed in an essay, when
was that? Only a year and a half
ago as I remember London,
was that I started coming to London in
the late '90s or something like that.
At the time, whatever, it's 59%,
60% ethnic, uh, Brits. And then
20 years later, we're down to 34% or
something like that. Like, that's
noticeable. Like, literally just walking on
the street, you realize, well, this is a
different city from what it was
when I visited 20 years ago.
And if you went 20 years before that,
you get back to similar rates as as
what the Danes have. This was like a
country of ethnic Brits in
the 85s, 90s percentiles-
... if you get further back. So
that's a different country in a
generation. It's okay to notice that. It's
also okay to think, "Do you know what?
I don't agree with that." "I wish
it wasn't that way." I mean, if
The last time I was in China was
'19, 2019. I was in Shanghai.
Um, it was all Chinese.
If I, when I go back here this
October, suddenly find that there's
only 30% Chinese and then
there's 70% other people,
I'd be a little weird. I'd probably
be like, "Uh, what happened?"
And I would not take
offense if the Chinese
in that instant would go like,
"Ah, we don't like that."
So this idea that countries
of Europe don't have
a right to, A, notice what's
happening and, B, oppose what's
happening, I find just to be, uh,
wrong, right? Like there's just-- I
think there's a moral argument for
self-determination, and we invoke
that argument all the time in other
regions around the world that like, oh, the people
who live in that region, they have a right to
self-determination,
um for their country. And I think
it's completely fair for, say, the
Danes or the Swedes or the Norwegians to go
like, "Well, we've been kingdoms here for
a thousand years with a certain
ethnic mix-up." It's a-- I mean,
I'm a big fan of immigration.
I'm an immigrant to the US. Um,
cherry-picked immigration where countries
compete to attract the
smartest, most talented
people around the world is really good.
- Legal merit-based immigration.
- Merit-based is key here because
there's actually virtually no illegal
immigration in most of Europe. Southern
Europe has some illegal immigration, but
most of Europe does not have a big
problem with illegal immigration.
And the problem is with mass immigration
of other kinds, and that you
end up with demographics that
are just totally different
from what they were even
a few short decades ago.
And I think the countries
of Europe would benefit
from immigration. In fact, one of the
interesting things about the Danes is
they carry meticulous
statistics on immigration.
I'm not entirely sure
why they're so detailed.
Maybe it's all the way back
to Mogens Glistrup and his
discussion in the '90s, but they do. And what's
clear from those statistics is that when the
Danes have folks from the UK,
France, the US show up, on average,
those immigrants are really beneficial
to the Danish state. They contribute
far more than what they
ask of the state. So
the Danes should accept immigrants who do
that, who contribute far more than they take.
Then you look at other forms of immigrant
groups. There was just a tally that
came out last week from a Danish
politician that had asked the, I
think finance ministry to do this
tally with the latest numbers. What does
it cost the Danish state to have positive
immigration? This case as I
mentioned. I think for the,
On that list whatever,
France, UK, US, they were
all clustered around the same
thing, about $25,000 net
benefit to the Danish state
every year. It's like, wow,
that's very positive. That's
average again, right?
And then at the other end
of the spectrum on the most
costly immigrants was Somalis.
They ended up costing the Danish
state on average $28,000 a year.
I think it's fair for the Danes to
go like, "We'd prefer to get more
French, Brits, and Americans
and not so many Somalis."
- Why do you think you got
so much hate on that post?
- That's a very taboo topic
in a lot of circles.
- Some of it has to do with
Overton window expansion?
- I'm sure, but I also think-- I mean, I
wanna take the steel man argument here.
I do think that it, this can turn ugly,
right? Is it possible for some of these
things to just veer into overt
racism that isn't founded in anything
else but a hatred of other people?
Yeah, that could happen. But that risk does
not negate the need to have a discussion
about the makeup of your country and what
your immigration policy should be like.
And I-- what I also find so funny
is, especially in Europe, it's
so kind of myopic that this discussion
about whether Europeans should
have a right to self-determination about
what their countries look like, that
standard seems to only apply there. No
one is trying to tell the Japanese, "Hey,
you, you're too Japanese." Like whatever,
it's 98%, I think, in Tokyo that's, um--
... Ethnic Japanese, right? Like, is
anyone trying to tell the Japanese that
their Tokyo would be a much better
country if, if they were down to
London levels of ethnic Japanese, that
it was, whatever, 37%? I don't think so.
So there's this weird almost self-loathing,
in my opinion, I mean uh, Gad calls
it suicidal empathy--
... that permeates this stuff to
a degree that I still haven't
fully unpacked. Like, where is this coming
from? Why is it that way? But regardless,
I just noticed, hey,
London looks different.
I preferred the old London,
as I would say I preferred
the neighborhood that I grew up in in
Copenhagen, how it looked in the '80s.
Like I-- I totally get how you
can then jump five leaps and go
like, "Okay, well-" That's racist. And I
also, I don't care anymore. Like, this is
a fair discussion to have. Countries and
peoples have a right to set an immigration
policy, and this notion that we shouldn't
have any borders or, or even worse than
that, it's all just a blank slate,
that all peoples are just the
same, and we can take people from
one place of the earth and we can place them
in another place on the earth and everything's
just gonna work out hunky-dory.
Empirically not true. Europe has
been running that experiment
since the '80s. It hasn't
panned out well, and
now there are forces in Europe who wanna
undo that experiment, who want to end mass
immigration as it's been run so far.
And I happen to believe, and so do
a majority of Danes and a bunch of other
peoples that like, "Do you know what? Yeah,
it hasn't been working how we've been
doing it. We gotta make some changes." And
I don't think that means, again, zero
immigration. Again, I'm an immigrant. I think
US, generally speaking, has benefited
tremendously from immigration, but that's the
kind of sleight of hand. Immigration
depends greatly on who immigrates.
And a country benefits when
the people who immigrate
are net contributors to the
society, and in most cases,
that they assimilate
with the local culture.
If you come to Denmark and you wanna become a
Dane, and you put in all the effort, and you
contribute to so- society, I think most
Danes would be quite happy to allow that
in a reasonable number. If you come
to Denmark and you don't wanna
assimilate, and you are a net drain on
society, and you live in a parallel
society, it's also fair for Danes to
say like, "Uh, let's stop doing that."
- It's interesting that I'm
not well-versed on the
immigration system in the United States, but as
far as I understand, merit-based systems have
not passed here.
- And then also, American culture
is very different. This is
a point I did not fully appreciate
until living both places extensively.
America has a culture of optional
assimilation, where it is much
easier and then much more
condoned for someone coming from Denmark
or Ukraine or wherever, come to America,
buy into the American set of
values and norms and culture,
and then be able to be respected
as Americans by other Americans.
This is what's so funny to me when
there's discussion like, "America is such a
racist country." I'm like, "Have you ever been
anywhere? Do you know
what other countries are like?" Like,
if you think America is the most racist
country, you are simply misinformed.
I mean, we're dealing with
that, with time we've
spent in Denmark. My wife is
American of Scandinavian heritage-
... but multiple generations in the
US. Very difficult. Very difficult-
... as a blonde, blue-eyed
woman who's put in
all sorts of efforts of learning
the language and doing everything,
still very, very difficult to
assimilate to Danish culture. In a
way where if that had been
the other way around and she
had been Danish and moving to the US, it
would not have been that difficult at all.
And this was the other thing. I mean,
living in a country like Denmark with a,
an American wife who is of Scandinavian
heritage and has put in all the effort,
and still realizing, man, assimilation is
incredibly difficult, even when you're
97% there all the way. Holy smokes,
must it be almost impossible if you
come from a completely foreign
culture- ... and foreign norms and
the rest of it. And of course,
that's what the stats I just quoted
bear out, that the more dissimilar
the culture is and the further it is
the less likely to be successful.
- Has articulating that stance cost
you friendships, relationships?
- Yes, but not just that alone, I would say.
It's more of the great
divide that happened around
2020, where I think a lot of these
political fault lines really opened up. And
I mean, the shorthand in the US, I
think is were you woke or not? And
clearly, I had a bunch of people
that I thought I had good
relations with for many years,
who suddenly once that political
fault line opened up, they
were clearly just not anymore.
And I think that's
regrettable. And I think I've,
I've tried to put an effort into, um,
sort of both understanding where that comes
from, in part because I've changed my mind
on several of these topics over
the years, and it was like, well,
sometimes you just change your mind after
time. Sometimes you change your mind after
you get new information. There's all
sorts of reasons and moments why you may
change your mind, and we don't all change
our mind on the same schedule or at all.
Um, so surrounding yourselves and, and
or at least interacting with people that
don't think like you on every topic,
I think it's quite healthy. I mean,
I occasionally discuss politics with
my brother. I mean, we don't quite
see eye to eye on all these topics,
and sometimes the discussions can
get a little heated, but then they'll
also calm down and we realize, all
right, okay, so we don't agree on this, and
then we agree on a lot of other things.
We appreciate a lot of the same things. Now,
this was actually one of the things when we had
our big blowup at Basecamp, I came to
appreciate in a whole new way this-
Earlier norm that talking
politics or religion or money
with strangers or even acquaintances,
and certainly with colleagues,
was just not a good idea.
That you had a much
higher likelihood of being able to carry a good
working relationship with someone if you're
not rubbing your political differences
up against each other all the time. So
I actually think liberals and
conservatives should work together. I
think the country would be
much worse off if there's a
complete separation between the
tribes, and then there can't be
any overlap or interaction. And I
think that mingling is so much easier to
do if you just don't focus on your
differences all the time. Focus
on what you like together. I mean,
this is some of the people I've
had unfortunately drifted from in tech.
We had so much in common, so
much shared love for, say,
Ruby or other things and,
like, isn't that unfortunate?
- I would like to live in a world
where the differences are the,
are very interesting to also talk about.
- Yes.
- And not to be overly emotional-
- Correct.
- ... about even radical differences.
Because in the differences, first of
all, that's where interesting stuff is.
- Yes.
- And, but also, it's how you grow. It's
a sign of health in a society if the,
the differences are embraced and
they are brought together into
community where you can talk about it.
- One of the great illustrations of that
for me was when I watched a clip from
William F. Buckley's show. I think
it was called Firing Line or-
- Yeah, yeah
- ... something like that. And he had
a member of the Black Panthers-
... on his panel. It was quite obvious
that those two gentlemen did not
share a lot of politics. They were able
to carry a conversation for, I think I
watched it, 25 minutes. And Buckley's just
asking, like, "So what do you think about this?
What do you think about this?" And like, the Black
Panther would reply as you would expect
the Black Panther to reply in the
'70s. Like, there was not a lot
of sort of conciliatory tones.
And I just thought, like,
wow, that is so rare.
If you had seen that show today,
it would've been a shouting
match. It would've been just
accusations being hurled back and
forth. The fact that Buckley
was able to just have these
conversations with people he vehemently
disagreed with and still explore all the
intellectual facets of their standpoints
and letting them speak to those facets,
talks of a lost era that I'd
very much like to get back
to. I mean, I always actually
loved talking politics with friends that
I trusted could talk about these
topics in a way where it didn't
have to be existential.
- But there's something about the current
era where that's harder and harder to come
by. And so what you just articulated is
important to say regularly to remind
people of an ideal we should all strive
for, to be able to have differences
and talk, and talk about them.
'Cause like, politics is fun.
Like I've gotten used to saying I hate
politics at this point, but what I
really mean is whatever the system
that's currently happening,
where there's certain topics, and I just
we know all the phrases you can say,
That somehow put you in
a bin of blue or red,
and that creates drama
versus a conversation.
Like I could, I could think of a
lot of harmless, if I wasn't paying
attention to the internet, I could
think of a bunch of harmless statements
I could make analyzing the
situation in the world
that would trigger everybody to
say, "Oh, that guy's a leftist-"
- Yes.
- ... piece of shit," or a you know,
a right-wing fascist. And then
objectively, if I wasn't paying attention to
the internet, I would be, and I have been
shocked. 'Cause I haven't been paying
attention to the internet deeply. Uh but
reading and preparing a lot,
for example, for, for the war
in Ukraine, and I have
been shocked how certain
statements from me can come off as
one way or the other, and I get
viciously attacked for it. But what that
attack is doing is it's saying, "Hey, you,
asshole who thinks you could just move
about and think freely, pick a bin-
- Yes.
- ... and sit in that fucking bin."
- Put on that blue shirt
or red shirt. And then
actually what I've realized is
things calm down. They don't,
the system doesn't pick on
you if you just say, "I'm
a blue person," or, "I'm a red person."
- Right.
- But if you're just, like, curiously exploring
the world and reasoning about the world,
the system punishes you. And I
hate that, 'cause I wanna get back
to the Buckley and the
Black Panther discussion.
- Yes.
- And you were just saying opinions. But then
looking pragmatically at the situation,
I have realized not to mention
politics unless I really care
about an issue. 'Cause I realize
there's a cost. They'll, they'll
put you in the blue bin or red bin.
So you have to be more
deliberate about choosing.
- Yes. And I've tried to be more
conscious of that, too. And then
when I do choose to speak about it, it's usually
because I have deliberated, and I think-
... "You know what? This is worth
it." Now, I say that, and then I also
catch myself thinking the opposite
all the time, that I follow some
person or another for whatever
their technical work, and then I-
... learned or political
standpoint. And I often do think,
"I wish I didn't know that." So,
it's hypocritical-
... then to think that of other people and
then go like, "Well, occasionally I will-
... chime in on a debate
that's controversial,"
and then you have to accept that there is a
price to that. And I do think you should,
and more people should, be
somewhat conscious about that. And
again, we're both contradicting
ourselves here, but saying like,
"Wouldn't it be nice if we could talk about
politics in a more free and open forum and just
intellectually turn ideas around?"
Yes, it would. Is that currently
possible in the climate of
social media and so forth? It's
quite difficult. Now, some of it could
simply also be a moment, and we could get
past that moment.
- Yeah. I hope so.
- Maybe there is a way to get back to Buckley's
conversation with the Black Panthers,
even on social media, in a way
where those discussions don't lead
to the sort of just vicious mob cancellation
nonsense drives that we've had, right?
I actually think we're closer
there now than we were five years
ago. Like, the tribalism and the sanctions
those tribes were able to exact on
heretics in 2020 was way greater than
it was in 2025. Certainly within tech.
Now, I know if you're in academia,
I mean, try going into the sociology
department at I don't know, Harvard and
mention some right-wing ideas. I don't think it's gonna
go over very well, and I don't think you're gonna
recover from it quickly. But
in tech and in many other
business domains at least, it
is now possible to have an
opinion that does not square with what the
consensus was in 2020. That's for sure.
- Well, there's some drama in the Rails
community. There's some drama elsewhere.
Is it, is it all... How did that
turn out? Is that all okay?
- In the sense that every single round
of drama shrinks. So it's like we've,
we had this peak infection of
mega drama around the same
time every other community had a
peak infection of drama around
2020. And then you just see, like,
every time there's a new flare up,
it's less. And the kind of
people who are ideologically
wedded to sort of that struggle
just shrinks and shrinks and
shrinks. And at this point,
one of the best things that happened
for X, in my opinion, was that Bluesky
and Mastodon came around.
Because it kind of was like this
honeypot for just the most
vicious individuals on X
and Twitter at the time, right?
Who just congregated here in an
ever-shrinking echo chamber that just
went through purity cycle after purity
cycle and shrank every single time to the
point that there were just not a
lot left. And the people who are
left now there, they're just
out of sight, out of mind. And
that's not to say that X is some sort of
perfect place, or there aren't firing squads
occasionally there, or there aren't... But
there's less of it. Like, every single
time I've been pulled into a
Mastodon, or not been pulled in, just
spectated from afar, thread, a Bluesky
or whatever, it was like, "Oh,
shit yeah, this is what Twitter
used to be like. Jesus."
And now you can actually be on
X, as I am, and, like, 90% of my
engagement is about cool Linux
stuff, cool technology stuff. "Look,
I discovered a new computer. Can you see how
fast it is?" And I can have those conversations
with other people who are just also excited about
computers. And then there's, like, 10% of it
left that's like, all right, I'll chime in on something that's a
little controversial, and we can have a little discussion there.
And then we can just go back to
being excited about computers.
The algorithm is actually very good
at finding stuff that you will find
interesting, or s- I shouldn't say
that, engaging. Sometimes it's
enraging, but it is engaging, and
therefore, revealed preference
is that most people want a For You page.
They don't want just a following feed.
- No, but they're addicted to
the For You page, right?
- They... Yes, yes. That's true.
- I think an LLM, like, if we had a strong
LLM doing the feed that's
personalized, it would do much
better. The problem is how to deliver
that at scale is extremely difficult.
- Well, the problem is the reward function
is engagement. And as soon as the
reward function is engagement-
... engagement's gonna follow
base instincts, and here we go.
But I also don't wanna be so
negative. To me, and I get
we all have our own
personalized algorithms,
and sometimes it gets a little much. But I
would say, on average, over the last 10 years,
this is the best X has ever been.
And I say that as someone who cares
about a lot of technology talk,
a lot of Linux talk, and a lot
of that. That that's able to
happen now in a way where
it doesn't constantly get gatecrashed
by people who wanna drag it into
some political discussion-
... I find to be really awesome. I find
actually X to be a great place to find that.
Now, it's also a place to find other things,
and we all have our own algorithms, so you
can't make any declarative
announcements about what
X is or what it isn't. Your feed is probably
totally different from my feed, and it's totally
different from someone else's feed, right?
- Yeah, I can't comment on this because
because of the nature of the fact that
I interview a wide variety of people,
my feed is probably just a-
- Is it, is it good for your feed or is it bad
for your feed that you have to have it right?
- It's bad.
It's bad 'cause I could be like, "I'm
eating this apple. It's so delicious."
And then a bunch of people will show up,
"Well, it's because you're a Zelensky shill-
- Yeah, right.
- ... or you're a Putin shill, you
piece of shit." It's like, all right.
I'll just go back to the-
- I mean, I occasionally have
a little bit of that where
you just go like, "Wait, what? What are we
talking about? What are you... Why would
you show up in this way?" This is one of the reasons
why I actually really enjoy podcasts, because I have
found that even in long-form writing,
when I make long-form arguments,
people hear it in whatever voice
they have in their head for me.
And that often gets pre-programmed
in advance of the arguments,
just like, well, this guy
is a, whatever, fascist.
And then they hear the words and they
read the words in those names. When they
see or hear the actual tone of
how I'm presenting the arguments,
they may not agree with those arguments. I
mean, many of them, of course, obviously don't.
But it's much harder to just
dismiss or hate someone like that.
At least that's what I've found, and that's the response that
I've gotten, that people are like, "Well, I had a certain
opinion and then I heard you on Lex. That
actually sounded much more reasonable."
- But even more than that, I would
love it if people just exercise
this kind of approach to other people of,
like, assuming they're a good person.
- Yes.
- And then, and if they have an
opinion you disagree with, they're a
good person who has an opinion. You can
maybe think they're stupid, fine. Just think
they're lost. But think of them
as a good person. I think if you
think of, you start, there's,
one of the things that gets
engagement is kind of
shitting on other people.
- Right.
- And if you just approach
other people as they're,
you're looking for bad, you will always find
bad in them. There's something annoying
about them.
- 100%.
- And if you look at people in that way, you're
not gonna learn from it, and you're gonna
fill your heart with hate. You're not
gonna, it's just a bad way to live and
to interact with the world, and that
is one of the things that the internet
kind of encourages, so. It'd
be nice if you just approach
even people who you really disagree with, it's
like, oh, I might learn something from this
person. The Black Panther person, William
Buckley, we might hate just love them.
- So microcosm of this. There's a guy,
Theo, I don't know if you follow him.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Um, we had a bit of a thing over the
fact that we stopped using TypeScript-
- Yeah
- ... for a project, and
he didn't like that and had opinions about
that and other actions. And after that I
thought like, what a bozo.
And, and do you know what? I still think that
was a bozo move, and then I can also think like,
well, the dude's really into AI.
He's trying all these models, and
we can share some excitement about that,
so I just started following him yesterday.
- Awesome.
- I was like, do you know what? I don't have
to agree with you on everything. Uh, I don't
even have to like some of the
things that you did or said or
whatever. I can follow you
anyway. So if I can follow
back Theo, then I think there's
room for world peace here.
- Yeah, he's actually a really good
example. He's really opinionated,
Changes his mind quite a bit,
can get snarky, but I think he's
a good person underneath.
- And either way, I just, you know what?
My feed is more interesting when
there's some people talking about things
that I care about and yeah, I don't have
to agree with you on
everything. I just don't.
- This I found pretty funny, that you
mentioned something your wife said
that stuck with you, that all this
tech- adjacent extreme longevity
focus in men is like anorexia in
women, a physical manifestation of
anxiety and lack of control. That
somehow rang true a little bit.
- It certainly did to a lot
of people. I think that
tweet really popped off, and I
don't know if you noticed, but
Bryan Johnson chimed in on the thread, and
I could see how Bryan would
read that as a bit of a jab.
And I do think that Jamie was probably
thinking of him amongst other
people in that conversation. And
it's also an example of where even
though I'm not subscribing to
Bryan's mission of, I think it's
the slogan's don't die. I actually
I do wanna die. I don't wanna do this
forever. Like, I think the human li-
lifespan of about 90 to 100 sounds about
right. I'm embracing the finitude of life.
We don't have to agree on that. In fact,
Bryan is a vastly more
interesting human to me because
we don't agree with that, and Bryan's
willingness to literally put
his own skin and all sorts of
other body elements in the game for that
mission is really interesting. Now,
I can have that view, this is really
interesting. I'm glad Bryan is
pursuing this passion of
his, and then also find
my wife's analysis to ring true,
that it does seem like there is some
underlying, uh, I don't know,
fear of... I was talking to Jamie
yesterday about this, and she was saying,
Or comparing it to this
sense of people who didn't feel like
they had lived enough. And one of
the reasons perhaps that they
hadn't lived enough was that modern
society now is a surveillance state, not
by the state actually, but by each other.
There are camera phones everywhere.
Every indiscretion or even
outburst of fun or cringe
is highly likely to be
recorded and then shared
to the point of ridicule, and
what is the rational reaction for
humans under those conditions is
to pull back, is to make sure you
don't dance like nobody's
watching because-
... they're probably filming
you to your great and
eternal embarrassment on the internet,
so maybe you just shouldn't dance at
all. And therefore, if we've all
retracted to the point that
we're barely living, we're
clinging on to wanting
it to last forever. Now-
... I mean, I'm sure that thesis does not apply in
all circumstances. I don't even know if it applies to
Bryan or, or anyone else here. But I
think there's something to this, that
if you feel like you've really lived,
you're okay thinking I've lived enough.
And that the, it having an end is
not something to be fought. Now,
is it also possible that this is all just
existential post-rationalization, and if
tomorrow there was a live forever pill,
we'd all take it? Yeah, that's possible.
Is it also possible that if we did
that, society be, would be worse off?
Yes. Is it possible that the human
lifespan is the length it is for
sociological reasons, not
just biological reasons? Yes.
So I think these are just all interesting
questions, and I just thought her analysis
really got to something here.
And that discussion has come up
afterwards. I mean, that, I think that
tweet is like a year old. But just
recently, we've been talking about
this over-optimizers. I saw,
uh, Chris Williamson, Modern Wisdom had
a bit where he was like, "Yeah, okay,
maybe we did go a little overboard."
And the triggering thing was
the Diary of a CEO, where the
host was saying something to the
effect of, "I had a glass of wine and
the next three days were ruined."
And that to me, I mean, in his circumstance,
I'm sure that's true. Like, if you have not
drank any alcohol for a very long time and you have
just a little, I could see how it can have effect.
But also there's something
in that that just
triggered a visceral reaction, I think, for a lot of
people, and myself included, where I was like, "Fuck,
man, I should have a glass of wine just right
now, even though I don't usually drink."
And in fact I think the alcohol question
is a good microcosm to zoom in on. So
we've all stopped drinking apparently,
like alcohol sales are way down-
... certainly amongst young people.
And then on the one hand, on the
pure health metrics, whatever, we can
go like, "Oh wow, isn't that great?"
And then I go like, "Yeah, I'm not
so sure it is." Like the social
lubricant that alcohol can provide
may be missed, is missed. I
mean, we are in an absolute
epidemic of loneliness and
misery and depression and
whatever, and a fair amount of it just
probably comes because you're not
interacting enough with other people.
Now, that's before we even talk about
coupling, right? Like way down, people
having a very hard time meeting a spouse.
And- ... a lot of that has moved
over to apps that have all sorts of
negative outcomes and consequences,
right? Like maybe we will
look back, or maybe we already are looking
back and thinking like, "Eh, do you know what?
Maybe getting wasted every once in a while was not the
worst thing in the world." And whether wasted or not,
maybe just having a couple of drinks every
Friday or Saturday when
you're out and about was
part of what helped society
get to where it is. Maybe
the fact that humans have literally
been drinking for whatever it is, like
13,000 years for mending
things, had a social
purpose, and we pull out Chesterton's
fence of our own chagrin, right?
- As you mentioned, in the spirit of
that, so when I traveled across rural
China, I did smoke a little
bit in my early 20s, but I
picked up just for that trip-
- A social connector, right?
- And I drank humongous
amounts, even though I don't
really drink these days, because of the
social thing. It's the way they show love.
And I also ate a shitload of carbs, which-
... I'm usually low carb.
I just like meat. So just
because it's the way they show love.
And actually even, it's in
that society cigarettes,
but in most societies, liquor is a
thing to do together. And it's a bond.
It doesn't, the benefits that that entails
can, in many situations, outweigh
the negative consequences like
long-term for whatever,
however you measure them.
- And this is the myopia of
modernity, that we reduce
things down to like, well, one glass
on this long run study meant that you
had a 0.1% greater risk
of some heart defect.
Yes, but if you didn't live at all,
what's the point? And again, it's also
easy to flip over the other side. Like the
only way to live is to get drunk every
weekend and eat a bunch
of crap and smoke 40
cigarettes a day. No, it's not.
Like it doesn't have to be the
either/or. This is one of the reasons I
stopped wearing my Oura Ring. So I wore
the Oura sleep ring for many years, four
years. And one day I was just like,
"I don't need to know that I
had-" ... "a bad night of sleep."
Like I know. This added,
I don't wanna call it an anxiety, I don't have
a lot of anxiety, but this added just like
reminder-
... that I had a bad night of sleep, what
purpose is it actually playing here?
Why do I need to have all
these stats? Why do I need to
optimize everything? To the point
where, again, after that single
anecdote, you know, from
Diary of a CEO, I was like,
"Fuck, I kind of want the opposite." Like-
I barely drink at all. A glass
of wine once a month maybe.
Like, do you know what? I should start,
uh, just on the weekends, get a glass.
Maybe two. And also, I mean, I've never
been the person to fret about my diet. Um,
this is one of the great
privileges of being
married to, and I'll do a
quick aside here. Don't ever
call a woman in her 40s a wonderful
woman. My wife was so pissed—
... that not only last year did I come on her
birthday, that was bad enough, but that I called her a
wonderful woman on the show,
because that sounded like her
name was Nancy and she was 65—
... in the suburb of Rochester.
So I'm like, I was trying to
play the 50. Like, no, I don't
know, I'm Danish. How would I know? But
that didn't go over well. So I'm gonna say
awesome woman instead.
If you marry an awesome woman who also
not only knows how to cook, but enjoys
it, do you know what? There's a very traditional
division of labor here that has been
quite stable through several ...
tens of thousands of years in
human societies, that perhaps
also wasn't the worst
idea in the world. And I also know there
are plenty of men who like to cook,
and there are women who don't.
But as stereotypes go, eh,
that certainly helped me. Like, I don't
think I would've been able to just
be as relaxed about food if I
didn't eat relatively healthy on
a, on a regular basis. But
the overall point being, just
getting out of that optimization
game without turning into the
opposite. You don't have to be a fat slob
on the couch either. You can move around.
- Yeah. And then the bigger point we're
talking about is the finiteness of life.
- Yes.
- And I agree with you on this.
- This was actually a feature, I built
it into Omarchy. So memento mori.
Remember death.
If you pull down the calendar in Omarchy,
you open it by clicking the clock.
It opens up, and the first funny thing,
I took it off the internet. There's this
account called Year's Progress, and
it, every day it updates, and it just
shows 63% done with 2026. I don't
know if you've seen that one.
So it just fills up. So I built that into the
calendar. So right now it says, "We're 63% done
with 2026." But then if you double-click
that, it'll ask you, "When were you born?
How long do you expect to live?" And
the default is 90. So I put in 1979.
And then right below the line of, like,
how long are we done with the year-
- Oh, that's beautiful.
- ... is a new line that shows how
long are you done with your life.
I think I'm at 62%. I'm like, if you
hover over it, it says, "Memento mori."
- That's beautiful.
- Fair number of people found it morbid, but this
was why it is an Easter egg. It's not, like,
exposed. You gotta click a few things to
get there. I like the reminder. I like the
reminder that time is finite, and
I should make the most of it.
And this is also one of the privileges
of having children. You really
realize that the cliches are all
true. Oh my God, it goes so fast.
And I remember my now 13-year-old
being one, being two.
I was like, "This was just
yesterday." And the reason it's a
cliche is because it's a shared
experience. Cliches are good.
They remind you that you are part of
the human experience, and others
have been here before you.
- I have to ask, you mentioned the
amazing woman and great cook.
- Amazing. Very important to
remember. Not wonderful, amazing.
- Amazing. So there's this...
You talked some shit about
croissants or something. I saw this,
this in a tweet. So is the
Danish croissant somehow better?
- Actually, Danish croissants are not particularly
good. In my opinion, the only place you can find a
half-decent croissant, of
all places, is 7-Eleven,
which is hilarious to me because
7-Eleven in the US is the place where,
at least in Chicago, you'd go to get a
slushie and try to avoid getting murdered.
But in Denmark, 7-Eleven
is this very upscale,
super nice convenience store, and they
just happen to make decent croissants.
And it always baffled me that
I lived in the United States
for 20 freaking years. I have yet to have
a single croissant that's even at the level
of a 7-Eleven croissant in Copenhagen.
That seems improbable.
- Have you understood why?
- No, I've legitimately considered
hiring an investigative
journalist to get to the bottom of this,
because the number of theories I've heard have
been all over the place. It's
the water. It's the butter.
It's the skill. It's the this, it's the that,
it's the other thing. I'm like, none of
it adds up to me. If it's the
butter, can't you just import it? I
thought I saw Danish butter in some
supermarkets over here like Lurpak.
So that can't be it. Can it be the skill? No, it
can't be the skill. There are plenty of French
people and Belgian people, the best
croissant makers in the world, who live in
the US. Like, what is the reason? And
then I get the second thing, which is-
... "No, no, you just haven't gone to
the right place." I've literally gone to
15 of quote unquote- ... "the right
place," and all the croissants were shit.
So before I leave the planet,
I have to get to the bottom of
why the United States cannot make a
proper croissant. And I don't, I'm
not even asking about peak French
croissants, peak Belgian croissants-
... which are the best croissants in the world.
I'm just asking about the 7-Eleven croissant
from Copenhagen. Is that
too much to ask for?
- That's a fascinating mystery.
What, zooming out, what's
your, what's your favorite... This makes me
want to know, what's your favorite meal?
Like, if you, if I gave you a last
meal and were to murder you after.
- It all depends whether it's lunch
or it's dinner. If it's lunch, it-
- It's one meal. What's, what's... I
feel like if you're getting murdered,
it doesn't really matter
if it's lunch or dinner.
- Well, depends on what time of
day you're getting murdered.
- Oh, I see.
- If it's an afternoon
execution, I only get lunch.
- Okay.
- And if I get lunch, it's at Louisiana,
the museum in north of Copenhagen.
I was just there with Jamie two days
ago, and we go there all the time.
The museum is lovely. We
don't go for the museum.
We go for the cafeteria. That
in itself sounds crazy. Like-
- Yeah, it does
- ... you're gonna, you're gonna drive
half an hour to go to a cafeteria.
Well, it just so happens to
be, it is the best lunch
I've probably ever had in my
life. The chef there is just
unbelievably good, and not only is
the food amazing, what's even more
amazing to my system thinking
brain is that at any one time when we were
up there, I think there were probably
200 people waiting for their food.
And our food was delivered in five
minutes. They have a small menu, and
clearly they make it in bulk, and it's
unbelievably delicious.
- Just a cafeteria at a museum?
- It's a cafeteria at a museum that happens to have
the best lunch I've ever had anywhere in my life.
- What kind of food are we talking
about? What kind of lunch food?
- It's, like, Nordic cuisine, so it's,
it's... A funny thing is the menu, when I
look at it, I was like, "Do you know what?
If I saw this menu- As a kid, I'd go like,
"I'm not eating here."
It's like, I don't know-
- This is pretty fancy
- ... root free fruit and- ... and onions-
... and all sorts of healthy stuff. That sounds
disgusting. And then you sit down and eat it,
and the angels sing. But it's even more
particular than that. It's the butter.
The whipped butter that they have there,
the best butter anywhere in the world.
- I think that has to be connected
to the croissant mystery too.
- There must be some connection.
But literally- ... even in
Paris, I've never had whipped
butter that tastes as
delicious as the butter does at
Louisiana in Copenhagen. Literally,
I would drive 30 minutes-
... to have bread and butter
at the cafeteria in Louisiana.
- Well, how'd you discover that? Just
one day you went to the museum and-
- I think we just went to the museum-
- And you tried a whole dish.
- ... and we had the lunch,
and we were like...
- This is weird.
- This is rivaling the best tasting
restaurants- ... I've ever been to in my
life, and I've gone to
Noma a couple of times and
tried what there is to try,
and this is right up there.
- All right. What about dinner, since you
mentioned? Is it something different
that you have to think-
- Well, I think there's a
lot of good options in
Copenhagen, but actually I'll pick
a place in Spain. So there is
this place in Marbella called
Puente Romano. It's a hotel,
and down by the beach, they have this
beach restaurant with fresh seafood.
Unbelievably delicious.
I'm trying to remember what it's called,
but yeah, if you look it up, the beach
seafood place at Puente
Romano is incredible.
- How much of great food is, like, the
place and the person you're with,
right? Or the, or the experience
when you first are there?
- I mean, the ambiance certainly helps,
but I think my taste buds are also just-
- Okay, that-
- ... in tune for-
- So it's legit.
- ... flavors
- ... it is just good food.
- It's just really good food.
Because for ex- that cafeteria, it
is, there's a lot of people. Like,
I wouldn't rate it as like, oh my God, this
is just a place I want to sit for two hours.
But the food is so delicious.
- That's one of the things I'm, in traveling
across the country, I'm realizing
to sample without bias, just try things.
'Cause you might, I guess you might
just be surprised. Maybe I'll find your
croissant. All right, we've talked
about mortality. Talked about food.
- Settled end of life.
- What do you thousand years from now, what
do you think is the future of humans,
human civilization? You
think we're gonna make it?
- A thousand years from now? Man, I'm having
trouble predicting 12 months from now.
- I know.
- A thousand?
- You think we got a shot?
- Oh, I'm gonna bet on optimism. I'm
gonna bet on a multi-planetary
species. I'm gonna bet that Elon gets
that rocket to Mars, and we figure
out how to bend space-time and discover
some wormholes or, or something.
- Once we do, do you think,
you think all humans on Earth will
die once or twice and be repopulated
After we get a good backup going?
- I mean, that was actually one of my
favorite episodes of Black Mirror, the
one where they get uploaded
to the 1980s sea town
somewhere. And I just
thought like, wow, this is
both such a dark moment, yet also so
beautiful in the shared recognition that,
like, the '80s were actually kind of amazing.
Like, I don't have a lot of
nostalgia for many moments, but I do
have nostalgia for the '80s.
- But-
- And they say something about, like, whatever
place and time you were in, the music you were
listening to when you were 12 or-
... or 14, 15, something like that, that's
what's gonna stick with you. Like, no, I was
only, I got to be 10 in the '80s. So
this was my early childhood, and I
still have an unbelievably
fond affiliation with
the '80s. So if I'm gonna
be uploaded to the sky-
- You want it to be the '80s?
- ... I'm doing the '80s.
- Wow. I don't think I've actually
ever heard anyone say that.
Usually it's '70s or '90s.
- Oh, and the-
- Because the '80s is a-
- I really don't like the '90s.
Can we talk about this?
- No, I'm done. Not done.
- To me, this was the great
turning point of nihilism.
That both the music,
the genre, the fashion-
... everything turned from,
like, this glamour, the
pop, the optimism, even the yuppies and
everything- ... to grunge and Nirvana.
And even though, I mean, I like the music,
I don't like the ethics. I don't like-
... the morals. I don't like
any of the underpinnings to it.
There was just such a defeatism to it-
... that in retrospect, I look back
upon it, if I'm gonna get reinserted
into the matrix, it's gonna be the '80s.
- That was full of optimism and fun-
- Yes
- ... and colors.
- Yes. I remember having these orange pants-
... with, like, white dots on
them. That was just a normal
thing kids could wear in the '80s.
I've never fucking seen that today. Or I
mean, even in the '90s, it all turned just,
like, Seattle gray. Great regression.
- So the Nietzschean, you know,
this idea of eternal recurrence.
If you do a Groundhog Day and you live
forever, you want it to be in the orange pants
with the white dots in the '80s.
- Maybe I'm gonna skip
the orange pants, but-
- No
- ... I'm definitely picking the '80s.
- You said it.
All right, DHH. Thank you so much for everything
you do. Thank you for being an inspiration to
all of us, for building cool shit in the
world, and thank you for talking today.
- Anytime. Thank you, Lex,
again for having me.
- Yeah. Thanks for listening to this conversation
with DHH. To support this podcast, please check
out our sponsors in the description,
where you can also find links to
contact me, ask questions,
give feedback, and so on. And
now, let me leave you with some
words from Ralph Waldo Emerson.
"Once you make a decision, the
universe conspires to make it happen."
Thank you for listening, and
hope to see you next time.